<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Instructions how to play at billiards, trucks, bowls, and chess. Together with all manner of games either on cards, or dice. To which is added the arts and mysteries of riding, racing, archery, and cock-fighting.</title>
            <author>Cotton, Charles, 1630-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6386A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R174281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299015</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179790</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179790)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2803:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Instructions how to play at billiards, trucks, bowls, and chess. Together with all manner of games either on cards, or dice. To which is added the arts and mysteries of riding, racing, archery, and cock-fighting.</title>
                  <author>Cotton, Charles, 1630-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 175 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added illustrated t.p.: The compleate gamster. Printed for Hen:Brome.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to C. Cotton. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Games --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gambling --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Games --  Rules --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Social life and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>INSTRUCTIONS How to Play at <hi>Billiards, Trucks, Bowls,</hi> and <hi>Cheſs.</hi> Together wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h all manner of GAMES Either on <hi>Cards,</hi> or <hi>Dice.</hi> To which is added, the ARTS and MYSTERIES OF <hi>Riding, Racing, Archery,</hi> and <hi>Cock-fighting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Charles Brome,</hi> at the <hi>Gun</hi> at the Weſt End of <hi>S. Pauls.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:3"/>
            <head>The Explanation of the Frontiſpiece.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BIlliards <hi>from</hi> Spain <hi>at firſt deriv'd its name,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Both an ingenious, and a cleanly Game.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One</hi> Gameſter <hi>leads (the Table green as graſs)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And each like</hi> Warriers <hi>ſtrive to gain the</hi> Paſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But in the conteſt, e're the</hi> Paſs <hi>be won,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hazzards <hi>are many into which they run.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus while we play on this</hi> Terreſtrial Stage,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing but</hi> Hazzard <hi>doth attend each age.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Next here are</hi> Hazzards <hi>play'd another way,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By Box and Dice; 'tis</hi> Hazzard <hi>is the Play.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The</hi> Bully-Rock <hi>with mangy fiſt, and Pox,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſtles ſome out, and then takes up the Box.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He throws the</hi> Main, <hi>and crys, Who comes at</hi> Seven?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus with a</hi> dry fiſt nicks <hi>it with</hi> Eleven.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If out, he raps out Oaths I dare not tell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hot, piping out, and newly come from Hell.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Old-Nick <hi>o're-hearing, by a</hi> Palming-trick</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Secures the</hi> Gameſter; <hi>thus the</hi> Nicker's nickt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now t'</hi> Iriſh, <hi>or</hi> Back-Gammoners <hi>we come,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who wiſh their money, with their men ſafe home;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But as in War, ſo in this ſubtle Play,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſtragling men are ta'ne up by the way.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By entring then, one reinforceth more,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It may be to be loſt, as thoſe before.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By</hi> Topping, Knapping, <hi>and foul play ſome win;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But thoſe are loſers, who ſo gain by ſin.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>After theſe three the</hi> Cock-pit <hi>claims a name;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A ſport gentile, and call'd a</hi> Royal Game.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now ſee the</hi> Gallants <hi>crowd about the</hi> Pit,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And moſt are ſtockt with Money more than Wit;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Elſe ſure they would not, with ſo great a ſtir,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lay ten to one on a</hi> Cocks <hi>faithleſs Spur.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laſtly, obſerve the Women with what grace</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They ſit, and look their Partners in the face.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who from their eyes ſhoot</hi> Cupids <hi>fiery Darts;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thus make them loſe at once their Game and Hearts.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Their white ſoft hands, (when e're the Cards they cut)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Make the men wiſh to change the Game to</hi> Putt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Women knew their thoughts, then cry'd, Enough,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let's leave off</hi> Whiſt, <hi>and go to</hi> Putt, <hi>or</hi> Ruff.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ladies, don't truſt your ſecrets in that hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who can't their own (to their great grief) command.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For this I will aſſure you, if you do,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In time you'l loſe your</hi> Ruff <hi>and</hi> Honour <hi>too.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:4"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>THE COMPLEATE GAMSTER.</head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraving of men playing billiards</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraving of men playing backgammon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraving of men playing cards</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraving of cock fighting match</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraving of man and woman playing cards</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Printed for Hen: Brome</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:5"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Was once reſolv'd to have let this enſuing Treatiſe to have ſtept naked into the World, without ſo much as the leaſt rag of an Epiſtle to defend it a little from the cold welcom it may meet with in its travails; but knowing that not only cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom expects but neceſſity requires it, give me leave to ſhow you the motives indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to this preſent publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>It is not (I'le aſſure you) any private intereſt of my own that caus'd me to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture
<pb facs="tcp:179790:6"/>on this ſubject, but the delight &amp; benefit of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry individual perſon; Delight to ſuch who will paſs away their ſpare minuts in harmleſs recreation if not abus'd; and Profit to all, who by inſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all manner of <hi>Games</hi> may obſerve the cheats and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, &amp; ſo be arm'd againſt the injuries may accrue thereby.</p>
            <p>Certainly there is no man ſo ſevere to deny the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Recreation; There was never any Stoick found ſo cruel, either to himſelf, or nature, but at ſome time or
<pb facs="tcp:179790:6"/>other he would unbend his mind, and give it liberty to ſtray into ſome more pleaſant walks, than the miry heavy ways of his own ſowr, will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reſolutions. You may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Heathen Sages of the firſt world founded with their Laws their Feaſts, with their Labours their Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks, with their Warfare their Triumphs. Nay at this day the ſevereſt <hi>Dionyſian-Pedagogue</hi> will give his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars their Play-days, &amp; Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings up with a <hi>Horum miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere laborum, feſſum quies pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum
<pb facs="tcp:179790:7"/>juvat.</hi> And the moſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous Maſters will tye their ſervants but to certain hours; every toyl exacting as <hi>ex offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio,</hi> or out of duty ſome time for Recreation. I my ſelf have obſerved in the courſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men of exceeding ſtrict lives and converſation, to whom although ſeverity of profeſſion, infirmity of body, extremity of age, or ſuch like, have taken away all <hi>actual</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation, yet have their minds begot unto themſelves ſome habits or cuſtoms of delight, which have in as large mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:179790:7"/>given them contentment whether they were their own, or borrowed, as if they had been the ſole actors of the ſame. Furthermore, Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not only lawful but neceſſary:
<q>
                  <l>Interpone tuis interdum gaudia curis,</l>
                  <l>Ut poſſis animo quemvis ſufferre laborem.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So intermix your care with joy, you may</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lighten your labour by a little play.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now what Recreation this ſhould be I cannot preſcribe, nor is it requiſite to confine any to one ſort of pleaſure, ſince herein Nature taketh to her ſelf an eſpecial Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, for what to one is moſt pleaſant, to another is moſt
<pb facs="tcp:179790:8"/>offenſive; Some ſeeking to ſatisfie the Mind, ſome the Body, and others both in a joint motion. To this end I have laid before you what variety of Paſtimes I could collect for the preſent, leaving the reſt (as you like theſe) to be ſuppli'd hereafter. Miſtake me not, it is not my intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to make Gameſters by this Collection, but to inform all in part how to avoid being cheated by them: If I am im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect in my diſcoveries, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to my being no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Gameſter, and the hatred
<pb facs="tcp:179790:8"/>I bear that Helliſh ſociety; by whom I know I ſhall be laught at, and with whom if I ſhould converſe, I might ſooner by my ſtudy come to be Nature's Secretary, and unriddle all her <hi>Arcana</hi>'s, than collect from them any new unpractiſed ſecret, by which they bubble ignorant credulity, and purchaſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and good apparel with everlaſting ſhame and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy.</p>
            <p>To conclude, let me ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you, if you play (when your buſineſs will permit) let
<pb facs="tcp:179790:9"/>not a covetous deſire of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning another's money en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you to the loſing your own; which will not only diſturb your mind, but by the diſreputation of being a Gameſter, if you loſe not your eſtate, you will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſe your credit and good name, than which there is nothing more valuable. Thus hoping you will be thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd, and will withal excuſe my Errors, I ſhall ever ſtudy how to ſerve you, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe my ſelf a well-willer to all men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:179790:9"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF Gaming in general; or an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary deſcribed.</hi> Page 1.</item>
               <item>Ch. 1. <hi>Of</hi> Billiards. p. 17</item>
               <item>Ch. 2. <hi>Of</hi> Trucks. p. 28</item>
               <item>Ch. 3. <hi>Of</hi> Bowling. p. 34</item>
               <item>Ch. 4. <hi>Of a Game at</hi> Cheſs. p. 36</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Principal Games at Cards.</head>
               <item>Ch. 5. <hi>Of</hi> Picket. p. 56</item>
               <item>Ch. 6. <hi>The Game at</hi> Gleek. p. 64</item>
               <item>Ch. 7. L'Ombre, <hi>a Spaniſh Game.</hi> p. 69</item>
               <item>Ch. 8. <hi>The Game at</hi> Cribbidge. p. 75</item>
               <item>Ch. 9. <hi>A Game at</hi> All-Fours. p. 79</item>
               <item>Ch. 10. <hi>Engliſh Ruff and Honours, and Whist.</hi> p. 81</item>
               <item>Ch. 11. French-Ruff. p. 86</item>
               <item>Ch. 12. Five-Cards. p. 87</item>
               <item>Ch. 13. <hi>Of a Game called</hi> Coſtly Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. p. 88</item>
               <item>Ch. 14. Bone-Ace. p. 91</item>
               <item>Ch. 15. <hi>Of</hi> Put <hi>and the</hi> High-Game. p. 92</item>
               <item>Ch. 16. Wit <hi>and</hi> Reaſon, <hi>a Game ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> p. 97</item>
               <item>Ch. 17. <hi>A Paſtime called,</hi> The Art of Memory. p. 99</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:179790:10"/>
               <item>Ch. 18. <hi>A Game called</hi> Plain-dealing. p. 100</item>
               <item>Ch. 19. <hi>A Game called</hi> Queen Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reen. p. 101</item>
               <item>Ch. 20. Lanterloo. ibid.</item>
               <item>Ch. 21. <hi>A Game called</hi> Penneech. p. 104</item>
               <item>Ch. 22. Poſt <hi>and</hi> Pair. p. 106</item>
               <item>Ch. 23. Bankafalet. p. 107</item>
               <item>Ch. 24. Beaſt. p. 108</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Games within the Tables.</head>
               <item>Ch. 25. <hi>Of</hi> Iriſh. p. 109</item>
               <item>Ch. 26. <hi>Of</hi> Back-Gammon. p. 110</item>
               <item>Ch. 27. <hi>Of</hi> Tick-tack. p. 112</item>
               <item>Ch. 28. Dubblets. p. 115</item>
               <item>Ch. 29. Sice-Ace. p. 116</item>
               <item>Ch. 30. Ketch-Dolt. ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Games without the Tables.</head>
               <item>Ch. 31. <hi>Of</hi> Inn <hi>and</hi> Inn. p. 117</item>
               <item>Ch. 32. <hi>Of</hi> Paſſage. p. 119</item>
               <item>Ch. 33. <hi>Of</hi> Hazzard. p. 120</item>
               <item>Ch. 34. <hi>The Art and Myſtery of</hi> Riding, <hi>Whether the Great Horſe or any other.</hi> p. 124</item>
               <item>Ch. 35. <hi>Of</hi> Racing. p. 141</item>
               <item>Ch. 36. <hi>Of</hi> Archery. p. 149</item>
               <item>Ch. 37. <hi>Of</hi> Cock-fighting. p. 152</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179790:10"/>
            <head>Of <hi>Gaming</hi> in General, or an Ordinary deſcribed.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Aming</hi> is an enchanting <hi>witchery,</hi> gotten betwixt <hi>Idleneſs</hi> and <hi>Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice:</hi> An itching Diſeaſe, that makes ſome ſcratch the Head, whilſt others, as if they were bitten by a <hi>Tarantula,</hi> are laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves to death: Or laſtly, it is a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytical diſtemper, which ſeizing the arm the man cannot chuſe but ſhake his elbow. It hath this ill property above all other Vices, that it ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a Man incapable of proſecuting any ſerious action, and makes him always unſatisfied with his own condition; he is either lifted up to the top of mad joy with ſucceſs, or plung'd to the bottom of deſpair by misfortune, always in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, always in a ſtorm; this minute the Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's countenance is ſo ſerene and calm, that one would think nothing could diſturb it, and the next minute ſo ſtormy and tempeſtuous that it threatens deſtruction to it ſelf and others; and as he is tranſported with joy when he wins, ſo loſing he is toſt upon the billows of a high ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling paſſion, till he hath loſt ſight both of ſenſe and reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:179790:11"/>
            <p>I have ſeen ſome Dogs bite the ſtones which Boys have thrown at them, not regarding whence they were flung; ſo I have ſeen a loſing Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter greedily gnawing the innocent Box, and ſometimes tearing it to pieces as an acceſſary to his <hi>throwing</hi> out; nor muſt the Dice go unpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for not running his <hi>chance,</hi> and therefore in rage are thrown on the ground to be kickt to and fro by every body; and at laſt lookt upon no other than the fit companions of every ſaucy <hi>Skip-jack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then freſh Dice are called for, as thinking they will prove more kind than the former, or as if they believed that ſome were good natur'd, others bad, and that every Bale produced a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent diſpoſition. If theſe run croſs too, the Box-keeper ſhall not go without a horrid execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if for nothing elſe but that he lookt ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the caſt, it may be conceiving that his very eyes were capable of making them turn to his diſadvantage. This reſtleſs man (the miſerable Gameſter) is the proper ſubject of every man's pity. Reſtleſs I call him, becauſe (ſuch is the itch of play) either winning or loſing he can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſt ſatisfied; if he wins he thinks to win more, if he loſes he hopes to recover: To this Man's condition the ſaying of <hi>Hannibal</hi> to <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus</hi> may be fitly applied, that <hi>nec bonam, nec malam fortunam ferre poteſt,</hi> he could not be quiet either Conqueror or Conquered. Thus have I heard of ſome who with Five Pounds
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179790:11"/>have won Four Hundred Pounds in one Night, and the next Night have loſt it to a ſum not half ſo much; others who have loſt their eſtates and won them again with addition, yet could not be quiet till they loſt them irrecoverably.</p>
            <p>And therefore fitly was that queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, <hi>Whether men in Ships at Sea were to be accounted among the living or the dead, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were but few inches betwixt them and drowning.</hi> The ſame <hi>quaere</hi> may be made of great <hi>Gameſters,</hi> though their eſtates be never ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, Whether they are to be eſteemed poor or rich, ſince there are but few <hi>Caſts</hi> at <hi>Dice</hi> betwixt a rich man (in that circumſtance) and a beggar.</p>
            <p>Now ſince ſpeculation will not be convincing, unleſs we ſhew ſomewhat of the modern pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; we muſt therefore lay our <hi>Scene</hi> at an <hi>Ordinary,</hi> and proceed to action: Where note, an <hi>Ordinary</hi> is a handſome houſe, where every day, about the hour of twelve, a good Dinner is prepared by way of <hi>Ordinary,</hi> compoſed of variety of diſhes, in ſeaſon, well dreſt, with all other accommodations fit for that purpoſe, whereby many Gentlemen of great Eſtates and good repute, make this place their reſort, who after Dinner play a while for recreation, both moderately and commonly, without deſerving reproof: But here is the miſchief, the beſt Wheat will have Tares growing amongſt it, Rooks and Daws will ſometimes be in the company of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179790:12"/>nor can real gentlemen now adays ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude themſelves from the ſociety of ſuch as are pretendedly ſo, but that they oftentimes mix company, being much of the ſame colour and feather, and by the eye undiſtinguiſhable.</p>
            <p>It is reported of the <hi>Polypus</hi> (a Fiſh), that it will conform it ſelf to the colour of what is neareſt, for ſecurity and advantage: And ſo do theſe pretended Gentlemen attire themſelves in what is both gentile and faſhionable, that under that diſguiſe they may with more facility riggle themſelves into the ſociety of ſuch worthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, out of whom they intend to ſqueeze ſome ſums of moneys by <hi>Cards, Dice,</hi> or otherways.</p>
            <p>Theſe Rooks can do little harm in the day time at an <hi>Ordinary,</hi> being forc'd to play upon the <hi>Square,</hi> although now and then they make an advantage, when the <hi>Box-keeper goes with him,</hi> and then the Knave and Raſcal will violate his truſt for profit, and lend him (when he ſees good) a <hi>Tickler</hi> ſhall do his buſineſs; but if diſcovered, the Box-keeper ought to be ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kickt for his pains: Such practices, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Box-keepers connivances, are ſo much us'd of late, that there is nothing near that fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> play in an <hi>Ordinary,</hi> as formerly.</p>
            <p>The day being ſhut in, you may properly compare this place to thoſe Countries which ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> far in the North, where it is as clear at midnigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as at noon-day: And though it is a houſe of Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet you cannot call it a houſe of Darkneſs, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:179790:12"/>the Candles never go out till morning, unleſs the ſudden fury of a loſing Gameſter make them extinct.</p>
            <p>This is the time (when ravenous beaſts uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeek their prey) wherein comes ſhoals of <hi>Huffs, Hectors, Setters, Gilts, Pads, Biters, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, Lifters, Filers, Budgies, Droppers, Croſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, &amp;c.</hi> and theſe may all paſs under the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and common appellation of <hi>Rooks.</hi> And in this particular, an <hi>Ordinary</hi> ſerves as a <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi> for <hi>Tyburn;</hi> for if any one will put himſelf to the trouble of obſervation, he ſhall find, that there is ſeldom a Year wherein there are not ſome of this Gang hang as <hi>precious Jewels</hi> in the ear of <hi>Tyburn:</hi> Look back and you will find a great many gone already, God knows how many are to follow.</p>
            <p>Theſe Rooks are in continual motion, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from one Table to another, till they can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſome unexperienc'd young Gentleman, Caſheer or Apprentice, that is come to this <hi>School of Virtue,</hi> being unskill'd in the quib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and devices there practiſed; theſe they call <hi>Lambs,</hi> or <hi>Colls:</hi> Then do the <hi>Rooks</hi> (more properly called <hi>Wolves</hi>) ſtrive who ſhall faſten on him firſt, following him cloſe, and engaging him in ſome advantageous Bets, and at length worries him, that is, gets all his money, and then the <hi>Rooks</hi> (Rogues I ſhould have ſaid) laugh and grin, ſaying, <hi>the Lamb is bitten.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:179790:13"/>
            <p>Some of theſe <hi>Rooks</hi> will be very importunate to borrow money of you without any intention to pay you; or to go with you ſeven to twelve half a Crown or more, whereby without a very great chance (ten to one or more) he is ſure to win: If you are ſenſible hereof, and refuſe his propoſition, they will take it ſo ill, that if you have not an eſpecial care they will pick your pocket, nim your gold or ſilver buttons off your Cloak or Coat; or it may be draw your ſilver-hilted Sword out of your Belt without diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, eſpecially if you are eager upon your Caſt, which is done thus; the ſilver buttons are ſtrung, or run upon Cats guts faſtned at the upper and nether end; now by ripping both ends very ingeniouſly (as they call it) give it the gentile pull, and ſo rub off with the buttons; and if your Cloak be looſe 'tis ten to one they have it.</p>
            <p>But that which will moſt provoke (in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) any Man's rage to a juſt ſatisfaction, is their throwing many times at a good Sum with a <hi>dry fiſt</hi> (as they call it,) that is, if they <hi>nick</hi> you, 'tis theirs; if they loſe, they owe you ſo much with many other quillets: ſome I have known ſo abominably impudent, that they would ſnatch up the Stakes, and thereupon inſtantly draw, ſaying, if you will have your money you muſt fight for it; for he is a Gentleman and will not want: however if you will be patient, he will pay you another time; if you are ſo tame to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179790:13"/>take this, go no more to the Ordinary; for then the whole Gang will be ever and anon watching an opportunity to make a <hi>Mouth</hi> of you in the like nature. If you nick them, 'tis odds, if they wait not your coming out at night and beat you: I could produce you an hundred examples in this kind, but they will rarely adventure on the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, unleſs they are backt with ſome <hi>Bully-Huffs,</hi> and <hi>Bully-Rocks,</hi> with others whoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are as deſperate as their own. We need no other teſtimony to confirm the danger of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociating with theſe Anthropo-phagi or Man-eaters, than <hi>Lincolns</hi>-Inn-Fields whilſt <hi>Speerings Ordinary</hi> was kept in Bell-yard, and that you need not want a pair of Witneſſes for the proof there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, take in alſo <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is the Houſe it ſelf to be exempted, every night almoſt ſome one or other, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heated with Wine, or made cholerick with the loſs of his Money, raiſes a quarrel, ſwords are drawn, box and candleſticks thrown at one anothers head, Tables overthrown, and all the Houſe in ſuch a Garboyl, that it is the perfect Type of Hell. Happy is the Man now that can make the frame of a Table or Chimney-corner his Sanctuary; and if any are ſo fortunate to get to the Stair-head, they will rather hazard the breaking of their own necks than have their Souls puſht out of their Bodies in the dark by they know not whom.</p>
            <p>I once obſerved one of the <hi>Deſperadoes</hi> of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179790:14"/>Town (being half drunk) to preſs a Gentleman very much (at play) to lend him a Crown, the Gentleman refus'd him ſeveral times, yet ſtill the Borrower perſiſted, and holding his Head ſomewhat too near the <hi>Caſters</hi> elbow, it chanced to hit his noſe, the other thinking it to be affront enough to be denied the loan of Money without this ſlight touch of the noſe, drew, and ſtepping back (unawares to the Gentleman) made a full paſs at him, intending to have run him through the body; but his drunkenneſs miſguided his hand, ſo that he ran him only through the arm: this put the Houſe into ſo great a confuſion and fright, that ſome fled thinking the Gentleman ſlain. This wicked Miſcreant thought not this ſufficient, but tripping up his heels, pinn'd him as he thought to the floor; and after this, takes the Gentlemans ſilver ſword, leaving his in the wound, and with a <hi>Grand-Jury</hi> of <hi>Dammees</hi> (which may hereafter find him guilty at the <hi>Great Tribunal</hi>) bid all ſtand off if they lov'd their lives, and ſo went clear off with ſword and liberty; but was notwithſtanding (the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman recovering) compel'd to make what ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction he was capable of making, beſides a long impriſonment; and was not long abroad before he was apprehended for <hi>Burglary,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, condemned, and juſtly executed.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Fatebere tandem</l>
               <l>Nec Surdum, nec Tireſſam quenquam eſſe Deorum.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:179790:14"/>
            <p>But to proceed on as to play: late at Night when the Company grows thin, and your eyes dim with watching, falſe Dice are frequently put upon the ignorant, or they are otherwiſe cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Topping, Slurring, Stabbing,</hi> &amp;c. and if you be not careful and vigilant, the Box-keeper ſhall ſcore you up double or treble Boxes, and though you have loſt your money, dun you as ſeverely for it, as if it were the juſteſt debt in the World.</p>
            <p>The more ſubtile and gentiler ſort of <hi>Rooks</hi> (as aforeſaid) you ſhall not diſtinguiſh by their outward demeanor from perſons of condition; theſe will ſit by a whole Evening, and obſerve who wins; if the <hi>Winner</hi> be <hi>bubbleable,</hi> they will inſinuate themſelves into his company by applauding his ſucceſs, adviſing him to leave off whilſt he is well; and laſtly, by civilly inviting him to drink a glaſs of Wine, where having well warm'd themſelves to make him more than half drunk they wheadle him in to play; to which if he condeſcend he ſhall quickly have no money left him in his Pocket, unleſs perchance a Crown the Rooking-winner lent him in courteſie to bear his charges homewards.</p>
            <p>This they do by falſe Dice, as High-Fullams 4, 5, 6. Low-Fullams 1, 2, 3. By Briſtle-Dice, which are fitted for their purpoſe by ſticking a Hogs-briſtle ſo in the corners, or otherwiſe in the Dice, that they ſhall run high or low as they pleaſe; this briſtle muſt be ſtrong and ſhort, by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:179790:15"/>which means the briſtle bending, it will not lie on that ſide, but will be tript over; and this is the neweſt way of making a high or low <hi>Fullam:</hi> the old ways are by drilling them and loading them with Quick-ſilver; but that cheat may be eaſily diſcovered by their weight, or holding two corners between your forefinger and thumb, if holding them ſo gently between your fingers they turn, you may then conclude them falſe; or you may try their falſhood otherwiſe by breaking or ſplitting them: others have made them by filing and rounding; but all theſe ways fall ſhort of the Art of thoſe who make them: ſome whereof are ſo admirably skilful in making a Bale of Dice to run what you would have them, that your Gameſters think they never give e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for their purchaſe if they prove right. They are ſold in many places about the Town; price current (by the help of a friend) eight ſhillings, whereas an ordinary Bale is ſold for ſix pence; for my part I ſhall tell you plainly, I would have thoſe Bales of falſe Dice to be ſold at the price of the Ears of ſuch deſtructive Knaves that made them.</p>
            <p>Another way the Rook hath to cheat, is firſt by <hi>Palming,</hi> that is, he puts one Dye into the Box, and keeps the other in the hollow of his little finger, which noting what is uppermoſt when he takes him up, the ſame ſhall be when he throws the other Dye, which runs doubtfully any caſt. Obſerve this, that the bottom and top
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:179790:15"/>of all Dice are ſeven, ſo that if it be 4 above, it muſt be a 3 at bottom; ſo 5 and 2. 6 and 1. Secondly, by <hi>Topping,</hi> and that is when they take up both Dice and ſeem to put them in the Box, and ſhaking the Box you would think them both there, by reaſon of the ratling occaſioned with the ſcrewing of the Box, whereas one of them is at the top of the Box between his two forefingers, or ſecur'd by thruſting a forefinger into the Box. Thirdly, by <hi>Slurring,</hi> that is, by taking up your Dice as you will have them ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageouſly lie in your hand, placing the one a top the other, not caring if the uppermoſt run a Mill-ſtone (as they uſe to ſay) if the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt run without turning, and therefore a ſmooth table is altogether requiſite for this purpoſe; on a rugged rough board it is a hard matter to be done, whereas on a ſmooth table (the beſt are rub'd over with Bees-wax to fill up all chinks and creviſes) it is uſual for ſome to ſlur a Dye two yards or more without turning. Fourthly, by <hi>Knapping,</hi> that is, when you ſtrike a Dye dead that it ſhall not ſtir, this is beſt done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Tables; where note there is no ſecuring but of one Dye, although there are ſome who boaſt of ſecuring both: I have ſeen ſome ſo dexterous at Knapping, that they have done it through the handle of a quart Pot, or over a Candle and Candleſtick: but that which I moſt admired, was throwing through the ſame leſs than Ames Ace with two Dice upon a Groat
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:179790:16"/>held in the left hand on the one ſide of the handle a foot diſtance, and the Dice thrown with the right hand on the other.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, by <hi>Stabbing,</hi> that is, having a Smooth Box, and ſmall in the bottom, you drop in both your Dice in ſuch manner as you would have them ſticking therein by reaſon of its narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Dice lying one upon another; ſo that turning up the Box, the Dice never tumble; if a ſmooth Box, if true, but little; by which means you have bottoms according to the tops you put in; For example, if you put in your Dice ſo that two fives or two fours lie a top, you have in the bottom turn'd up two two's, or two treys; ſo if ſix and an Ace a top, a Six and an Ace at bottom.</p>
            <p>Now if the Gentleman be paſt that <hi>Claſſis</hi> of Ignoramuſſes, then they effect their purpoſe by Croſs-byting, or ſome other dexterity, of which they have all variety imaginable. A friend of mine wondring at the many ſlights a noted Gameſter had to deceive, and how neatly and undiſcoverably he managed his tricks, wondring withall he could not do the like himſelf, ſince he had the ſame Theory of them all, and knew how they were done; O young man, replyed the Gameſter, there is nothing to be attain'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pains; wherefore had you been as laborious as my ſelf in the practice hereof, and had ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at it as many cold winter mornings in your ſhirt as I have done in mine, undoubtedly you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:179790:16"/>would have arrived at the ſame perfection.</p>
            <p>Here you muſt obſerve, that if theſe <hi>Rooks</hi> think they have met with a ſure Bubble, they will purpoſely loſe ſome ſmall ſum at firſt, that they may engage him the more freely to bleed (as they call it) which may be at the ſecond, if not beware of the third meeting, which under the notion of being very merry with wine and good cheer, they will make him pay for the roaſt.</p>
            <p>Conſider the further inconveniences of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as they are rank'd under theſe Heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if the Houſe find you free to the Box and a conſtant <hi>Caſter,</hi> you ſhall be treated with Suppers at night, and a Cawdle in the morning, and have the honour to be ſtiled a Lover of the Houſe, whilſt your money laſts, which certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cannot be long; for here you ſhall be quickly deſtroy'd under pretence of kindneſs, as Men were by the <hi>Lamiae</hi> of old; which you may eaſily gather if from no other conſideration than this; that I have ſeen three perſons ſit down at twelve penny <hi>In and In,</hi> and each draw forty ſhillings a piece in leſs than three hours, the Box hath had three pound, and all the three Gameſters have been loſers.</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider how many perſons have been ruined by play, I could nominate a great many, ſome who have had great eſtates have loſt them, others having good employments have been forced to deſert them and hide themſelves
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:179790:17"/>from their Creditors in ſome foreign Plantation by reaſon of thoſe great debts they had contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted through Play.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this courſe of life ſhall make you liable to ſo many affronts and manifold vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as in time may breed diſtraction. Thus a young fellow not many years ſince, had by ſtrange fortune run up a very ſmall ſum to a thouſand pounds, and thereupon put himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a garb accordingly; but not knowing when he was well, fell to play again, fortune turn'd, he loſt all, ran mad, and ſo died.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, is it not extreme folly for a man that hath a competent eſtate, to play whether he or another man ſhall enjoy it, and if his eſtate be ſmall, then to hazard even the loſs of that, and reduce himſelf to abſolute beggery; I think it madneſs in the higheſt degree. Beſides, it hath been generally obſerved that the loſs of one hundred pounds ſhall do you more prejudice in diſquieting your mind, than the gain of two hundred pounds ſhall do you good, were you ſure to keep it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, conſider not only your loſs of time which is invaluable, <hi>Nulla major est jactura quam temporis amiſſio,</hi> but the damage alſo the very watching brings to your health, and in particular to the eyes, confirmed by this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Allia, Vina, Venus, Fumus, Faba, Lumen &amp; Ignis,</l>
               <l>Iſta nocent oculis, ſed vigilare magis.</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:179790:17"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Garlick, Wine, Women, Smoak, Beans, Fire and Light</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Do hurt the Eyes, but watching more the ſight.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this Character with a peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential Sonnet, written by a Lord (a great Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter a little before his death) which was in the Year 1580.</p>
            <q>
               <l>By loſs in play men oft forget</l>
               <l>The duty they do owe</l>
               <l>To him that did beſtow the ſame,</l>
               <l>And thouſand Millions moe.</l>
               <l>I loath to hear them ſwear and stare</l>
               <l>When they the <hi>Main</hi> have loſt;</l>
               <l>Forgetting all the <hi>Byes</hi> that were</l>
               <l>With God and Holy Ghost:</l>
               <l>By <hi>wounds</hi> and <hi>nails</hi> they think to win,</l>
               <l>But truly 'tis not ſo;</l>
               <l>For all their frets and fumes in ſin</l>
               <l>They monileſs muſt go.</l>
               <l>There is no Wight that us'd it more</l>
               <l>Than he who wrote this Verſe,</l>
               <l>Who cries <hi>peccavi</hi> now therefore,</l>
               <l>His Oaths his heart do pierce;</l>
               <l>Therefore example take by me</l>
               <l>That curſe the luckleſs time,</l>
               <l>That ever <hi>Dice</hi> mine eyes did ſee,</l>
               <l>Which bred in me this crime.</l>
               <l>Lord pardon me for what is paſt,</l>
               <l>I will offend no more,</l>
               <l>In this moſt vile and ſinful cast</l>
               <l>Which I will still abhor.</l>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:179790:18"/>
               <head>The Character of a Gameſter.</head>
               <p>SOme ſay he was born with Cards in his hands, others that he will die ſo; but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is all his life, and whether he ſleeps or wakes he thinks of nothing elſe. He ſpeaks the language of the Game he plays at, better than the language of his Country; and can leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a ſoleciſm in that than this: he knows no Judge but the Groom-porter, no Law but that of the Game, at which he is ſo expert, all appeal to him, as ſubordinate Judges to the ſupream ones. He loves Winter more than Summer, becauſe it affords more Gameſters, and Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas more than any other time, becauſe there is more gaming then. He gives more willingly to the Butler than to the Poors-box, and is never more religious than when he prays he may win. He imagines he is at play when he is at Church; he takes his Prayer-book for a Pack of Cards, and thinks he is ſhuffling when he turns over the leaves. This man will play like <hi>Nero</hi> when the City is on fire, or like <hi>Archimedes</hi> when it is ſacking, rather than interrupt his Game. If play hath reduced him to poverty, then he is like one a drowning, who faſtens upon any thing next at hand. Amongſt other of his ſhipwracks, he hath happily loſt ſhame, and this want ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies him. No man puts his brain to more uſe than he; for his life is a daily invention, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:179790:18"/>each meal a new ſtratagem, and like a flie will boldly ſup at every man's cup. He will offer you a quart of Sack out of his joy to ſee you, and in requital of this courteſie you can do no leſs than pay for it. His borrowings are like <hi>Subſidies,</hi> each man a ſhilling or two, as he can well diſpend, which they lend him not with the hope to be repaid, but that he will come no more. Men ſhun him at length as they do an Infection, and having done with the Aye as his cloaths to him, hung on as long as he could, at laſt drops off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of BILLIARDS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Gentile, cleanly and moſt ingenious Game at Billiards had its firſt original from <hi>Italy,</hi> and for the excellency of the Recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation is much approved of, and plaid by moſt Nations in <hi>Europe,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>England,</hi> there being few Towns of note therein which hath not a publick Billiard-Table, neither are they want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in many Noble and private Families in the Country, for the recreation of the mind and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the body.</p>
               <p>The form of a Billiard-Table is oblong, that is, ſomething longer than it is broad, it is rail'd
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:179790:19"/>round, which rail or ledge ought to be a little ſwell'd or ſtuft with fine flox or cotton: the ſuperficies of the Table muſt be covered with green-cloth, the finer and more freed from knots the better it is: the Board muſt be levell'd as exactly as may be, ſo that a Ball may run true upon any part of the Table without leaning to any ſide thereof; but what by reaſon of ill-ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd boards which are ſubject to warp, or the floar on which it ſtands being uneven, or in time by the weight of the Table, and the Gameſters yielding and giving way, there are very few Billiard-Tables which are found true; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch which are exactly level'd are highly valuable by a good player; for at a falſe Table it is impoſſible for him to ſhow the excellency of his Art and Skill, whereby Bunglers many times by knowing the windings and tricks of the Table have ſhamefully beaten a very good Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who at a true Table would have given him three in five.</p>
               <p>But to proceed in the deſcription thereof; at the four corners of the Table there are holes, and at each ſide exactly in the middle one, which are called Hazards, and have hanging at the bottoms Nets to receive the Balls, and keep them from falling to the ground when they are hazarded. I have ſeen at ſome Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles Wooden Boxes for the hazards, ſix of them as aforeſaid, but they are nothing near ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable as the former, becauſe a Ball ſtruck
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:179790:19"/>hard is more apt to flie out of them when ſtruck in.</p>
               <p>There is to the Table belonging an Ivory Port, which ſtands at one end of the Table, and an Ivory King at the other, two ſmall Ivory Balls and two Sticks; where note if your Balls are not compleatly round, you can never expect good proof in your play: your Sticks ought to be heavy, made of <hi>Braſile, Lignum vitae,</hi> or ſome other weighty wood, which at the broad end muſt be tipt with Ivory; where note, if the heads happen to be looſe, you will never ſtrike a ſmart ſtroke, you will eaſily perceive that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by the hollow deadneſs of your ſtroak and faint running of your Ball.</p>
               <p>The Game is five by Day-light, or ſeven if odds be given, and three by Candle-light or more according to odds in Houſes that make a livelihood thereof; but in Gentlemens houſes there is no ſuch reſtriction; for the Game may juſtly admit of as many as the Gameſters pleaſe to make.</p>
               <p>For the Lead you are to ſtand on the one ſide of the Table oppoſite to the King, with your Ball laid near the Cuſhion, and your Adverſary on the other in like poſture; and he that with his Stick makes his Ball come neareſt the King leads firſt.</p>
               <p>The Leader muſt have a care that at the firſt ſtroke his Ball touch not the end of the Table leading from the King to the Port, but after the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:179790:20"/>firſt ſtroke he need not fear to do it, and let him ſo lead that he may either be in a poſſibility of paſſing the next ſtroke, or ſo cunningly lie that he may be in a very fair probability of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding his Adverſaries Ball, that very ſtroak he plaid after him.</p>
               <p>The firſt conteſt is who ſhall paſs firſt, and in that ſtrife there are frequent opportunities of hazarding one another; and it is very pleaſant to obſerve what policies are uſed in hindering one another from the paſs, as by turning the Port with a ſtrong clever ſtroke; for if you turn it with your Stick it muſt be ſet right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; but indeed more properly he that doth it ſhould loſe one; ſometimes it is done (when you ſee it is impoſſible to paſs) by laying your Ball in the port, or before your Adverſaries, and then all he can do is to paſs after you; if he hath paſt and you dare not adventure to paſs after him, for fear he ſhould in the interim touch the King and ſo win the end, you muſt wait upon him and watch all opportunities to hazard him, or King him; that is, when his Ball lyeth in ſuch manner that when you ſtrike his Ball may hit down the King, and then you win one.</p>
               <p>Here note, that if you ſhould King him, and your Ball fly over the Table, or elſe run into a Hazard, that then you loſe one notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The player ought to have a curious eye, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:179790:20"/>very good judgment when he either intends to King his Adverſary's Ball, or hazard, in taking or quartering out juſt ſo much of the Ball as will accompliſh either; which obſervation muſt be noted in paſſing on your Adverſary's Ball, or corner of the Port. Some I have obſerved ſo skilful at this Recreation, that if they have had leſs than a fifth part of a Ball they would rarely miſs King or Hazard.</p>
               <p>As this is a cleanly paſtime, ſo there are Laws or Orders made againſt lolling ſlovingly Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that by their forfeitures they may be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to regularity and decency; wherefore be careful you lay not your Hand on the Table when you ſtrike, or let your Sleeve drag upon it, if you do it is a loſs; if you ſmoak and let the aſhes of your Pipe fall on the Table, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by oftentimes the Cloth is burned, it is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, but that ſhould not ſo much deter you from it as the hindrance piping is to your play.</p>
               <p>When you ſtrike a long ſtroke, hold your ſtick neatly between your two fore-fingers and your thumb, then ſtrike ſmartly, and by aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly you may when you pleaſe either fetch back your Adverſary's Ball when he lyeth fair for a paſs, or many times when he lyeth behind the King, and you at the other end of the Table, you may King him backward.</p>
               <p>If you lie cloſe you may uſe the ſmall end of your ſtick, or the flat of the big end, raiſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:179790:21"/>up one end over your ſhoulder, which you ſhall think moſt convenient for your purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Have a care of raking, for if it be not a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture it is a fault hardly excuſable, but if you touch your Ball twice it is a loſs.</p>
               <p>Beware when you jobb your Ball through the Port with the great end of your Stick that you throw it not down, if you do, it is a loſs, but do it ſo handſomely that at one ſtroke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out turning the Port with your Stick you effect your purpoſe; it is good play to turn the Port with your Ball, and ſo hinder your Adverſary from paſſing; neither is it amiſs if you can to make your Adverſary a Fornicator, that is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſt your ſelf a little way, and the others Ball being hardly through the Port, you put him back again, and it may be quite out of paſs.</p>
               <p>It argueth policy to lay a long Hazard ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for your Antagoniſt, whereby he is often entrapped for raſhly adventuring at that diſtance, thinking to ſtrike your Ball into the Hazard, which lieth very near it, he frequently runs in himſelf by reaſon of that great diſtance.</p>
               <p>There is great art in lying abſcond, that is, to lie at bo-peep with your Adverſary, either ſubtlely to gain a paſs or hazard.</p>
               <p>Here note, if your Adverſary hath not paſt and lyeth up by the King, you may endeavour to paſs again, which if you do, and touch the King, it is two, but if thrown down you loſe: Some inſtead of a King uſe a ſtring and a bell,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:179790:21"/>and then you need not fear to have the end, if you can paſs firſt; this is in my judgment bung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling play, there being not that curious art of finely touching at a great diſtance a King that ſtands very tickliſhly.</p>
               <p>For your better underſtanding of the Game read the enſuing Orders. But there is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way than practice to make you perfect therein.</p>
               <div type="rules_to_play_billiards">
                  <head>ORDERS <hi>to be obſerved by ſuch who will play at Billiards.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. IF the Leader touch the end of the Table with his Ball at the firſt ſtroke he loſeth one.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the Follower intend to hit his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries Ball, or paſs at one ſtroke he muſt ſtring his Ball, that is, lay it even with the King, or he loſeth one.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that paſſeth through the Port hath the advantage of touching the King which is one if not thrown down.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. He that paſſeth twice, his Adverſary having not paſt at all, and toucheth the King without throwing him down wins two ends.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that paſſeth not hath no other advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage than the Hazards.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He that is a Fornicator (that is, hath paſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:179790:22"/>through the back of the Port) he muſt paſs twice through the fore-part, or he cannot have the advantage of paſſing that end.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that hits down the port or King, or hazards his own Ball, or ſtrikes either Ball over the Table loſeth one.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. He that hazards his Adverſarie's Ball, or makes it hit down the King, winneth the end.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. If four play, two againſt two, he that miſtakes his ſtroke loſeth one to that ſide he is of.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. He that after both Balls plaid, removes the Port without conſent, or ſtrikes his Ball twice together, or that his Adverſaries Ball touch his Stick-hand, Clothes, or playeth his Adverſaries Balls, loſeth one.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. He that ſets not one Foot upon the ground when he ſtrikes his Ball ſhall loſe an end, or if he lays his hand or ſleeve on the Cloth.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. A ſtander by though he betts ſhall not inſtruct, direct or ſpeak in the Game without conſent, or being firſt asked; if after he is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed hereof he offend in this nature, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very fault he ſhall inſtantly forfeit Two pence for the good of the Company, or not be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to ſtay in the Room.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. He that plays a Ball, while the other runs, or takes up a Ball before it lie ſtill, loſeth an end.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:179790:22"/>
                  <p n="14">14. He that removes the Port with his Stick when he ſtrikes his Ball, and thereby prevents his Adverſaries Ball from paſſing, loſeth an end.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. All Controverſies are to be decided by the Standers by, upon asking judgment. Here note, that whoſoever breaks the King forfeits a ſhilling, for the Port ten ſhillings, and each Stick five ſhillings.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Five ends make a Game by Day-light, and three by Candle-light.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="rules_to_play_billiards">
                  <head>The ORDERS in Verſe, as I found them fram'd for a very ancient BILLIARD-TABLE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="1">1. <hi>THe Leading-ball the upper end may'nt hit;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For if it doth, it loſeth one by it.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="2">2. <hi>The Follower with the King lie even ſhall</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If he doth paſs or hit the others ball;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or elſe loſe one: the like if either lay</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their arm or hand on board when they do play.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="3">3. <hi>That man wins one who with the others ball</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So strikes the King that he doth make him fall.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="4">4. <hi>If ſtriking at a hazard both run in,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The ball struck at thereby an end ſhall win.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="5">5. <hi>He loſeth one that down the Port doth fling;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The like doth he that juſtles down the King.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:179790:23"/>
                     <l n="6">6. <hi>He that in play the adverſe ball ſhall touch</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With stick, hand, or cloaths forfeits juſt as much.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="7">7. <hi>And he that twice hath paſt ſhall touch the King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The other not paſt at all ſhall two ends win.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="8">8. <hi>If both the balls over the Table flie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The striker of them loſeth one thereby.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And if but one upon the board attend,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The striker still the loſer of the end.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="9">9. <hi>One foot upon the ground muſt still be ſet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or one end's loſt if you do that forget:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And if you twice ſhall touch a ball e're He</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hath struck between an end for him is free.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="10">10. <hi>If any Stander-by ſhall chance to bet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And will inſtruct, he then muſt pay the ſet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="11">11. <hi>The Port or King being ſet, who moves the ſame</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With hand or stick ſhall loſe that end or Game.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="12">12. <hi>He that can touch being paſt, or ſtrike the other</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into the Hazard is allowed another.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="13">13. <hi>If any Stander-by ſhall stop a ball,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Game being loſt thereby he pays for all.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="14">14. <hi>If any paſt be stricken back again,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His paſs before ſhall be accounted vain.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="15">15. <hi>He that breaks any thing with violence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>King, Port, or Stick is to make good th'offence.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="16">16. <hi>If any not the Game doth fully know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May ask another whether it be ſo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Remember alſo when the Game you win,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To ſet it up for fear of wrangling.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l n="17">17. <hi>He that doth make his ball the King light hit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And holes th'other ſcores two ends for it.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:179790:23"/>
                  <p>There are ſeveral other Orders which only concern the Houſe which I omit, as impertinent to the Rules of playing at Billiards.</p>
                  <p>Since Recreation is a thing lawful in it ſelf if not abuſed, I cannot but commend this as the moſt gentile and innocent of any I know, if rightly uſed; there being none of thoſe cheats to be plaid at this as at ſeveral other Games I ſhall hereafter mention. There is nothing here to be uſed but pure art; and therefore I ſhall only caution you to go to play, that you ſuffer not your ſelf to be over-matcht, and do not when you meet with a better Gameſter than your ſelf condemn the Table, and do not ſwear as one did playing at <hi>Nine-Pins,</hi> this <hi>L. N.</hi> hath put falſe pins upon me.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, I believe this Paſtime is not ſo much uſed of late as formerly, by reaſon of thoſe ſpunging Caterpillars which ſwarm where any Billiard-Tables are ſet up, who making that ſingle Room their Shop, Kitc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing and Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; their Shop, for this is the place where they wait for ignorant Cullies to be their Cuſtomers; their Kitching, for from hence comes the Major part of their proviſion, drinking and ſmoaking being their common ſuſtenance; and when they can perſwade no more Perſons to play at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they make it their dormitory, and ſleep un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it; the Floor is their Feather-bed, the legs of the Table their Bed-poſts, and the Table the Teſter; they dream of nothing but <hi>Hazards,</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:179790:24"/>being never out of them, of <hi>paſſing</hi> and <hi>repaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> which may be fitly applied to their lewd lives, which makes them continually paſs from one Priſon to another till their lives are ended; and there is an end of the Game.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of TRUCKS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TRucks</hi> is an <hi>Italian</hi> Game, and is much uſed in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> it is not very unlike <hi>Billiards,</hi> but more boiſterous, and in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion leſs gentile.</p>
               <p>It is a paſtime leſs noted in <hi>England,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tables are rarely met withal; one I have ſeen at <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> but ſo bunglingly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and ſo irregularly form'd and fram'd, that it was fit for none to play at but ſuch who never ſaw or plaid at any other than that.</p>
               <p>A right <hi>Truck-table</hi> ought to be ſomewhat larger than a <hi>Billiard-table,</hi> being at leaſt three foot longer than it is broad and covered with Green Cloth, but it need not be every whit ſo fine as the former.</p>
               <p>It hath three holes at each end, beſides the corner holes; the middlemoſt at one end ſtands directly againſt the <hi>Sprigg</hi> which ſtands for the King at <hi>Billiards,</hi> and the other end, middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:179790:24"/>hole, ſtands exactly againſt the <hi>Argolio,</hi> which is in the nature of a port at <hi>Billiards.</hi> Of each ſide there are ten holes, none of theſe have nets to receive the Balls, and therefore it is a ſport more troubleſome than <hi>Billiards.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Argolio</hi> ſtands as the Port at <hi>Billiards</hi> as aforeſaid, and is made of a ſtrong hoop of Iron faſtned to the Table, that it cannot ſtir, having a wider paſſage than a Port, and in its bending is higher from the Board.</p>
               <p>The Sprigg is another piece of Iron, about the thickneſs of a Man's little finger, and is tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler than the Billiard King, and driven into the Board, ſo that it is immovable.</p>
               <p>The Tacks with which they play, are much bigger than Billiard Sticks, and are headed at each end with Iron; the ſmall end is round from the middle, or farther running taperwiſe, but the great end is flat beneath, though rounding a top; good Gameſters play for the moſt part with the ſmall end.</p>
               <p>The Balls are made of Ivory, and are in big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs like Tennis-balls, and require much art in their rounding, for otherwiſe they will never run true.</p>
               <p>You may lead as you do at Billiards, but that is lookt upon as bungling play; the beſt Artiſts at this Game uſually bank at the fourth Cuſhion from the end where the Argolio ſtands, and is commonly markt for diſtinction with a little chalk.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:179790:25"/>
               <p>The Game, becauſe it is ſooner up than Billi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, is Nine, and ſometimes Fifteen, or indeed as many, or as few as you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>He that leads muſt have a care he hit not the end, for that is a loſs, but he may bank if he pleaſe; if the Leader lie in paſs, the Follower muſt hit him away if he can, for if he paſs it is ten to one but he wins the end, becauſe he may boldly ſtrike at the Sprigg. If the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der lies not in paſs, he may either ſtrike at him, or lye as well to paſs as the former, and then all the ſtrife lyeth in trucking one another, or ſtriving who ſhall paſs firſt.</p>
               <p>In paſſing here is this ſubtlety to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if your Adverſary's Ball lie ſtraight before the Argolio, and yours lies a little behind it, and it is your ſtroke, you would think it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to paſs by reaſon of that obſtruction; whereas it is eaſily done thus, take the ſmall end of your Tack, and ſet it ſloaping behind your Ball, but touch it not, for if you do, you loſe the end; then bend your fiſt, and give your Stick a ſmart cuff, and it will raiſe your Ball o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your Adverſary's through the Port with much facility, this is called by Artiſts, falkating; all that the follower can do to ſave the end, is (lying as he doth juſt againſt the Sprigg) to paſs and touch the Sprigg at one ſtroke, and that is two; if he touch not the end, is the others; if in ſtriking the Sprigg too hard, he run not our of one hole or other, and then he loſeth.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:179790:25"/>
               <p>For the advantage of ſtriking you may lay one hand on the Table, arm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture; but you muſt not touch your Ball with your ſleeve or hand without leave firſt obtained under the loſs of the end. As thus, you may not know which is your Ball, upon this you cry, <hi>By your leave, Sir,</hi> and then you may take it up and ſee by the mark whether it be yours or not.</p>
               <p>If you truck your Adverſary's Ball it is one, but if you do it and run out, or flye over the Table, you loſe one, ſo if you ſtrike at your Adverſary's Ball, and one or both flye over the Table it is a loſs to you.</p>
               <p>If after you have paſt you truck your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary's Ball and hit the Sprigg, it is three; if you paſs at one ſtroke, truck your Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry's Ball and hit the Sprigg, you win four; this is very rarely done, as you may well imagine, yet I have ſeen it done, but never done by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, but caſually; there is much art in holding your Tack rightly, the beſt way I can inform you is to hold the great end in your right hand, and level the ſmall end over your fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger and thumb, leaning your left arm on the Table, for the more ſteddy and direct guidance of your Tack to tranſmit the Ball to what part of the Table you ſhall think moſt requiſite, and when you intend a ſmart ſtroke let your ſhove be brisk.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, I muſt leave this as all other Games
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:179790:26"/>to your obſervation and practice; only this let me adviſe you, if any difference ariſe, leave it to the judgment of the Table, to decide the Controverſie, but end it not with your lives, by uſing two ſuch clubbing Arbitrators as you play with, for with one ſtroke (they are ſo ſtrong and heavy) they are ſufficient to daſh out a Man's brains, and by the ſeveral great miſchiefs have been done thereby be adviſed not to fall into the like dangerous raſhneſs.</p>
               <p>One thing I had almoſt forgot, and that is, if you fulkate over hand be very careful how you ſtrike your Ball, for by careleſneſs or miſſing your Ball you frequently wound the Table. Now fulkating over hand, is, when you lie near the Cuſhion for a paſs, and your Adverſary's Ball lies directly before yours, to make yours to jump over his through the Argolio, you muſt ſtrike a ſtrong ſtroke, ſloaping downwards, which will make your Ball mount aloft.</p>
               <div type="rules">
                  <head>Orders for a Truck-Table.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. IF the Leader touch the end, it is the loſs of one.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the Follower intend to hit his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary's Ball from the paſs at the firſt ſtroke he muſt ſtring his Ball even with the Sprigg, or loſeth one.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He that paſſeth and firſt hits the Sprigg wins one.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:179790:26"/>
                  <p n="4">4. He that paſſeth twice and hits the Sprigg wins two.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He that paſſeth backward (and is called a Fornicator) he muſt paſs twice through the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, or he cannot have the advantage of paſſing that end.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He that trucks his own Ball, or ſtrikes it, or his Adverſary's over the Table, loſeth one.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. He that trucks his Adverſary's Ball wins two.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. He that toucheth his Adverſary's Ball with Hand, Stick, or Clothes, or ſtrikes it for his own, loſeth one.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. He that paſſeth and toucheth at a ſtroke, wins two.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. He that having paſt trucks his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Ball and hits the Sprigg with his own, wins three.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Laſtly, he that paſſeth, trucketh his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary's Ball and hits with his own the Sprigg, wins four.</p>
                  <p>There are other trivial Orders, which for brevity ſake I here omit.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:179790:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of BOWLING.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BOwling is a Game or Recreation, which if moderately uſed is very healthy for the body, and would be much more commendable than it is, were it not for thoſe ſwarms of Rooks which ſo peſter Bowling-Greens, Bares, and Bowling-Alleys where any ſuch places are to be found, ſome making ſo ſmall a ſpot of ground yield them more annually than fifty Acres of Land ſhall do elſewhere about the City, and this done, cunning, betting, crafty matching, and baſely playing booty.</p>
               <p>In Bowling there is a great art in chuſing out his ground, and preventing the windings, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and many turning advantages of the ſame, whether it be in open wide places, as Bares and Bowling greens, or in cloſe Bowling-Alleys. Where note that in Bowling the chuſing of the Bowl is the greateſt cunning. Flat Bowls are beſt for cloſe Alleys; round byaſſed Bowls for open grounds of advantage, and Bowls round as a Ball for green ſwarths that are plain and level.</p>
               <p>There is no adviſing by writing how to bowl, practice muſt be your beſt tutor, which muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you the riſings, fallings, and all the ſeveral
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:179790:27"/>advantages that are to be had in divers Greens, and Bowling-Alleys; all that I ſhall ſay, have a care you are not in the firſt place rookt out of your money; and in the next place you go not to theſe places of pleaſure unſeaſonably, that is when your more weighty buſineſs and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns require your being at home, or ſome-where elſe.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Character of a Bowling-Ally and Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-Green.</head>
                  <p>A Bowling-Green, or Bowling-Ally is a place where three things are thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way beſides the Bowls, <hi>viz.</hi> Time, Money and Curſes, and the laſt ten for one. The beſt ſport in it, is the Gameſters, and he enjoyns it that looks on and betts nothing. It is a School of wrangling, and worſe than the <hi>Schools;</hi> for here men will wrangle for a hairs bredth, and make a ſtir where a ſtraw would end the controverſie. Never did <hi>Mimmick</hi> ſcrew his body into hall the forms theſe Men do theirs; and it is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of their Creed, that the bending back of the body or ſcrewing in of their ſhoulders is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to hinder the over-ſpeed of the Bowl, and that the running after it adds to its ſpeed. Though they are skilful in ground, I know not what grounds they have for loud lying, crying
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:179790:28"/>ſometimes the Bowl is gone <hi>a mile, a mile,</hi> &amp;c. when it comes ſhort of the Jack by ſix yards; and on the contrary crying <hi>ſhort, ſhort,</hi> when he hath overbowled as far. How ſenſleſs theſe Men appear when they are ſpeaking ſenſe to their Bowls, putting confidence in their intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for a good caſt! It is the beſt diſcovery of humours, eſpecially in the loſers, where you may obſerve fine variety of impatience, whilſt ſome fret, rail, ſwear, and cavil at every thing, others rejoyce and laugh, as if that was the ſole deſign of their creation.</p>
                  <p>To give you the Moral of it, it is the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of the World, or the Worlds ambition, where moſt are ſhort, over, wide or wrong by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſed, and ſome few juſtle in to the <hi>Miſtreſs,</hi> Fortune! And here it is as in the Court, where the neareſt are the moſt ſpighted, and all Bowls aim at the other.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of a Game at Cheſs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHeſs</hi> is a Royal Game and more difficult to be underſtood than any other Game whatever, and will take up ſometimes in the playing ſo long a time that I have known two play a Fortnight at times before the Game hath
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:179790:28"/>been ended: and indeed I believe the tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Game hath caus'd the practice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be ſo little uſed; however ſince this pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime is ſo highly ingenious that there is none can parallel it, I ſhall here lay down ſome brief Inſtructions tending to the knowledge thereof.</p>
               <p>The firſt and higheſt is a <hi>King,</hi> the next in height is a <hi>Queen,</hi> the cloven heads are <hi>Biſhops;</hi> they who have heads cut aſſaunt like a feather in a Helmet are called <hi>Knights,</hi> the laſt are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Rooks,</hi> with a round button'd cap on his head, and theſe ſignifie the Country and Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantry, the <hi>Pawns</hi> are all alike, and each Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man hath one of them to wait upon him.</p>
               <p>The Cheſs-men ſtanding on the board, you muſt place the White King in the fourth houſe being black from the corner of the field in the firſt and lower rank, and the black King in the white houſe, being the fourth on the other ſide in your Adverſaries firſt rank oppoſite to the white King; then place the white Queen next to the white King in a white houſe, which is the fourth on that ſide of the field; likewiſe the black Queen in a black houſe next to a black King in the ſame rank.</p>
               <p>Then place on the other ſide of the King in the ſame rank, firſt a Biſhop, becauſe he being a Man of counſel is placed before the Knight, who is a man of action or execution; the Knight af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Biſhop, and after the Knight place the Rook (who is the peaſant or Country-man) in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:179790:29"/>the laſt place or corner of the field: place alſo on the Queens ſide and next to her a Biſhop, next a Knight and then a Rook; the Pawns take up the laſt place; one of which you muſt place before each Nobleman as Attendants, ſo that theſe great or Noblemen fill up the firſt rank and the Pawns the ſecond from one corner of the field to the other, and as many great Men and Pawns as belong to the King ſo many hath the Queen, <hi>viz.</hi> three great men and four Pawns a-piece, that is, one Biſhop, one Knight, and one Rook with their Pawns.</p>
               <p>Having thus placed and ordered your men, you muſt in the next place conſider their march, how they advance and take guard and check.</p>
               <p>The Pawns do commonly begin firſt the onſet, and their march is forward in their own file, one houſe at once only and never backward; for the Pawns alone never retreat, the manner of his taking men is ſide-ways in the next houſe forward of the next file to him on either ſide, where when he hath captivated his enemy, and placed himſelf in his ſeat, he proceeds and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves forward one houſe at once in that file, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til he find an opportunity to take again.</p>
               <p>The Pawn guards a Piece of his ſide which ſtands in that place, where if it were one of the contrary party he might take it. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Pawn checks the King, <hi>viz.</hi> as he takes not as he goes, which Check if the adverſe King cannot ſhun either by taking up the Pawn himſelf
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:179790:29"/>(if the Pawn be unguarded, or occaſion his ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by ſome of his Pieces, he muſt of neceſſity remove himſelf out of the Pawns Check) or if it lie not in his power it is pawn-Mate, and ſo the Game is ended, and loſt by him whoſe King is ſo Mate.</p>
               <p>The Rook goes backward and forward in any file and croſs-ways to and fro in any rank as far as he will, ſo that there ſtands no piece between him and the place he would go to. Thus he doth guard his own and check the King alſo, which check if the King can neither cover by the interpoſition of ſome piece of his between the checking Rook and himſelf, nor take the Rook, nor be the cauſe of his taking, he muſt remove himſelf out of that check or it is Mate, and the Game is up.</p>
               <p>The Knight skips forward, backward and on either ſide from the place he ſtands in to the next ſave one of a different colour, with a ſideling march or a ſloap, thus he kills his enemies, guards his friends, and checks the King of the adverſe party, which becauſe (like the Pawns check) it cannot be covered, the King muſt either remove or courſe the Knight to be taken (for he himſelf cannot take the Knight that checks him) or its Mate, and the Game is up.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop walks always in the ſame colour of the field that he is firſt placed in, forward and backward, aſloap every way as far as he liſts; provided, that the way be clear between him
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:179790:30"/>and the place he intends to go to: thus he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes the adverſary, guards his conſorts, and checks the adverſe King, which not being avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as aforeſaid, is Mate to him and the Game is ended.</p>
               <p>The Queens walk is more univerſal; for ſhe goes the draughts of all the aforenamed pieces, (the Knights only excepted, for her march is not from one colour to the other aſloap) ſo far as ſhe liſteth finding the way obſtructed by any piece, and thus ſhe diſturbs her Adverſaries, protects her ſubjects, and mates the King, unleſs (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid) he removes, covers, takes, or cauſes her to be taken, otherwiſe it is his Mate and the Game is concluded.</p>
               <p>The Kings draught is from his own to the next to him any way, that either is empty of his own ſubjects, or where he may ſurpriſe any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarded enemy, or where he may ſtand free from the check of any of the adverſe party. Thus he confounds his foes, defends his friends, but checks not the King his enemy, who never check one another; for there muſt ever be one houſe or place at leaſt between the two Kings, though unpoſſeſt of any other piece; and if one King be compel'd to flie for refuge to the King of the adverſe party, then it is Mate or a Stale, and ſo he that gives the firſt wins the Game. Let this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for the various draughts and ſeveral walks of the Cheſs-men: but this is not all, I ſhall give you ſome other Inſtructions as brief as I may,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:179790:30"/>and refer the reſt to your own obſervation.</p>
               <p>Kings and Queens have ſeven a piece to attend them. The King whether white or black guards five perſons before he goes forth, and being once advanced into the field, though it be but into the ſecond houſe, he then and afterwards in his March guards eight houſes till he come again to one ſide or other of the field.</p>
               <p>The five the King guards before his March, are the Queen, the Biſhop, his own, his Queens, and his Biſhops Pawn.</p>
               <p>The Queen protects her King, and Biſhop, her Kings, her Biſhops, and her own Pawn. Thus the Queen guards as many as the King before ſhe goes forth, and after till the Game be won or loſt.</p>
               <p>The Kings Biſhop guards the Kings Pawn, and his Knights, the Queens Biſhop guards, the Queens Pawn and her Knights guard but three houſes apiece before they go forth; but after they are marched off from the ſide of the field, they guard as many houſes as the King and Queen do. Thoſe houſes which the Knights guard ere they go out, are the Kings. The Knight guards the Kings Pawn, and the third houſe in the front of the Kings Biſhops Pawn, and the third houſe in the front of the Kings Rooks Pawn.</p>
               <p>The Queens Knight guards her Pawn, and the third houſe in the front of her Biſhops Pawn, alſo the third houſe in the front of her Rooks Pawn. The Kings Rook guards his own Pawn,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:179790:31"/>and the Kings Knight and no more till he be off of the ſide of the field, and then he guards four houſes, and the ſame does the Queens Rook. The Pawns likewiſe guard theſe places before they be advanced into the field, <hi>viz.</hi> The Kings Pawn guards the third houſe before the Queen, and the third before the Kings Biſhop, the Queens Pawn guards the third houſe before the King, and the third before her Biſhop. The Kings Biſhop's Pawn guards the third houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King, and the third before the Kings Knight. The Queens Biſhop's Pawn guards the third houſe before the Queen, and the third be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Queens Knight. The Kings Knights Pawn guards the third houſe before the Kings Biſhop, and the third before the Kings Rook. The Queens Knight's Pawn guards the third houſe before the Queens Biſhop, and the third before the Queens Rook. The Kings Rooks Pawns, and the Queens Rooks Pawn guard but one houſe apiece, that is to ſay, the third houſes before the Knight, becauſe they ſtand on the ſide of the field.</p>
               <p>Next conſider the value of the great men. The King expoſeth not himſelf to danger upon every occaſion, but the Queen is under him as General, and doth more ſervice than any two great Men beſides; and when it happens that ſhe is loſt, her King moſt certainly loſeth the field, unleſs the Adverſary knows not how to make uſe of ſo great an advantage. Wherefore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:179790:31"/>if a King loſe two or three of his beſt men in taking the opponents Queen, yet he hath the beſt of it, if he can but manage his Game rightly.</p>
               <p>Next to the Queen in value is the Rook, and is as much in worth above the Biſhop and Knight, as the Queen is above him; ſo that a Rook is more worth than two Biſhops, or two Knights, becauſe he can give a Mate by the help of the King, which no other piece can do, unleſs plaid with excellent skill.</p>
               <p>Biſhops are accounted better than Knights, becauſe they can give a Mate with a King when no other men are left to help them, with more eaſe than the Knights can; for they ſeldom or never do it: yet it is more dangerous to loſe a Knight than a Biſhop, becauſe the Knights check is more dangerous than the Biſhops; for the Biſhop is tyed to one colour of the field out of which he cannot paſs, but the Knight paſſeth through all the houſes of the field; the Biſhops check may be covered, the Knights cannot; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides if it fall out that one of the Kings hath no other men left but his Biſhops, and the other King none but his Knights, the Knights with their checks can take the Biſhops one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the Biſhops cannot guard each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which the Knights can do; ſo that at the beginning of the Game it is better to loſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops for the Adverſaries Knights, than the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:179790:32"/>
               <p>The difference of the worth of Pawns is not ſo great as that of Noblemen, becauſe there is not ſuch variety in their walks, only thus much, the Kings Biſhop's Pawn is the beſt in the field among the Pawns, and therefore the Gameſter ought to be very careful of him; for if it ſhould happen that the black King loſe his Biſhop's Pawn to gain the white Kings Pawn, the black Kings loſs is the greater, becauſe he cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this accident make a rank of Pawns of three of a rank on that ſide of the field for his own ſecurity, which is a great diſadvantage, ſo that it is better for either of the Kings to loſe his own Pawn than his Biſhops.</p>
               <p>But if you ſhould object that the King which loſeth his Biſhops Pawn may relieve himſelf on the other ſide of the field, turning to his Queens Rooks quarters, where he ſhall have Pawns to ſuccour him, I anſwer, 'tis true, he may do ſo, but he will be a longer time in effecting his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, becauſe there are more pieces between him and his Queens Rooks by one draught than between his own Rook and himſelf; ſo that in playing that draught he indangers the whole Game if his adverſary know how to make uſe of advantages. The Kings Pawn is next in worth, which oftentimes keeps the King from check by diſcovery; then the Queens Pawn is next, and after that the Knights, and laſt of all the Rooks Pawns, becauſe they guard but one houſe apiece in the field.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:179790:32"/>
               <p>The King and the Pawn have certain privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges granted them, which none of the other Cheſs-men have; as for inſtance, The King whoſe remove (as hath been already mentioned) is from the place of his ſtanding at any time to the next houſe in file or rank of any ſide (that is one only ſtep at once,) yet if at any time his rank be empty of his men, ſo that no one ſtands between the King and the Rook of either corner, the King may then ſhift or change with what Rook he pleaſeth, between whom and himſelf the way ſtands clear from other men; and that for his better ſecurity, provided, that neither the King nor the Rook he intends to change with, hath not as yet been removed from the place of their firſt ſtanding. Now the manner of the Kings ſhifting or changing with a Rook is thus:</p>
               <p>The rank cleared as aforeſaid, and neither King nor Rook having yet ſtirred, he may go two draughts at once to his own Rook, and ſo towards his Queens Rook, cauſing the Rook he changeth with to change his place, and come and ſtand by him on the other ſide; that is, his own Rook in the Biſhops place, and the Queens Rook in the Queens place, and either of theſe changes but for one draught. This is the Kings firſt prerogative.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is, that whereas any man may be taken by any adverſary, if he be brought ſo near as to come within the compaſs, the King cannot, but he is only to be ſaluted by his adverſary
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:179790:33"/>with the word check, adviſing him thereby to look about him the more warily, and provide for his own ſafety: now if that adverſary do this unguarded ſo near the King, he may ſtep thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his true draught, and the King may ſtay him with his own hand, if he judge it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient.</p>
               <p>As for the Pawn, the firſt priviledge he hath, is, that whereas his walk is but to the next houſe forward in his own file at once when he march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and to the next houſe ſide-long forward of the next file of either ſide, when he takes, I ſay, his priviledge is, that he may remove to the ſecond houſe forward, which is the fourth rank in his own file for his firſt draught, and ever after but one forward at once.</p>
               <p>The ſecond priviledge is greater, and that is, when any Pawn is come ſo far as to the firſt rank of the adverſary, and ſeats himſelf in any of his Noble houſes, he is dignified for this fact with the name and power of a Queen, and ſo becomes chief of his own Kings forces if the firſt Queen were ſlain before, and if the firſt Queen be yet ſtanding in the field, the Pawn coming to the rank aforeſaid in any houſe whatſoever, may there make what piece you pleaſe which you have already loſt.</p>
               <p>Some are of opinion that Chefs as well as Draughts may be plaid by a certain Rule, indeed I am partly inclined to believe it notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that moſt are of a contrary opinion.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:179790:33"/>
               <p>The firſt remove is an advantage, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt draw for who ſhall have the firſt draught, which may be done with a black and white man diſtributed into either hand, and offer'd the Opponent which he will chuſe; if he chuſe his own man the firſt draught is his; but when a Game is ended, and a Mate given, he is to have the firſt Draught next Game who gave the former Mate.</p>
               <p>The firſt remove is divers according to the judgment of the Gameſter, as ſome will firſt remove their Kings Knights Pawn one ſingle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move, that is to the third houſe in his own file, others play the Kings Rooks Pawn firſt a double draught; but the beſt way is to play the Kings Pawn firſt a double remove, that ſo if they are not prevented by their adverſaries playing the like, they may ſtill remove that Pawn forward with good guard; for he will prove very inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to the adverſe King.</p>
               <p>This Pawn I ſhall adviſe you to remove firſt, but not ſo venturouſly as a double remove, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if you cannot guard him cunningly, then are you like to loſe him with a check to your King, by the Queens coming forth upon him to the great hazard of your Kings Rook; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore play your Kings Rook one ſingle remove, that there may be way made for the coming forth of Queen one way two houſes aſloap, and to your Kings Biſhop the other way three hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes aſloap, and ſo upon the neglect of your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:179790:34"/>he may be put to a Scholars check, at leaſt in danger of it: here note it is ill to play the Biſhops Pawn firſt, and worſe to play the Queens.</p>
               <p>He that would be an Artiſt in this noble Game, muſt be ſo careful to ſecond his pieces, that if any man advanced be taken, the enemy may be likewiſe taken by that piece that guards or ſeconds it; ſo ſhall he not clearly loſe any man, which ſhould it fall out contrarily might loſe the Game; he muſt alſo make his paſſages free for retreat, as occaſion ſhall ſerve, leſt he be worſted.</p>
               <p>In defending you muſt alſo be very careful that you are as able to aſſault as your enemy; for you muſt not only anſwer your adverſaries aſſault by foreſeeing his deſign by his play, and preventing it, but you muſt likewiſe deviſe plots, how to peſter and grieve your aſſailant, and chiefly how to entrap ſuch pieces as are advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by him, preventing their retreat, amongſt which a Pawn is the ſooneſt enſnared, becauſe he cannot go back for ſuccour or relief; but Biſhops and Rooks are harder to be ſurprized, becauſe they can march from one ſide of the field to the other to avoid the enſuing danger; but the Knights and Queens of all are moſt difficultly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd, becauſe they have ſo many places of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, and the Queen more eſpecially: where note as a great piece of policy, that if poſſible you conſtantly have as many guards upon any
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:179790:34"/>one piece of yours as you ſee your enemy hath when he advanceth to take it, and be ſure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that your guards be of leſs value than the pieces he encountreth you with; for then if he fall to taking you will reap advantage thereby; but if you ſee you cannot guard yours but muſt of neceſſity loſe it, then be very circumſpect and ſee whether you can take a far better piece of his in caſe he takes yours, by advancing ſome other piece of yours in guard; for ſo as it often falls out, that yours which you had given over for loſt may be ſaved, whereas no other way could have done it.</p>
               <p>When an adverſe piece comes in your way, ſo that by it all may be taken, conſider with your ſelf firſt whether it be equal in worth to yours; next whether it can do you any damage in the next Draught, if not let it alone; for as it is beſt to play firſt, ſo it is to take laſt; unleſs as was ſaid you might take the piece clear, or get a better than that you loſe to take it, or at leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order him one Pawn in his taking your man that took his; but when you have the advantage be it but of one good piece for a worſe, or of a Pawn clear, then it is your beſt way to take man for man as often as you can; beſides you are to note, that whatſoever piece your adverſary plays moſt or beſt withall, be ſure, if it lie in your power, to deprive him thereof, though it be done with loſs of the like, or of one ſomewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as a Biſhop for a Knight; for by this means
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:179790:35"/>you may fruſtrate your adverſaries deſign and become as cunning as himſelf.</p>
               <p>Now the chief aim at Chefs is to give the Mate, which is when you ſo check the King of the adverſe party, that he can neither take the checking piece (becauſe it is guarded) nor cover the check, nor yet remove out of it.</p>
               <p>Your care ought to be in the interim how to deprive him of ſome of his beſt pieces, as his Queen or Rook; and the way to entrap a Queen is two-fold, Firſt by confining her to her King, ſo that ſhe may not remove from him for leaving him in check of an adverſe piece; Secondly, by bringing her to or eſpying her in ſuch a place as a Knight of yours may check her King, and the next draught take her. In the ſame manner you may ſerve a Biſhop if the adverſe Queen covers her ſlope-wiſe; but if ſhe ſtand not in ſuch a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture ſhe may be brought to it; entice her thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome unguarded man, which ſhe out of eagerneſs of taking for nothing, may indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly bring her ſelf into trouble.</p>
               <p>But if you intend to catch the Queen with a Knight, imagine that the adverſe King ſtands in his own place unremoved, and that the Queen hath brought her ſelf to ſtand in that place where the Kings Rooks Pawn ſtood; firſt, ſhe ſtanding in this poſture bring if you can one of your Knights to check her King in the third houſe before his own Biſhop; and if there be no man ready to take up your Knight, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:179790:35"/>he will take up the Queen at the next draught.</p>
               <p>The Rooks are alſo to be ſurprized two ways; firſt, by playing your Biſhop into your Knights Pawns firſt place of ſtanding, which Biſhop ſhall march aſlope towards the adverſe Rook of the oppoſite corner, which if you can make unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered of the Knights Pawn, your Biſhop will then undoubtedly take clear for nothing; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way is like that of ſurprizing the Queen with a Biſhop or a Knight; where you muſt take notice that your adverſaries Queens Rook is ſo much the eaſier to be taken with your Queens Knight, that that Knight at his third draught may check the King and take the ſame Rook at his fourth draught. There are ſeveral other ways to take a Rook, which practice muſt inform you.</p>
               <p>There is an ingenious way of taking a great man for a Pawn; when you eſpy two great men of your adverſaries ſtanding in one and the ſame rank, and but one houſe between them, then prepare a Guard (if you have it not ready to your hand) for a Pawn, which bring up to the rank next to them in the middle or front of both of them, and without doubt, if he ſave the one your Pawn will take the other; this way of taking is called a <hi>Fork</hi> or <hi>Dilemma.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The neateſt and moſt prejudicial trick you can put upon your adverſary at <hi>Cheſs</hi> is a Check by diſcovery, which may be thus effected; obſerve
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:179790:36"/>when you find your adverſaries King any way weakly guarded, or perhaps not at all, that is, eaſie to be checked, then before you bring that piece that can check him there to provide ſome other man in that courſe that checks him not; afterwards bring that piece of yours which will check him (your brought-piece being away) and then with all poſſible ſpeed remove away for that former piece where it may moſt annoy him, ſaying withall, <hi>Check by diſcovery of your laſt brought a piece:</hi> which he being compelled to cover or remove, you may do him a greater prejudice with that piece you removed from between the check at the next draught thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe you play with the <hi>White-men,</hi> he removes firſt his Kings Pawn a double draught forward, you anſwer him with the like play; he then plays out his Kings Knight in front of his Kings Biſhop's Pawn, you do the like with yours: that Knight of his takes your Kings Pawn, and your Knight takes his likewiſe; he advances the Queens Pawn, and removes to chaſe away or to take your Knight; you play up your white Queen one remove before your King to frighten his Knight alſo: he thinks it better to ſave his Knight from your Queen, than take yours with his Queens Pawn; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conveys him away into a more ſecure place; you play your Kings Knight in front of his Queens Biſhop's Pawn, and therewithall ſay
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:179790:36"/>
                  <hi>Check by diſcovery of your Queen;</hi> now let him cover this check by Diſcovery as well as he can, your Knight at the next draught will aſſuredly take his Queen. There are ſeveral other ways to make a diſcovery, and a Mate given with it, which is the nobleſt Mate of all.</p>
               <p>A Queen if loſt indangers much the Game; but if there be Pawns l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ft on either ſide, there is poſſibility of making a new Queen, and ſo by conſequence the renovation of the Game, which ten to one was loſt before: There are ſeveral ways to Mate this Queen and eſtate her in as great power as the former, for brevity ſake, two Pawns in files next one to the other, and plaid firſt one forward and the other back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cloſe together, is a good way to make a new Queen, eſpecially if any one of them be guarded underneath with a Rook, for ſo they will force their way before them, nor can any of them be taken without great difficulty and danger.</p>
               <p>As to ſhort Mates take theſe obſervations: having both placed your men and yours the firſt draught; ſuppoſe you advance your Kings Pawn forward one ſingle remove, your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary plays his Kings Pawn forward a double remove in his own file; you at your ſecond draught come out with your Queen upon that Pawn, placing her in the houſe forward of your Kings Rooks file, your enemy to guard his Kings Pawn plays forth his Queens Knight into
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:179790:37"/>the third Houſe of the Queens Biſhops file, you (hoping that he will not ſpy the attempt) bring not for your third draught your Kings Biſhop, which you place in the fourth houſe of your Queens Biſhops file, he not perceiving your intention judging all ſecure makes for your Queen with his Kings Knight, playing it in the front of his Kings Biſhops Pawn, either to chaſe her away or take her; you immediately upon this take up that Biſhops Pawn with your Queen, and for your fourth draught give him a Mate, which is called a <hi>Scholars Mate;</hi> becauſe any but young beginners may prevent it.</p>
               <p>You may alſo give a Mate at two draughts if you encounter with a raw Gameſter, playing after this manner; firſt remove his Kings Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Pawn a ſingle draught (which is ill play at firſt) you your Kings Pawn a ſingle remove, he his Kings Knights Pawn advanced a double re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move for his ſecond draught, you bringing out your Queen into the fifth houſe of your Kings Rooks file give him a Mate at your ſecond draught.</p>
               <p>There is another called a <hi>Blind-Mate,</hi> and that is when your Adverſary gives you a check that you cannot avoid by any means, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a <hi>Mate abſolute;</hi> but he not ſeeing it to be a Mate, ſays only to you <hi>check,</hi> and it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called a <hi>Blind-Mate;</hi> this ſhould be both loſs of Game and ſtake if you before agree not to the contrary.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:179790:37"/>
               <p>A <hi>Stale</hi> may be termed a Mate and no Mate, an end of the Play but no end of the Game, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it properly ſhould be ended with a <hi>Check-Mate.</hi> The Stale is thus: when his King hath the worſt of the Game, and brought to ſuch a ſtrait, that he hath but one place to flie unto, and the purſuing King is ſo unadviſed as to bar him of that place or ſtop it without checking him, the diſtreſſed King being no way able to remove but in Check, and having no other piece of his own that he can play, then it is a <hi>Stale</hi> and a loſt Game to him that gives it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that follows the flying King gives him check as long as he hath any place to flye to; but when he hath none left to avoid his check, let him then ſay <hi>check-Mate,</hi> and both Game and Stake are won.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, there is another term uſed in Cheſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing, and that is called a <hi>Dead-Game,</hi> which makes (if I may ſay improperly) an endleſs end of the Game, both Gameſters ſaving their Stakes: and thus it is, when the Aſſailant falls to take all that comes near, careleſly giving man for man, ſo that it happens that either King hath but one man apiece left him, the Aſſailant fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his eager purſuit takes his Adverſaries man, not minding that his King can take his alſo, ſo that the Kings loſing all their men and they being ſo unable to come ſo near as to grapple the Game is ended, but the Stakes on both ſides are ſaved.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:179790:38"/>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this Game with the Laws of Cheſs, which are theſe following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What Piece ſoever of your own you touch or lift from the point whereon it ſtandeth, you muſt play it for that draught if you can, and into what houſe you ſet your Man there it muſt ſtand for that draught, according to the ſaying at this Game, <hi>Touch and take, out of hand and ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If you take up your Adverſaries man, and after think beſt to let it ſtand untaken, before you ſet your piece in place thereof, you muſt cry him mercy or loſe the Game.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If your Adverſary play a falſe draught, and you ſee it not till you play your next draught 'twill then be too late to challenge him for it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If you play a falſe draught through mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, and your Adverſary take no notice for his advantage, and plays his next draught, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not recall it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If you miſplace your men, and ſo play a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while, and then diſcover it, it lies in your Adverſaries power to continue or begin the Game.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Pawns may be plaid a double remove for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for their firſt draught, but no Pawn hath that priviledge without permiſſion, on whoſe next file on either ſide a Pawn of your Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries is already advanced as far as your fourth rank.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:179790:38"/>
               <p n="7">7. The ſtanding of the King ought to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in his ſhifting and not as you pleaſe to place him as ſome men play.</p>
               <p n="8">8. If your King ſtand in the check of any adverſe piece, and you have plaid one draught or more without avoiding the check, your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary may ſay, <hi>check</hi> to you when he liſteth, and for your draught then make you avoid that check you ſtood in, though it may be to your great peril.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If any one condition by wager, that he will give Mate or win the Game, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary brings it to a <hi>Dead-Game,</hi> though he ſave the firſt Stake yet he loſeth the Wager.</p>
               <p n="10">10. He that gives over the Game before it is finiſhed, without the conſent of his Adverſary, loſeth his Stake.</p>
               <p>Many more Obſervations might be here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted for the underſtanding of this noble Game, which I am forced to wave to avoid prolixity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Principal Games on CARDS. PICKET.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore you begin the Game at Picket, you muſt throw out of the Pack the <hi>Deuces, Treys, Fours</hi> and <hi>Fives,</hi> and play with the reſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:179790:39"/>of the <hi>Cards,</hi> which are in number thirty and ſix.</p>
               <p>The uſual <hi>Set</hi> is an hundred, not but that you may make it more or leſs; the laſt Card deals and the worſt is the Dealers.</p>
               <p>The Cards are all valued according to the number of the ſpots they bear, the Ace only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, which wins all other Cards, and goes for eleven.</p>
               <p>The Dealer ſhuffles, and the other cuts, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering what number he pleaſeth at a time, ſo that he exceed not four nor deal under two, leaving twelve on the Table between them.</p>
               <p>He that is the elder, having lookt over his Cards, and finding never a Court-Card among them, ſays <hi>I have</hi> a blank, and I intend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card ſuch a number of Cards, and that you may ſee mine, diſcard you as many as you intend; this done, the Eldeſt ſhows his Cards and reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ten for the blank, then taking up his Cards again he diſcards thoſe which he judgeth moſt fit: here note he is always bound to that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber which he firſt propounded. This being done, he takes in as many from the Stock as he laid out; and if it ſhould chance to fall out that the other hath a <hi>Blank</hi> too, the youngers <hi>Blank</hi> ſhall bar the former and hinder his <hi>Picy</hi> and <hi>Repicy,</hi> though the eldeſt hands <hi>Blank</hi> conſiſts of the biggeſt Cards.</p>
               <p>It is no ſmall advantage to the eldeſt to have the benefit of diſcarding, becauſe he may take
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:179790:39"/>in eight of the twelve in the Stock diſcarding as many of his own for them, nor but that if he find it more advantageous he may take in a leſs number; after this the Antagoniſt may take in what he thinks fit, acquitting his hand of the like number. Here note, that let the Game be never ſo good, the Gameſters are both obliged to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card one Card at leaſt. After the diſcarding you muſt conſider the <hi>Ruff,</hi> that is how much you can make of one ſuit; the eldeſt ſpeaks firſt, and if the youngeſt makes no more the <hi>Ruff</hi> is good, and ſets up one for every ten he can produce; as for example, for thirty reckon three, for forty four, and ſo onward; withall take notice you are to count as many for thirty five as for forty, and as much for forty five as fifty, and ſo of the reſt; but from thirty five to thirty nine you muſt count no more than for thirty five, and ſo from thirty to thirty four count no more than for thirty; and this Rule is to be obſerved in all other higher numbers.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Sequences</hi> and their value after the <hi>Ruff</hi> is plaid, the Elder acquaints you with his <hi>Sequences</hi> (if he have them) and they are <hi>Tierces, Quarts, Quints, Sixieſms, Septieſms, Huictieſms</hi> and <hi>Neufieſms,</hi> as thus; ſix, ſeven, and eight; nine, ten, and Knave; Queen, King, and Ace; which laſt is called a Tierce Major, becauſe it is the higheſt. A Quart is a ſequence of four Cards, a Quint of five, a Sixiſm of ſix, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe Sequences take their denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:179790:40"/>from the higheſt Card in the Sequence. It is a Tierce Major or a Tierce of an Ace when there is Queen, King and Ace, a Tierce of a King when the King is the beſt Card; a Tierce of a Queen when there is neither King nor Ace, and ſo till you come to the loweſt Tierce, which is a Tierce of an eight. You muſt reckon for every Tierce three, for a Quart four, but for a Quint fifteen, for a Sixieſm ſixteen, and ſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; now what ever you can make of all you muſt add to your Blank, and count the whole together.</p>
               <p>Here note that the biggeſt Tierce, Quart, or other Sequence, although there be but one of them, makes all the others leſs Sequences uſeleſs unto him be they never ſo many; and he that hath the biggeſt Sequence by vertue thereof reckons all his leſs Sequences, though his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries Sequences be greater, and otherwiſe would have drowned them.</p>
               <p>Farther obſerve, that a Quart drowns a Tierce, and a Quint a Quart, and ſo of the reſt, ſo that he who hath a Sixieſm may reckon his Tierces, Quarts, or Quints, though the other may happen to have Tierce, Quart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of higher value than the others are that hath the Sixieſm; trace the ſame method in all the other like Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</p>
               <p>After you have manifeſted your Sequences, you come to reckon your three Aces, three Kings, three Queens, three Knaves, or three
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:179790:40"/>Tens, as for Nines, Eights, Sevens, and Sixes, they have no place in this account; for every Ternary you count three, and they are in value as it is in Sequences; Aces the higheſt and beſt, Kings next, after theſe Queens, then Knaves, and laſt of all Tens. The higher drowns the lower here as in the Sequences. He that hath three Aces may reckon his three Queens, Knaves, or Tens, if he have them, though the other hath three Kings; and this is done by reaſon of his higher Ternary. Now he that hath four Aces, four Kings, four Queens, four Knaves, or four Tens, for each reckons fourteen, which is the reaſon they are called Quatorzes.</p>
               <p>Now they begin to play the Cards, the elder begins and younger follows in ſuit as at Whisk, and for every Ace, King, Queen, Knave, or Ten, he reckons one.</p>
               <p>A Card once play'd muſt not be recall'd, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he have a Card of the ſame ſuit in his hand, if the elder hand plays an Ace, King, Queen, or Ten, for every ſuch Card he is to reckon one, which he adds to the number of his Game be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and if the other be able to play upon it a higher Card of the ſame ſuit, he wins the Trick, and reckons one for his Card as well as the other. Whoſoever wins the laſt Trick reckons two for it, if he win it with a Ten, but if with any Card under, he reckons but one; then they tell their Cards, and he that hath the moſt is to reckon Ten for them.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:179790:41"/>
               <p>After this, each Perſon ſets up his Game with Counters, and if the <hi>ſet</hi> be not up, deal again; now a <hi>ſet</hi> is won after this manner, admit that each party is ſo forward in his Game that he wants but four or five to be up, if it ſo happens that any of the two have a Blank, he wins the <hi>ſet,</hi> becauſe the Blanks are always firſt reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but if no Blanks, then comes the Ruff, next your Sequences, then your Aces, Kings, Queens, Knaves, and Tens, next what Cards are reckoned in play, and laſt of all the Cards you have won. If any of the Gameſters can reckon, either in Blanks, Ruffs, Sequences, Aces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> up to thirty in his own hand, without playing a Card, and before the other can reckon any thing, inſtead of thirty he ſhall reckon ninety, and as many as he reckons after above his thirty, adding them to his ninety; this is known by the name of a <hi>Repicy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, he that can make in like manner, what by Blank, Ruff, Sequences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> up to the ſaid number, before the other hath play'd a Card, or reckoned any thing, inſtead of thirty he reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſixty, and this is called a <hi>Picy.</hi> Here note, that if you can but remember to call for your <hi>Picy,</hi> or <hi>Repicy,</hi> before you deal again, you ſhall loſe neither of them, otherwiſe you muſt.</p>
               <p>He that wins more than his own Cards reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Ten, but he that wins all the Cards reckons Forty, and this is called a <hi>Capet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Rules belonging to this Game are theſe.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:179790:41"/>If the Dealer give more Cards than his due, whether through miſtake or otherwiſe, it lieth in the choice of the elder hand whether he ſhall deal again or no, or whether it ſhall be play'd out.</p>
               <p>He that forgets to reckon his Blank, Ruff, Sequences, Aces, Kings, or the like; and hath begun to play his Cards cannot recall them. So it is with him that ſheweth not his Ruff before he play his firſt Card, loſing abſolutely all the advantage thereof.</p>
               <p>He that miſreckons any thing, and hath play'd one of his Cards, and his Adverſary finds at the beginning, middle, or end of the Game, that he had not what he reckoned, for his puniſhment he ſhall be debar'd from reckoning any thing he really hath, and his Adverſary ſhall reckon all he hath, yet the other ſhall make all he can in play. He that takes in more Cards than he diſcardeth is liable to the ſame penalty.</p>
               <p>He that throws up his Cards imagining he hath loſt the Game, mingling them with other Cards on the Table though afterward he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his miſtake, yet he is not allowed to take up his Cards and play them out.</p>
               <p>No man is permitted to diſcard twice in one dealing.</p>
               <p>He that hath a <hi>Blank,</hi> his <hi>Blank</hi> ſhall hinder the other <hi>Picy</hi> and <hi>Repicy,</hi> although he hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſhew but his <hi>Blank.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that hath four Aces, Kings, Queens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:179790:42"/>dealt him and after he hath diſcarded one of the four reckons the other three, and the other ſay to him <hi>it is good;</hi> he is bound to tell the other, if he ask him what Ace, King, Queen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he wants.</p>
               <p>If after the Cards are cleanly cut, either of the Gameſters know the upper Card by the backſide, notwithſtanding this the Cards muſt not be ſhuffled again. In like manner, if the Dealer perceive the other hath cut himſelf an Ace, and would therefore ſhuffle again, this is not permitted; and if a Card be found faced, it ſhall be no argument to deal again, but muſt deal on; but if two be found faced, then may he ſhuffle again.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Whoſoever is found changing or taking back again any of his Cards, he ſhall loſe the Game, and be accounted a Foul Player.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The Game at GLEEK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEuces and Treys muſt be caſt out as uſeleſs in this Game, then lifting for Dealing the leaſt Card deals: The number of Perſons playing muſt be three, neither more nor leſs, and moſt frequently they play at Farthing, Half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penny,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:179790:42"/>or Penny-Gleek, which in play will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount conſiderably.</p>
               <p>The Dealer delivers the Cards by four till e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one hath twelve, and the reſt are laid on the Table, for the Stock, being in number eight, ſeven whereof are bought and the Ace is turned up; the turn'd up Card is the Dealers; and if it be Tiddy turn'd up is four apiece from each to the Dealer.</p>
               <p>The Ace is called <hi>Tib,</hi> the Knave <hi>Tom,</hi> the four of Trumps Tiddy, <hi>Tib</hi> the Ace is fifteen in hand and eighteen in play, becauſe it wins a Trick, <hi>Tom</hi> the Knave is nine, and <hi>Tiddy</hi> is four, the fifth Towſer, the ſixth Tumbler, which if in hand Towſer is five and Tumbler ſix, and ſo double if turn'd up, and the King and Queen of Trumps is three.</p>
               <p>The eldeſt hand bids for the ſtock in hopes of bettering his Game, though ſometimes it makes it worſe: the firſt penny you bid is twelve, thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, and ſo on; if at ſixteen they ſay take it, and none will venture more for it, he is bound to take it, that is taking in ſeven Cards, and putting out ſeven in their ſtead, and muſt pay beſides eight to one, and eight to the other of the Gameſters for buying, if any odd money be given, as 15, 17, or the like, the eldeſt hand uſually claims it, or elſe it is given to the box; but if he have <hi>Mournival, Gleek</hi> or <hi>Tiddy</hi> in his hand after he hath taken in the Stock, he bates for them all, and ſo poſſibly may gain by
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:179790:43"/>it, if he have a good hand and pay for his buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two.</p>
               <p>Here you muſt note that if <hi>Tib</hi> be turned up it is fifteen to the Dealer in reckoning after play, but he muſt not make uſe of it in play be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trump-Card, for then 'twould make him eighteen, becauſe it would win a Trick which is three more.</p>
               <p>Next you ſpeak for the <hi>Ruff,</hi> and he that hath moſt of a ſuit in his hand wins it, unleſs ſome of the Gameſters have four Aces and then he gains the <hi>Ruff,</hi> though you have never ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a ſuit in your hand. If any wins a <hi>Ruff</hi> and forgets to ſhow it before a Card plaid he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it, and he that ſhews any for a <hi>Ruff</hi> after ſhall have it.</p>
               <p>The firſt or eldeſt ſays, <hi>I'le vye the Ruff,</hi> the next ſays, <hi>I'le ſee it,</hi> and the third, <hi>I'le ſee it and revie it: I'le ſee your revie,</hi> ſays the firſt; becauſe he hath as many in his hand as another: the middle probably ſays, <hi>I'le not meddle with it;</hi> then they ſhew their Cards, and he that hath moſt of a ſuit wins ſix pence or farthings ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Game of him that holds out longeſt, and four of the other that ſaid he would ſee it, but after refuſed to meddle with it; but if any of the three Gameſters ſays he hath nothing to ſay as to the Ruff he pays but a farthing, half-penny, penny, according as the Game is aforeſaid; and if the eldeſt and ſecond hand paſs the Ruff the youngeſt hath power to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:179790:43"/>double it, and then it is to be plaid for the next deal, and if any forgets to call for the double Ruff, it is to be play'd for the next deal after that.</p>
               <p>Sometimes one of the Gameſters having all of a ſuit in his hand bids high for the Ruff, and the other having four Aces is reſolved to bid higher, ſo that it ſometimes amounts to ſixteen and more, then <hi>I'le ſee it and revie,</hi> ſaith one; <hi>I'le ſee it and revie,</hi> ſaith another, that is eight to the winner, and all above is but two a time, as it may be they will ſay, <hi>I'le ſee it and revie it again, and I'le ſee that and revie it again,</hi> ſaith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, for which ſeeing and revying they reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but two, after that it is once come to eight; but he that hath the four Aces carrieth it clearly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Buying or bidding for the Ruff is when you are in likelihood to go in for Mournival, Gleek, or increaſe of Trumps, that ſo if you have bad Cards, you may ſave your buyings and your Cards too, whereas otherwiſe you may loſe all.</p>
               <p>If you call for either Mournival or Gleek, and have lay'd them out in the ſtock, if you be taken in it, for forfeit double what you receive.</p>
               <p>Sometimes out of policy or a vapour they will vie when they have not above thirty in their hands, and the reſt may have forty or fifty, and being afraid to ſee it, the firſt many
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:179790:44"/>times wins out of a meer bravado, and this is good play though he acquaint you with it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>A Mournival of Aces is eight, of Kings ſix, of Queens four, and a Mournival of Knaves two a piece.</p>
               <p>A Gleek of Aces is four, of Kings three, of Queens two, and of Knaves one a piece from the other two Gameſters.</p>
               <p>A Mournival is either all the Aces, the four Kings, Queens, or Knaves, and a Gleek is three of any of the aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>Here note, that twenty two are your Cards; if you win nothing but the Cards that were dealt you, you loſe ten; if you have neither <hi>Tib, Tom, Tiddy, King, Queen, Mournival,</hi> nor <hi>Gleek,</hi> you loſe becauſe you count as many Cards as you had in tricks, which muſt be few by reaſon of the badneſs of your hand; if you have Tib, Tom, King, and Queen of Trumps in your hand, you have thirty by honours, that is, eight above your own Cards, beſides the Cards you win by them in play. If you have Tom only, which is Nine and the King of Trumps, which is three, then you reckon from twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen, till you come to two and twenty, and then every Card wins ſo many half-pence, pence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as you play'd for; if you are under two and twenty you loſe as many.</p>
               <p>Here note, that before the Cards are dealt,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:179790:44"/>it is requiſite to demand, whether the Gameſters will play at <hi>Tiddy,</hi> or leave it out, it being a Card that is apt to be forgotten; and know, that it is lookt upon as very foul play to call for a Gleek of Kings, Aces, Queens, or Knaves, when the perſon hath but two in his hands. If you diſcard wrong, <hi>i. e.</hi> lay out but 5 or 6 Cards, if you call for any Gleek or Mournivals, you loſe them all if it be found out that you ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card. Let this ſuffice for this noble and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Game or Recreation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>L'OMBRE, a Spaniſh Game.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are ſeveral ſorts of this Game called <hi>L'Ombre,</hi> but that which is the chief is called <hi>Renegado,</hi> at which three only can play, to whom are dealt nine Cards apiece, ſo that by diſcarding the eights, nines and tens, there will remain thirteen Cards in the Stock; there is no Trump but what the Player pleaſeth; the firſt hand hath always the liberty to play or paſs, after him the ſecond, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are two ſorts of Counters for Stakes, the greater and the leſſer, which laſt have the ſame proportion to the other as a penny to a ſhilling: of the great Counters each man Stakes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:179790:45"/>one for the Game, and one of the leſſer for paſſing, and for the hand when eldeſt, and for every Card taken in one Counter.</p>
               <p>There are two ſuits, Black and Red; of the Black there is firſt the <hi>Spadillo,</hi> or Ace of Spades; the <hi>Mallillio</hi> or black Deuce, the <hi>Basto</hi> or Ace of Clubs; the King, the Queen, the Knave, the ſeven, the ſix, the five, four, and three. Of the Red Suit there is the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dillo, Punto, Mallillio,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spadillo</hi> or Ace of Spades, is always the firſt Card, and always Trump, and the <hi>Basto</hi> or Ace of Clubs is always third; of the Black there is 11 Trumps, of the Red 12. The Red Ace enters into the fourth place when it is Trump, and it is called <hi>Punto</hi> then, otherwiſe only called an Ace.</p>
               <p>The leaſt ſmall Cards of the Red are always beſt, and the moſt of the Black; except the Deuce and Red Seven, which are called the <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lillio</hi>'s and always ſecond when Trump. The <hi>Matadors</hi> (or killing Cards) which are the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dillo, Mallillio,</hi> and <hi>Baſto</hi> are the chief Cards, and when they are all in a hand the others pay for them three of the greater Counters apiece; and with theſe three for foundation you may count as many <hi>Matadors</hi> as you have Cards in an interrupted ſeries of Trumps; for all which the others are to pay you one Counter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece.</p>
               <p>He who hath the firſt hand hath his choice
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:179790:45"/>(as aforeſaid) of playing the <hi>Game,</hi> of naming the Trump, and of taking in as many and as few Cards as he liſt, and after him the ſecond, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having demanded whether any one will play without <hi>taking in,</hi> you oblige your ſelf to take in though your Game be never ſo good, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you do well to conſider it before.</p>
               <p>If you name not the Trump before you look on the Cards which you have taken in, any other may prevent you and name what Trump they pleaſe; if you know not of two ſuits which to name Trump firſt, the black ſuit is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the Red, becauſe there are fewer Trumps of it. Secondly, you were beſt to chuſe that ſuit of which you have not the King, becauſe beſides your three Trumps you have a King which is as good as a fourth. When you have the choice of going in three <hi>Matadors,</hi> or the two black Aces with three or four other Trumps, if the Stakes be great you are to chuſe this laſt, as moſt like to win moſt Tricks; if it be but a ſimple Stake you are to chuſe the firſt, becauſe the ſix Counters you are to receive for the three <hi>Matadors</hi> more than countervail the four or five you loſe for the Game.</p>
               <p>He that hath the firſt hand is never to take in nor play, unleſs he have three ſure Tricks in his hand at leaſt; to underſtand which the better, know the end of the Game is to win moſt Tricks, whence he that can win five Tricks of the nine hath a ſure Game; or if he win four and can ſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:179790:46"/>divide the Tricks as one may win two, the other three, if not it's either <hi>Codillio,</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puesto,</hi> ſo the Player loſeth and maketh good the Stakes.</p>
               <p>It is called <hi>Codillio</hi> when the Player is <hi>beaſted,</hi> and another wins more Tricks than he, when this takes up the Stakes and the other makes it good.</p>
               <p>Here note, although the other two always combine to make him loſe, yet they all do their beſt (for the common good) to hinder any one from winning, only ſtriving to make it <hi>Repueſto,</hi> which is when the player wins no more Tricks than another, in which caſe the Player doubles the Stake without any ones winning it, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſo for the advantage of the next Player.</p>
               <p>Here note that Kings of any ſuit are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as good Trumps, mean while all other Cards but Kings and Trumps are to be diſcarded.</p>
               <p>The Player having taken in, the next is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the goodneſs of the Game, and to take in more or leſs for the beſt advantage of his Game; neither is any for the ſaving a Counter or two to neglect the taking in, that the other may commodiouſly make up his Game with what Cards he hath left, and that no good Cards may lie dormant in the Stock, except the Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er playeth without taking in, when they may refuſe to take in, if they imagine he hath all the Game.</p>
               <p>When one hath a ſure Game in his hand, he
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:179790:46"/>is to play without taking in, then the others are to give him each one of the great Counters as he is to give them, if he play without taking in a Game that is not ſure and loſeth it; if you win all the Tricks in your hand or the <hi>Voll,</hi> they likewiſe are to give you one Counter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, but then you are to declare before the fifth Trick that you intend to play for the <hi>Voll,</hi> that ſo they keep their beſt Cards, which elſe, ſeeing you win five Tricks (or the Game) they may careleſly caſt away.</p>
               <p>If you renounce you are to double the Stake, as alſo if you have more or fewer Cards than nine, to which end you muſt carefully count your Cards in dealing and taking in before you look on them; beſides according to the rigour of the Game if you ſpeak any thing tending to the diſcovery thereof, either in your own hand or anothers (excepting <hi>Gagno</hi>) or <hi>play ſo,</hi> to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the making of <hi>Repueſto</hi> or <hi>Codillio,</hi> you are not fit to play.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, that in playing Trumps, if any plays an ordinary one, and you have only the three beſt Cards or <hi>Matadors</hi> ſingly or jointly in your hands, you may refuſe to play them without renouncing, becauſe of the priviledge which theſe Cards have, that none but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Cards can force them out of your hand.</p>
               <p>You are to ſay nothing when you play your Card, but I <hi>paſs</hi> or <hi>play,</hi> or <hi>gagno,</hi> or <hi>gagno del
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:179790:47"/>Re</hi> when you play your Queen to hinder them from taking it with the King.</p>
               <p>Now ſince it is impoſſible to provide againſt all accidents in the Game, only take notice of theſe general Rules.</p>
               <p>Firſt, never win more than one Trick if you cannot win more than two, becauſe of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage you give the Player by it, in dividing the Tricks.</p>
               <p>Secondly, you are to win the Trick always from the Player if you can, unleſs you let it paſs for meer advantage, where the ſecond is to let paſs to the third if he have the likelier Game to beaſt the Player, or if he be likelier to win it. There may be diverſe advantages in refuſing to take the Players Trick; but the chief is, if you have the <hi>Tenaces</hi> in your hand, that is two Cards, and if you have the leading, you are ſure to loſe one of them; if the Player lead to you, you are ſure to win them both; For example, if you have <hi>Spadillio</hi> and <hi>Baſto</hi> in your hand, and he have the <hi>Mallillio</hi> and another Trump, if you lead you loſe one of them; for either you play your <hi>Spadillio,</hi> and he plays the leſſer Trump upon it, and wins your <hi>Baſto</hi> the next Trick with his <hi>Mallillio,</hi> and ſo the contrary; whereas if he leads he loſeth; for if he leads his <hi>Mallillio</hi> you win it with your <hi>Spadillio,</hi> and with your <hi>Baſto</hi> win the other Trump, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you are not ſure to win five Tricks, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving only three <hi>Matadors,</hi> and Kings your auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:179790:47"/>Cards; if you have the leading, play firſt a <hi>Matador</hi> or two before you play your Kings to fetch out his Trumps which might have trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped them, and if you have three <hi>Matadors</hi> with two other Trumps, your beſt way is to play your <hi>Matadors</hi> firſt to ſee where the Trumps lie; if both follow, you are ſure if the Trump be red there remains only one Trump in their hands, if black none at all.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if the Players have but a weak Game, they are to imitate cunning Beaſt-players in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Tricks, and conſulting to play their Cards. To conclude, lay your Tricks angle-wiſe, that you may the more facilely compute them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The Game at GRIBBIDGE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT Cribbidge there are no Cards to be thrown out, but all are made uſe of; and the number of the Set is ſixty one.</p>
               <p>It is an advantage to deal, by reaſon of the Crib, and therefore you muſt lift for it, and he that hath the leaſt Card deals.</p>
               <p>There are but two Players at this Game, the one ſhuffles and the other cuts, the Dealer deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:179790:48"/>out the Cards one by one, to his Antagoniſt firſt and himſelf laſt, till five apiece be dealt to one another; the reſt being ſet down in view on the Table, each looketh on his Game, and ordereth his Cards for the beſt advantage.</p>
               <p>He that deals makes out the beſt Cards he can for his Crib, and the other the worſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will do him as little good as he can, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Crib; which Crib is four Cards, two a piece, which they lay out upon the Table, not knowing nor ſeeing one anothers Cards, and then they turn up a Card from the parcel that was left of dealing, and each of them may make uſe of that Card to help them on in their Game in hand, and when they have play'd out their three Cards, and ſet up with Counters their Games in their hands, the Crib is the others the next deal, and ſo they take it by turns.</p>
               <p>The value of the Cards is thus: Any fifteen upon the Cards is two, whether nine and ſix, ten and five, King and five, ſeven and eight, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Pair</hi> is two, a <hi>Pair-Royal</hi> ſix, a double <hi>Pair-Royal</hi> twelve, <hi>Sequences of three</hi> is two, <hi>Sequences of four</hi> is four, <hi>of five</hi> five, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo is a <hi>Fluſh of three,</hi> three; <hi>of four,</hi> four, &amp;c. <hi>Knave Noddy</hi> is one in hand and two to the Dealer; that is, if you have a Knave of that ſuit which is turned up, it is <hi>Knave Noddy.</hi> A Pair of Aces, Kings, Queens, Knaves, Tens, &amp;c. is two; Three Aces, Kings, Queens, &amp;c. is a <hi>Pair-Royal;</hi> a double <hi>Pair-Royal</hi> is four Aces,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:179790:48"/>four Kings, four Queens, &amp;c. and is twelve Games to him that hath them.</p>
               <p>Having lookt on your Cards, you count your Game after this manner: Suppoſe you have in your hand a Nine and two Sixes, after you have laid out two Cards for the Crib, that makes you ſix Games, becauſe there is two fifteens and a pair, by adding your Nine to the two Sixes, and if a Six chance to be turn'd up, then you have twelve Games in your hand; for though you muſt not take the turn'd up Card into your hand, yet you may make what uſe you can of it in counting, ſo that the three Sixes makes you ſix, being a <hi>Pair-Royal,</hi> and the Nine added to every Six makes three fifteens, which ſix more added to the former, makes twelve, which you muſt ſet up with Counters or otherwiſe, that your Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent may know what you are, though you muſt not ſee his Cards, nor he yours; if you think he plays foul by reckoning too much, you may count them after the hand is play'd.</p>
               <p>Thus you have ſet up your twelve, your Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite it may be hath four, five, and ſix in his hand; that is two, becauſe of <hi>Sequences of three;</hi> then it is two more becauſe it is four, five, and ſix; again, taking in the counting ſix that is turn'd up, that is in all four, then there is fifteen and fifteen, four and five is nine, and ſix is fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen, and then with the ſix turn'd up 'tis fifteen more, which makes eight Games, this he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſets up, keeping his Cards undiſcovered.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:179790:49"/>Here note, he that deals not ſets up three in lieu thereof.</p>
               <p>Having thus done, he that dealt not plays firſt, ſuppoſe it a ſix, if you have a nine play it, that makes fifteen, for which ſet up two, the next may play a four which makes nineteen, you a ſix twenty five, and he a five that is thirty, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not able to come in, having a ſix in your hand, he ſets up one, (for it is one and thirty you aim at in playing the Cards), becauſe he is moſt, and two for <hi>Sequences</hi> four, five, and ſix, which were his four after the fifteen, your five and his ſix; and that doth not hinder them from being <hi>Sequences,</hi> though the ſix was play'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the four and the five; but if an Ace, Nine, King, Queen, or the like, had been play'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, they had been no <hi>Sequences;</hi> ſo the two for the Sequences, and the one for thirty being moſt (as at one and thirty) makes him three, which he muſt ſet up to the reſt of his Game, and in this playing of the Cards you may make <hi>Pairs, Sequences, Fluſh, Fifteens, Pair-Royals,</hi> and double <hi>Pair-Royals,</hi> if you can, though that is rarely ſeen.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, you look upon your Crib, that is the two Cards apiece laid out at firſt, which is the Dealers; if he find no Games in them, nor help by the Card that was turn'd up, which he takes into his hand, then he is bilkt, and ſometimes it ſo happens that he is both bilkt in hand and crib. Thus they play and deal by
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:179790:49"/>turns till the Game of ſixty one be up.</p>
               <p>Here note, if you get the Game before your Adverſary is forty five (forty four will not do it) you muſt then ſay, I have <hi>lurkt</hi> you, and that is a double Game for whatever you play'd with, ſix ſhilling, or a greater ſum.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>A Game at ALL-FOURS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALL-FO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RS</hi> is a Game very much play'd in <hi>Kent,</hi> and very well it may, ſince from thence it drew its firſt original; and although the Game may be lookt upon as trivial and inconſiderable, yet I have known <hi>Kentiſh</hi> Gentlemen and others of very conſiderable note, who have play'd great ſums of money at it, yet that adds not much to the worth of the Game, for a Man may play away an eſtate at <hi>One and Thirty;</hi> as I knew one loſe a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſum at <hi>moſt at three throws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Game I conceive is called <hi>All-Fours</hi> from <hi>Highest, Lowest, Jack</hi> and <hi>Game,</hi> which is the Set as ſome play it, but you may make from ſeven to fifteen, or more if you pleaſe, but commonly eleven.</p>
               <p>There are but two can play at it at a time, and they muſt lift for dealing, the higheſt Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:179790:50"/>deals, who delivers to his adverſary three Cards, and to himſelf the like, and the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and having ſix apiece, he turns up a Card which is Trump; if Jack (and that is any Knave) it is one to the Dealer.</p>
               <p>If he to whom the Cards were dealt after peruſal of his Game like them not, he hath the liberty of begging one; if the Dealer refuſe to give him one, then he deals three apiece more, but if he then turns up a Card of the ſame ſuit, he deals further till he turns up a Card of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuit.</p>
               <p>Here note, That an Ace is four, a King is three, a Queen is two, a Knave one, and a Ten is ten.</p>
               <p>Now you muſt play down your Cards, but to what advantage I cannot here preſcribe, it muſt be according to the Cards you have in your hand managed by your judgment to the beſt advantage.</p>
               <p>Having play'd your Cards you reckon, if you are higheſt and loweſt of what is Trumps, you reckon two; if you are only higheſt but one, and the like of Jack and Game; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times you are higheſt, loweſt, Jack, and Game, and then you muſt reckon four; the Game is he that tells moſt after the Cards are play'd, and therefore a Ten is a very ſignificant Card, which crafty Gameſters know ſo well that they will frequently take out of a Pack two Tens, and hide them contrary to the knowledge of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:179790:50"/>which is a great advantage to this foul player, if he play of the ſame ſuit of theſe Tens he hath abſconded, for it muſt of neceſſity ſecure him from loſing the Game.</p>
               <p>Here note, That he that wins Jack wins one alſo; and furthermore obſerve that for advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage reneging is allowable if you have Trumps in your hand to trump it.</p>
               <p>There is another ſort of <hi>All-fours</hi> called <hi>Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-All-Fours,</hi> at which they play One and Thirty up, and in this Game the Dealer hath a great advantage, for if he turn up an Ace it is four, a King three, a Queen two, and a Knave one, and theſe are the ſame alſo in play. A Ten is the beſt Card for making up.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Engliſh Ruff and Honours, and Whiſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>RUff and Honours (<hi>alias</hi> Slamm) and Whiſt, are Games ſo commonly known in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in all parts thereof, that every Child al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of Eight Years old hath a competent knowledge in that recreation, and therefore I am unwilling to ſpeak any thing more of them than this, that there may be a great deal of art uſed in Dealing and playing at theſe Games which differ very little one from the other.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:179790:51"/>
               <p>In playing your Cards you muſt have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe altogether to your own judgment or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, ſtill making the beſt of a bad Market; and though you have but mean Cards in your own hand, yet you may play them ſo ſuitable to thoſe in your Partners hand, that he may either Trump them, or play the beſt of that ſuit on the Board.</p>
               <p>You ought to have a ſpecial eye to what Cards are play'd out, that you may know by that means either what to play if you lead, or how to trump ſecurely and advantagiouſly. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neging or renouncing, that is, not following ſuit when you have it in your hand, is very foul play, and he that doth it ought to forfeit one, or the Game upon a Game, and he that loſeth dealing loſeth one, or a trick as you make it.</p>
               <p>At Ruff and Honours, by ſome called Slamm, you have in the Pack all the Deuces, and the reaſon is, becauſe four playing having dealt twelve a piece, there are four left for the Stock, the uppermoſt whereof is turn'd up, and that is Trumps, he that hath the Ace of that, Ruffs; that is, he takes in thoſe four Cards, and lays out four others in their lieu; the four Honours are the Ace, King, Queen, and Knave; he that hath three Honours in his own hand, his partner not having the fourth ſets up Eight by Cards, that is two tricks; if he hath all four, then Sixteen, that is four tricks; it is all one if the two Partners make them three or
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:179790:51"/>four between them, as if one had them. If the Honours are equally divided among the Gameſters of each ſide, then they ſay Honours are ſplit. If either ſide are at eight Groats he hath the benefit of calling Can-ye, if he hath two Honours in his hand, and if the other anſwers one, the Game is up, which is nine in all, but if he hath more than two he ſhows them, and then it is one and the ſame thing; but if he forgets to call after playing a trick, he loſeth the advantage of Can-ye for that deal.</p>
               <p>All Cards are of value as they are ſuperiour one to another, as a Ten wins a Nine if not Trumps, ſo a Queen, a Knave in like manner; but the leaſt Trump will win the higheſt Card of any other Card; where note the Ace is the higheſt.</p>
               <p>Whiſt is a Game not much differing from this, only they put out the Deuces and take in no ſtock; and is called Whiſt from the ſilence that is to be obſerved in the play; they deal as before, playing four, two of a ſide, (ſome play at two handed, or three handed Whiſt; if three handed, always two ſtrive to ſuppreſs and keep down the riſing-man), I ſay they deal to each Twelve a piece, and the Trump is the bottom Card. The manner of crafty playing, the number of the Game Nine, Honours and dignity of other Cards are all alike, and he that wins moſt tricks is moſt forward to win the ſet.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:179790:52"/>
               <p>He that can by craft over-look his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries Game hath a great advantage, for by that means he may partly know what to play ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; or if he can have ſome petty glimpſe of his Partners hand. There is a way by winking, or the Fingers to diſcover to their Partners what Honours they have, as by the wink of one eye, or putting one Finger on the Noſe or Table, it ſignifies one Honour, ſhutting both the eyes, two; placing three fingers or four on the Table, three or four Honours. They have ſeveral ways of ſecuring an Honour or more in the bottom when they deal, either to their Partners or ſelves; if to their Partner they place in the ſecond lift next the top, 1, 2, 3, or four Aces, or Court cards all of a ſuit, according as they could get them together in the former deal, and place a Card of the ſame ſuit in the bottom, when the Cards are cut they muſt uſe their hand ſo dexterouſly as not to put the top in the bottom, but nimbly place where it was before.</p>
               <p>If they would ſecure Honours to themſelves when dealing, they then place ſo many as they can get upon their lap or other place undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, and after the Cards are cut, then clap them very neatly under. But the cleanlieſt rook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing way is by the breef, that is, take a pack of Cards and open them, then take out all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, that is as aforeſaid, the four Aces, the four Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then take the reſt and cut a
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:179790:52"/>little from the edges of them all alike, by which means the Honours will be broader than the reſt, ſo that when your Adverſary cuts to you, you are certain of an Honour, when you cut to your Adverſary cut at the ends, and then it is a chance if you cut him an Honour, becauſe the Cards at the ends are all of a length, thus you may make breefs end-ways as well as ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways.</p>
               <p>There are a ſort of cunning fellows about this City, who before they go to play will plant half a dozen of theſe Packs (nay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times half a ſcore) in the hands of a Drawer, who to avoid being ſuſpected will call to their confederate Drawer for a freſh pack of Cards, who brings them as from a ſhop new, and ſome of theſe Packs ſhall be ſo finely markt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Gameſter ſhall plainly and certainly know every Card therein contain'd by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, although the beſt of other eyes ſhall not diſcern where any mark was made at all; and this done with that variety that every Card of every ſuit ſhall have a different diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mark.</p>
               <p>Some have a way to ſlick with a Slick-ſtone all the Honours very ſmooth, by which means he will be ſure to cut his Partner an Honour, and ſo his partner to him again, and that is done by lying a fore-finger on the top indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent hard, and giving a ſlurring jerk to the reſt which will ſlip off from the ſlickt Card.</p>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:179790:53"/>
               <p>It is impoſſible to ſhew you all the Cheats of this Game, ſince your cunning Gameſter is always ſtudying new inventions to deceive the ignorant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>FRENCH-RUFF.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT <hi>French-Ruff</hi> you muſt lift for deal, moſt or leaſt carries it according to the agreement of the Gameſters.</p>
               <p>You may play either two, four or ſix of a ſide, dealing to each five a piece, either two firſt at a time, or three, according to pleaſure, and he that deals turns up Trump; the King is the higheſt Card at Trumps, and ſo it is higheſt in all other Cards that are not Trumps, the Queen is next, the Knave next, and next to that the Ace, and all other Cards follow in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminency according to the number of the Pips, but all ſmall Trumps win the higheſt of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuit.</p>
               <p>Having turn'd up Trumps, he that hath the Ace muſt take the Ace turn'd up, and all other Trumps which immediately follow that, if ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed among the Gameſters, laying out ſo many Cards as he took up in lieu thereof.</p>
               <p>After this they play: to win two tricks ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:179790:53"/>nothing, to win three or four wins but one, but to win five is the winning of five.</p>
               <p>If you play at <hi>forſat</hi> (that is the rigour of the play) he that deals wrong loſeth one and his Deal. You are bound to follow ſuit, and if you renounce or renege, you loſe the whole Game, if you ſo make it, otherwiſe but one or two ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to agreement.</p>
               <p>He that plays a Card that is trumped by the follower, if the next player hath none of the former ſuit he muſt trump it again, although he hath never a trump in his hand that can win the former trump, and ſo it muſt paſs to the laſt player.</p>
               <p>All the Players round are bound to win the higheſt trump play'd if they can. Here note, that he who playeth before his turn loſeth one, unleſs it be the laſt Card of all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Five-CARDS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIve-Cards</hi> is an <hi>Iriſh</hi>-Game, and is as much play'd in that Kingdom, and that for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſums of money, as <hi>All-fours</hi> is play'd in <hi>Kent,</hi> but there is little analogy between them.</p>
               <p>There are but two can play at it, and there
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:179790:54"/>are dealt five Cards a piece. The leaſt of the black, and the moſt of the red wins. The Ace of Diamonds is the worſt of the whole Pack, unleſs it prove to be trump.</p>
               <p>The five fingers (<hi>alias,</hi> five of trumps) is the beſt Card in the Pack; the Ace of Hearts is next to that, and the next is the Ace of Trumps, then the Knave, and the reſt of Cards are beſt according to their value in pips, or as they are trumps.</p>
               <p>Before you play ask whether he will <hi>five it,</hi> if he ſpeaks affirmatively turn up the next Card of the Pack under that firſt turn'd up, and that muſt be trumps; if not, play it out: he that wins moſt Cards wins five, but he that wins all, wins ten.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, that the Ace of Hearts wins the Ace of Trumps, and the Five-fingers not only wins the Ace of Trumps, but alſo all other Cards whatever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of a Game called Coſtly-Colours.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Game is to be play'd out only by two Perſons, of which the eldeſt is to play firſt as in other Games. You muſt deal off three a piece, and turn up the next Card
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:179790:54"/>following; then the Eldeſt is to take his choice whether he will <hi>Mogg</hi> (that is change a Card or no) and whoſoever refuſeth is to give the other one chalk or hole, of which generally Threeſcore and one makes the Game. Then muſt the Eldeſt play, and the other if he can muſt make it up fifteen, for which he ſhall ſet up as many holes or chalks as there are Cards upon the Table; ſo likewiſe for five and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and alſo as many Cards as are play'd to make up thirty, no more nor leſs, ſo many chalks may be ſet up who play'd laſt, to make up one and thirty, and if one and thirty be not made, then he that play'd laſt and is neareſt one and thirty without making out muſt ſet up one, which is called ſetting up one for the latter.</p>
               <p>This being done, the eldeſt muſt ſhow how many Chalks he hath in his hand to ſet up, and after him the youngeſt, which they muſt reckon in this manner, taking notice both of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and number of pips upon the Card turn'd up as thoſe in their hands ſtill, reckoning as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for all the fifteen and five and twenty as there go Cards to make the number; and if you have it by chance in your hand, and with the Card turned up one and thirty, then you muſt ſet up four for that: you muſt alſo ſet up if you have them in your hands or can make them ſo in the Card turn'd up as followeth, two for a pair, be they either Coat-cards, or others;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:179790:55"/>two for a Knave, and if a Knave of the ſame colour and ſuit of the Card turn'd up, then you muſt ſet up four; and ſo for a Deuce four, if it be of the ſame colour turn'd up: if you have three of a ſort, either three fours, five ſixes, or Coat cards, you muſt ſet up nine, and this is called a Pair-Royal; now if they are all either Hearts, Diamonds, or the like, then you muſt ſet up ſix for <hi>Coſtly Colours.</hi> If you have three of a colour, you can reckon but two for Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</p>
               <p>Whoſoever dealt, if he turn'd up either Deuce or Knave, he muſt ſet up four for it; as for example, imagine you had dealt your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary three Cards, <hi>viz.</hi> the five of Hearts, four of Hearts, and eight of Hearts; to your ſelf the Deuce of Hearts, ſeven of Clubs, and nine of Hearts. Laſtly, you turn up a Card, which is the Knave of Hearts, for which you muſt ſet up four; then becauſe he will not ask you to change one, he gives you one, which you muſt ſet up, and then he plays, ſuppoſe it be his five of Hearts, you then play your ſeven of Clubs, which makes twelve, then he plays his eight of Hearts which makes twenty; then you play your nine of Hearts, which makes twenty nine, and becauſe he cannot come in with his five of Hearts, you muſt play your Deuce of Hearts, which makes you one and thirty. For your five you muſt ſet up five, then he muſt ſet up what he hath in his hand,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:179790:55"/>which you will find to be but ſix, for he hath nothing in his hand but <hi>Coſtly-Colours.</hi> Then muſt you ſet up your Games, which firſt are two, for your nine of Clubs and nine of Hearts which make fifteen, then that fifteen and the Knave turn'd up makes five and twenty, for which ſet up three; then for your Deuce of Hearts which is the right, ſet up four, and three for Colours, becauſe you have three of a ſort in your hand with that turn'd up, now theſe with the five you got in playing for thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty one makes you this Deal with the Knave turn'd up and the Cards in your hand juſt twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Many other examples I might give you, but that it is needleſs, ſince this one is ſufficient to direct you in all others. And thus much for <hi>Coſtly-Colours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>BONE-ACE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Game you may look on as trivial and very inconſiderable, and ſo it is by reaſon of the little variety therein contain'd, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have ſeen Ladies and Perſons of quality have plaid at it for their diverſion, I will briefly deſcribe it, and the rather becauſe it is a licking Game for Money.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:179790:56"/>
               <p>There are ſeven, or eight (or as many as the Cards will permit) play at it at one time. In the lifting for dealing the leaſt deals, which is a great diſadvantage; for that makes the Dealer youngeſt hand.</p>
               <p>The Dealer deals out two to the firſt hand, and turns up the third, and ſo goes on to the next, to the third, fourth, fifth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He that hath the biggeſt Card carries the Bone, that is one half of the Stake, the other remaining for the Game; now if there be three Kings, three Queens, three Tens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> turn'd up, the eldeſt hand wins it. Here note that the Ace of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds is Bone-Ace, and wins all other Cards whatever: thus much for the Bone; afterwards the neareſt to one and thirty wins the Game, and he that turns up or draws to one and thirty wins it immediately.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of PUTT and the High-Game.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>P<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tt</hi> is the ordinary rooking Game of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place, and ſeems by the few Cards that are dealt to have no great difficulty in the play, but I am ſure there is much craft and cunning in it; of which I ſhall ſhow as much as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:179790:56"/>
               <p>If you play at two-handed Putt (or if you pleaſe you may play at three hands) the beſt Putt-Card deals. Having ſhuffled the Cards, the Adverſary cuts them, then the Dealer deals one to his Antagoniſt, and another to himſelf till they have three apiece: five up or a Putt is commonly the Game. The eldeſt if he hath a good Game, and thinks it better than his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, puts to him, if the other will not or dare not ſee him, he then wins one, but if he will ſee him they play it out, and he that wins two tricks or all three wins the whole ſet; but if each win a trick and the third tyed, neither win, becauſe it is trick and tye.</p>
               <p>Sometimes they play without putting, and then the winner is he that wins moſt tricks. Here note that in your playing keep up your Cards very cloſe; for the leaſt diſcovery of any one of them is a great advantage to him that ſees it.</p>
               <p>This Game conſiſts very much in daring; for a right Gameſter will put boldly upon very bad Cards ſometimes, as upon a five, ſeven and a nine; the other thinking there are good Cards in his Adverſaries hand, having very indifferent ones in his own dares not ſee him, and ſo by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtock loſeth one. Here note that he that once hath the confidence to put on bad Cards cannot recall his putting, by which means he frequently pays for his bravado.</p>
               <p>The beſt Putt-Cards are firſt the Trey, next
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:179790:57"/>the Deuce, then the Ace, the reſt follow in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence thus; the King, the Queen, the Knave, the Ten, and ſo onwards to the four, which is the meaneſt Card at Putt.</p>
               <p>Some of the Cheats at Putt are done after this manner:</p>
               <p>Firſt, for cutting to be ſure of a good Putt-Card, they uſe the Bent, the Slick, and the Breef; the bent is a Card bended in play which you cut, the ſlick is when before-hand the Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter takes a Pack of Cards, and with a ſlick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone ſmooths all the Putt-Cards, that when he comes to cut to his Adverſary with his four-fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger above and his thumb about the middle, he ſlides the reſt of the Cards off that which was ſlickt, which is done infallibly with much faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; but in this there is required neatneſs and dexterity for fear of diſcovery, and then your confidence in this contrivance will be vain and of no effect.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the Breef in cutting is very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to him that cuts, and it is thus done: the Cheat provides before-hand a Pack of Cards, whereof ſome are broader than others; under ſome of which he plants in play ſome good Putt-Cards, which though they ſhuffle never ſo much they ſhall rarely ſeparate them; by which means he that cuts (laying his fingers on the broad Card) hath ſurely dealt him a Putt-Card.</p>
               <p>In dealing theſe Rooks have a trick they call
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:179790:57"/>the <hi>Spurr,</hi> and that is, as good Cards come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their hand that they may know them again by the out-ſide (and ſo diſcover the ſtrength or weakneſs of their Adverſaries Game) I ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where on the out-ſide they give them a gentle touch with their nail.</p>
               <p>Now when they intend to bleed a <hi>Col</hi> to ſome purpoſe whom they have ſet before, they always fix half a ſcore Packs of Cards before (as I have related in <hi>Whist</hi>) by ſlicking them or ſpurring them, that is, giving them ſuch marks that they ſhall certainly know every Card in the Pack, and conſequently every Card that is in his Adverſaries hand, an advantage that cannot well be greater.</p>
               <p>But if they are not furniſhed with ſuch Cards, and cannot accompliſh their ends by the former indirect means without palpable diſcovery, then they have accomplices who ſtanding by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent <hi>Col</hi> look over his Game, and diſcovers what it is to his Adverſary: and to ſtrengthen their intereſt by cheating, they frequently carry about them Treys, Deuces, Aces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their Pockets, which they uſe as need requires, or if not, they will ſteal them out of the Pack whilſt they are playing, which is the ſecureſt way and freeſt from diſcovery.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, they have one moſt egregious piece of Roguery more, and that is playing the <hi>High-Game</hi> at <hi>Putt;</hi> and this is to be done but once at a Set-meeting; and therefore on this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:179790:58"/>the abſolute overthrow of the <hi>Col</hi> that plays, or the <hi>Col</hi> that is a ſtander-by.</p>
               <p>This <hi>High Game</hi> at <hi>Putt</hi> is thus performed: the Rook whilſt playing ſingles out the Deuces and Treys for the laſt Game, and placeth them thus in order, hiding them in his lap or other covert, firſt a Deuce, then a Trey, next a Deuce, then a Trey, then a Trey and a Trey; now ſtooping letting fall a Card or ſome other way as he ſhall think fit, he claps theſe Cards fac'd at the bottom, having ſhuffled the Cards before, and bids his Adverſary cut, which he nimbly and neatly with both his hands joyns the divided Cards, and then the bottom fac'd Cards are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and then he deals, and leſt there ſhould be a diſcovery made of the facing, he palms them as much as he can, nimbly paſſing the laſt Card.</p>
               <p>Now do the Gameſters ſmile at the goodneſs of each others Game, one ſhows his to one, the other his to another; and cries who would not put at ſuch Cards? the other in as brisk a tone, ſays, Come if you dare. What will you lay of the Game, ſays the Rook? what you dare, ſays the <hi>Col;</hi> then pauſing a while the Rook ſeems to conſult with his friends, who cry, they know not what to think on't; five pound cries a rooking Confederate on this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's ſide, the <hi>Col</hi> encouraged hereby, cries ten pound more: and thus the Rook holds him in play till there be a good Sum of Money on the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:179790:58"/>Board; then anſwers the Putt of the now ruin'd <hi>Cully.</hi> They now play; the <hi>Col</hi> begins with a Deuce, the Rook wins that with a Trey; the Rook then plays a Deuce, and the <hi>Col</hi> wins it with his Trey; then he plays his Deuce which is won with a Trey; thus the Rook wins the Day. This Game may be plaid otherways ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to fancy: let theſe and the former cheats be a ſufficient warning.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>VVIT and REASON, a Game ſo called.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WIT</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> is a Game which ſeems very eaſie at firſt to the Learner, but in his practice and obſervation ſhall find it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. It is a Game ſomething like one and thirty, and is plaid after this manner.</p>
               <p>Two playing together, the one hath all the red Cards, and the other hath the black: then they turn up croſs or pile who ſhall lead; for the Leader hath a great advantage over the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as ſhall be demonſtrated.</p>
               <p>You are not to play a ten firſt; for if you do you ſhall certainly loſe; for one and thirty being the Game he that firſt comes to it wins; now ſhould the Leader play a ten the follower
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:179790:59"/>will play another ten, that makes twenty; let the Leader then play any thing next, the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower will be ſure to make it up one and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>He that hath the Lead if he play a nine may certainly win the Game, if he look about him; ever remembring to get firſt to twenty, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpending two of one ſort, as two Deuces, two Treys, two Quaters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> otherwiſe you will loſe: As for example, you play a nine firſt, your Adverſary plays a Deuce that makes ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, you then play a nine again, and that makes twenty; thus you have plaid out both your nines, wherefore your Antagoniſt plays a Deuce, now you can play no Card but he wins; for if you play an eight (for you cannot come in with your ten) and you have never a nine, then he hath an Ace for one and thirty; ſo if you play a ſeven, which makes nine and twenty, he hath a Deuce remaining to make up one and thirty, and ſo you may obſerve in the reſt of the Cards.</p>
               <p>Take this for a general rule, that you have a very great advantage in fetching out by play any two of a number, as aforeſaid; as two fives, two ſixes, two ſevens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherefore you muſt not play raſhly, but with due conſideration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmetically grounded to make up a certain Game of one and thirty. To conclude, he that hath the art of playing well at one and thirty without Cards, that is by naming ſuch a number
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:179790:59"/>at firſt, and proſecuting it by ſuch addition of others, that your Adverſary cannot think of any number but what ſhall be your Game; I ſay ſuch a Man is fitteſt to play at this Game called <hi>Wit and Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>A Paſtime called The</hi> Art <hi>of Memory.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis <hi>Art of Memory</hi> is a Sport at which Men may play for Money, but it is moſt commonly the way to play the Drunkard. It is beſt when many play at it; for with few it is no ſport at all: For example, as many perſons as do play, ſo many Cards trebled muſt be thrown down on the Table with their faces upwards; which every one muſt take notice of and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to regiſter them in his Memory. Then the Dealer muſt take them all up, and ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling them after cutting deals to every one three a-piece.</p>
               <p>The firſt it may be calls for a King, which muſt be laid on the Table with his face down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by him that hath it in his hands; the next it may be calls for a ten of the Spades, which muſt be laid down in like manner, and ſo it goes round; now if any one calls for what is already laid down, if they play for Liquor, he muſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:179790:60"/>then drink a Glaſs; if for mony, he muſt then pay a farthing, half-penny, or the like.</p>
               <p>This ſport wholly depends on the Memory; for want of which a Man may loſe at this ſport his Money or his Underſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. <hi>A Game called PLAIN-DEALING.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE that deals hath the advantage of this Game; for if he turn up the Ace of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds he cannot loſe: to his Adverſary he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers out nine and but three to himſelf; then are the Cards plaid as at <hi>Whist,</hi> the beſt of Trumps or other Cards wins, and but one to be gotten at a deal. I cannot commend this Paſtime for its ingenuity, and therefore only name it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we treat of Games in general.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:179790:60"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>A Game called Queen</hi> Nazareen.</head>
               <p>THere may as many play at it as the Cards will allow of, five Cards are dealt to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Player. The Queen of Diamonds is Queen <hi>Nazareen,</hi> and he that hath it demands three apiece of every Player. The Knave of Clubs is called Knave Knocher, and he that hath it chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth two a-piece. If Women play among Men, it is cuſtomary for Knave Knocher to kiſs Queen <hi>Nazareen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, he that lays down a King the laſt Card that is plaid challengeth one, and begins again; and he that hath firſt plaid away his Cards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands as many Counters as there are Cards in the hands of the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>LANTERLOO.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LAnterloo</hi> is a Game may be plaid ſeveral ways, but I ſhall inſiſt on none but two; the firſt way is thus.</p>
               <p>Lift for dealing, and the beſt Putt-Card car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:179790:61"/>it; as many may play as the Cards will permit, to whom muſt be dealt five apiece, and then turn up Trump. Now if three, four, five or ſix play, they may lay out the threes, fours, fives, ſixes and ſevens to the intent they may not be quickly loo'd; but if they would have the loos come faſt about then play with the whole pack.</p>
               <p>Having dealt ſet up five ſcores or chalks; and then proceed forwards in your Game.</p>
               <p>He that is Eldeſt hand hath the priviledge of paſſing by the benefit thereof, that is, he hath the advantage of hearing what every one will ſay, and at laſt may play or not play accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as he finds his Game good or bad. If the Eldeſt ſaith he paſſeth, the reſt may chuſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will play or no.</p>
               <p>You may play upon every Card what you pleaſe, from a penny to a pound. Trumps as at Whiſt are the beſt Cards, all others in like manner take their precedency from the higheſt to the loweſt.</p>
               <p>You muſt not revoke, if you do you pay all on the Table. If you play and are loo'd (that is, win never a trick) you muſt lay down to the ſtock ſo much for your five Cards as you plaid upon every one of them.</p>
               <p>Every deal rub off a ſcore, and for every trick you win ſet up a ſcore by you till the firſt ſcores are out, to remember you how many tricks you have won in the ſeveral deals in the Game.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:179790:61"/>
               <p>All the Chalks for the Game being rub'd out, tell your own ſcores, and for ſo many ſcores or tricks which you have won, ſo much as they were valued at in the Game ſo much you muſt take from the Stock; thus muſt every one do according to the number of tricks he hath won.</p>
               <p>Here note, that he who hath five Cards of a ſuit in his hand loos all the Gameſters then playing, be they never ſo many, and ſweeps the board; if there be two loos he that is eldeſt hand hath the advantage.</p>
               <p>As there is cheating (as they ſay) in all trades, ſo more particularly intolerable in Gaming; as in this for example, if one of the Gameſters have four of a ſuit and he want a fifth, he may for that fifth make an exchange out of his own Pocket if he be skill'd in the cleanly art of conveyance; if that fail, ſome make uſe of a friend, who never fails to do him that kind office and favour. There are other Cheats to be performed, which I ſhall omit, ſince it is not my buſineſs to teach you how to cheat, but ſo to play as not to be cheated.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Lanterloo another way plaid.</head>
                  <p>LIft for dealing as aforeſaid, and the beſt Put-card deals five to every one apiece. The Dealer for his five Cards muſt lay down ſo many Six-pences, Shillings, and ſo forth, as they
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:179790:62"/>conclude upon and agree for every Card, or ſo many Counters being valued at either Six-pence or Twelve-pence, more or leſs. After this all muſt play; if any be loo'd he muſt lay down ſo much for his loo as his five Cards amount to. If any next dealing be loo'd he muſt lay down as much for his dealing, and as much more for his loo.</p>
                  <p>If after this the eldeſt hand paſs, the reſt may refuſe to play, or play if they think they can win a Card.</p>
                  <p>Here note, If there be never a loo the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney may be divided by the Gameſters according to the number of their Tricks, if there be a loo the winners muſt take up the money, and he that is loo'd muſt lay down as much money on the board as every one had laid down before, be it never ſo great a ſumm, beſides the like quantity for dealing, if he that was loo'd dealt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>A Game called PENNEECH.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving dealt ſeven Cards apiece, turn up a Card, and that is Trumps. The Ace and Coat-Cards of Trumps are thus reckoned, the Ace is five, the King four, the Queen three, and the Knave two.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:179790:62"/>
               <p>Having play'd, he that wins the firſt trick turns up another Card, and that is Trumps; and ſo every trick produceth a freſh Trump, till all the ſeven be play'd. Now if it ſo happen, that what is turn'd up proves an Ace or Coat-Card, that is a great advantage to him who won the laſt trick; for if it be an Ace turn'd up then he reckons five, if a King four, if a Queen three, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>After all the ſeven Cards be play'd, (which at firſt are dealt one by one) he that won the laſt trick turns up a Card, and if it prove Ace, King, Queen, or Knave, he reckons for it accordingly as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>If the Seven of Diamonds be turn'd up, that is <hi>Penneech,</hi> and is reckon'd fourteen turn'd up, but it is but ſeven in hand, and not that neither unleſs Diamonds be Trumps; if it be Trump it is the higheſt Card and wins all others; if it be not Trump it wins all Diamonds.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Having play'd out all the fourteen Cards betwixt ye, count how many Cards you have more than your own ſeven at firſt dealt you, and for every Card reckon one, and ſo you muſt reckon on with the value of your Coat-Card Trumps, with <hi>Penneech</hi> turn'd up or in hand, till you come to ſixty one, which is the Game.</p>
               <p>Here note, if you have neither Ace nor Face, you may throw up your Game and deal again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:179790:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>POST and PAIR.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>POst</hi> and <hi>Pair</hi> is a Game on the Cards very much play'd in the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>All-Fours</hi> is play'd in <hi>Kent,</hi> and <hi>Fives</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Play depends much upon daring; ſo that ſome may win very conſiderably, who have the boldneſs to adventure much upon the Vye, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their Cards are very indifferent.</p>
               <p>You muſt firſt ſtake at Poſt, then at Pair; after this deal two Cards apiece, then ſtake at the Seat, and then deal the third Card about. The eldeſt hand may paſs and come in again, if any of the Gameſters vye it; if not, the Dealer may play it out, or double it.</p>
               <p>The Ace of Trumps, as at Ruff and Honours, is the beſt Card of all, and ſo of the reſt in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. At Poſt the beſt Cards are one and twenty, <hi>viz.</hi> two Tens and an Ace, but a pair-royal wins all, both Poſt, Pair, and Seat. Here note, that he who hath the beſt Pair or the beſt Poſt is the winner. A Pair is a pair of any two, as two Kings, two Queens, &amp;c. A Pair-royal is of three, as three Kings, three Queens, &amp;c. The Vye is what you pleaſe to adventure upon the goodneſs of your own hand, or if it be bad, and you imagine your Adverſaries is ſo likewiſe, then bid high couragiouſly, by which means you daunt your Antagoniſt, and ſo bring him to ſubmiſſion.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:179790:63"/>If all the Gameſters keep in till all have done, and by conſent ſhew their Cards, the beſt Cards carry the Game. Now according to agreement thoſe that keep in till laſt, may divide the ſtakes, or ſhew the beſt Card for it.</p>
               <p>Obſerve, where the Cards fall in ſeveral hands of the ſame ſort, as a Pair or Pair-Royal, and ſo forth, the eldeſt hand carries it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXIII. <hi>BANKAFALET, a Game on the Cards ſo called.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Cards muſt be cut into as many heaps as there are Players, or more if you pleaſe, and every Man lays as much money on his own Card as he thinks fit, or on the ſupernumerary heaps. So many as the Dealers Card is inferior to, ſo many he pays; ſo many as his Card is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to, ſo many he wins from.</p>
               <p>The beſt Card is the Ace of Diamonds, the next to that the Ace of Hearts, thirdly the Ace of Clubs, and laſtly the Ace of Spades, and ſo the reſt of theſe ſuits in order, according to their degree. The Cheat lies in ſecuring an Ace or any other good ſure winning Card; and if you mark the Cards aforehand, ſo as to know them by the backſide, you know how to make your advantage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:179790:64"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>BEAST.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is called by the <hi>French, La Bett,</hi> and is play'd by them after this manner. The beſt Cards are King, Queen, and ſo forwards. They make three heaps, the King, the Play, and the Triolet.</p>
               <p>To every one is dealt five Cards, (there may play three, four, five, or more) as at <hi>French Ruff,</hi> with the ſame rigour; before the Cards are dealt, every one ſtakes to the three heaps. He that wins moſt tricks takes up the heap that is called the Play; he that hath the King takes up the heap ſo called; and he that hath three of any ſort, that is, three fours, three fives, three ſixes, and ſo forth takes up the Triolet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:179790:64"/>
               <head>Games within the Tables.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XXV. <hi>Of IRISH.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IRiſh</hi> is an ingenious Game, and requires a great deal of skill to play it well, eſpecially the After-game. It is not to be learn'd other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than by obſervation and practice, however I ſhall lightly touch hereon.</p>
               <p>The men which are thirty in number are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually divided between you and your Adverſary, and are thus placed, two on the Ace point, and five on the ſice of your left hand Table, and three on the cinque, and five on the Ace point of your right hand Table, anſwer'd on the like points by your Adverſaries men with the ſame number; or thus, two of your men on the Ace point, five on the double ſice, or ſice Cinque point, three on the Cinque point in your own Tables, and five on the ſice point at home, and all theſe pointed alike by your Adverſary.</p>
               <p>In your play have a care of being too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and be not too raſh in hitting every blot, but with diſcretion and conſideration move ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but ſecurely; by which means though your
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:179790:65"/>Adverſary have fill'd his Tables, but withall blots, and you by hitting him enter, you may win the Game; nay ſometimes though he hath born his men all to a very few.</p>
               <p>'Tis the part of a prudent Commander as he leads out his men to bring them home as ſafe as he may; ſo muſt you have a care of your men as you are bringing them home that they are not pickt up by the way.</p>
               <p>Have a ſpecial care that your Adverſary dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not the Trey, Ace-point with his men, and ſo make what convenient haſte you can to fill up your own Tables, and beware of blotting; that done, bear as faſt as you can.</p>
               <p>For an After-game I know not what inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to give you, you muſt herein truſt to your own judgment and the chance of the Dice, and if they run low for ſome time, it will be ſo much the better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>Of Back-Gammon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur men are placed as at <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Back-Gammon</hi> differs but very little from it, but in Doublets which at this Game is plaid four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, which makes a quicker diſpatch of the Game than <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:179790:65"/>
               <p>Be ſure to make good your Trey, Ace-points, hit boldly and come away as faſt as you can, to which end if your Dice run high, you will make the quicker diſpatch.</p>
               <p>When you come to bearing have a care of making when you need not, and Doublets now will ſtand you moſt in ſtead.</p>
               <p>If both bear together, he that is firſt off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Doublets wins one.</p>
               <p>If both bear and one goes off with Doublets he wins two.</p>
               <p>If your Tables be clear before your Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries men be come in, that's a <hi>Back-Gammon,</hi> which is three; but if you thus go off with Doublets it is four.</p>
               <p>Falſe Dice are much uſed at <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Back-Gammon</hi> for the benefit of entring, wherefore have a ſpecial care that you have not Cinque-Deuces, and Quater-Treys put upon you, you may quickly perceive it by the running of the Dice.</p>
               <p>The perſon that is cunning at play has great advantage of a novice or innocent man, which is commonly by toping or knaping, which by its often practice may be ſuſpected by his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; then he has recourſe to Dice, which runs particular chances for his purpoſe, which the other being ignorant of, is almoſt an equal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage with the former. For example, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides Dice that runs 6, 5, 4, 'tis his buſineſs to ſecure thoſe points, ſo that if he happens to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:179790:66"/>any of your men coming home, as 'tis two to one but he does, he does without a kind of Miracle win the ſet.</p>
               <p>'Tis poſſible ſometimes they may make uſe of 3, 2, which are the low Chances; but that they ſeldom do for this reaſon, the high or forward points being ſupplied, you muſt enter if at all upon the low points which keeps you backwards and gives him advantage. The advantage of this Game is to be forward if poſſible upon ſafe terms, and to point his men at that rate that it ſhall not be poſſible for you to paſs, though you have entred your men, till he gives you liberty, having two to one the advantage of the Game.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVII. <hi>Of TICK-TACK.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL your men muſt ſtand on the Ace-point, and from thence play forward, but have a care of being too forward, or ſo at leaſtwiſe that Doublets reach you not.</p>
               <p>Secure your Sice and Cinque-point whatever you do, and break them not unleſs it be when you have the advantage of going in, which is the greateſt advantage you can have next to a hit; for your Adverſaries eleventh point ſtanding
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:179790:66"/>open you have it may be the opportunity of going in with two of your men, and then you win a double Game. A hit is but one, and that is, when you throw ſuch a caſt that ſome one of your men will reach your Adverſaries un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, but ſometimes though it hits it will not paſs by reaſon of a ſtop in the way, and then it is nothing. Sometimes it is good going over into your Adverſaries Tables, but it is beſt for an After-game.</p>
               <p>Playing cloſe at home is the ſecureſt way, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at length is both raſh and unſafe, and be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of binding your men when you lie in danger of the enemy. Moreover, if you ſee you are in danger of loſing a double Game, give your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary one; if you can it is better doing ſo than loſing two.</p>
               <p>Here note, if you fill up all the points of your ſecond Table with your own men you win two, and that you may prevent your Adverſary from doing ſo (if you are in danger thereof) if you can, make a vacant point in his Tables, and it is impoſſible for him to do it.</p>
               <p>This is the plain Game of Tick-Tack, which is called ſo from <hi>Touch,</hi> and <hi>take,</hi> for if you touch a man you muſt play him though to your loſs; and if you hit your Adverſary and neglect the advantage, you are taken with a Why-not, which is the loſs of one: likewiſe if you are in, and your caſt is ſuch that you may alſo go into your Adverſaries eleventh point by two other men,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:179790:67"/>and you ſee it not, either by careleſneſs or eager proſecution of a hit which is apparent before your eyes, you loſe two irrecoverably. Beſides, it is a very great overſight as your men may ſtand, not to take a point when you may do it.</p>
               <p>Now ſome play this Game with Toots, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, and Flyers; Toots is, when you fill up your Table at home, and then there is required ſmall throws; for if you get over with a Sice, you have no benefit of Toots.</p>
               <p>Boveries is when you have a man in the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth point of your own Tables, and another in the ſame point of your Adverſaries directly anſwering.</p>
               <p>Flyers is, when you bring a man round the Tables before your Adverſary hath got over his firſt Table, to the effecting of which there is required very high throwing of your ſide, and very low throwing of his.</p>
               <p>Much more might be ſaid as to the craft of the play, which cannot be ſo well diſcovered as from obſervation in your own or others play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>There are ſeveral fooliſh paſtimes to be plaid in the Tables which are ridiculous to treat of, wherefore I ſhall only mention theſe Three, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:179790:67"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>DUBBLETS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT Dubblets the fifteen men are thus pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; upon Sice, Cinque and Quater there are three men apiece, upon Trey, Deuce, Ace, but two apiece.</p>
               <p>He that throws moſt hath the benefit of throwing firſt, and what he throws he lays down; and ſo doth the other; what the one throws and hath not, the other lays down for him to his own advantage; and thus they do till all the men are down, and then they bear, but not till they are down; he that is down firſt bears firſt, and will doubtleſly win the Game if the other throws not Dubblets to overtake him; now he that throws Dubblets apace is certain to win, for as many as the Dubblets are, ſo many he lays down, or bears; for example, if two fours, he lays down, or bears eight, and ſo for the other Dubblets; and therefore he that can either nap, top, or hath high runners about him hath a great advantage herein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:179790:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIX. <hi>SICE-AGE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIve may play at Sice-Ace with ſix men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, they one load another with Aces, ſixes bears only, and Dubblets drinks and throws again, ſo often ſome I have ſeen that for the lucre of a little money have reſolved rather to loſe themſelves than a penny. It is commonly agreed the laſt two, or the laſt out ſhall loſe, and the reſt go free.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXX. <hi>KETCH-DOLT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT Ketch-Dolt the firſt throws and lays down from the heap of men without the Tables, what is thrown at it may be Sice Deuce, if the other throw either Sice or Deuce, and draw them not from his Adverſaries Tables to the ſame point in his own, but takes them from the heap, and lays the Ace down, he is dolted and loſeth the Game, or if he but touch a man of the heap and then recall himſelf, the loſs is the ſame. Some by frequent practice will never be Dolted,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:179790:68"/>and then they ſtrive who ſhall fill up their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles firſt; which done, he that bears them off firſt hath won the game. And ſo much for play within the Tables.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>Games without the Tables.</head>
               <head type="sub">CHAP. XXXI. <hi>Of Inn and Inn.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>INn and Inn</hi> is a Game very much uſed in an <hi>Ordinary,</hi> and may be play'd by two or three, each having a <hi>Box</hi> in his hand. It is play'd with four Dice. You may drop what you will, Six-pences, Shillings, or Guinneys; every Inn you drop, and every <hi>Inn and Inn</hi> you ſweep all; but if you throw out, if but two play, your Adverſary wins all; if three play, that Out is a <hi>Bye</hi> between the two other Gameſters, which they may either divide or throw out for it. Here you are to obſerve that <hi>Out</hi> is when you have thrown no Dubblets on the four Dice; <hi>Inn</hi> is when you have thrown two Dubblets of any ſort, as two Aces, two Deuces, two Kings, <hi>&amp;c. Inn</hi> and <hi>Inn</hi> is, when you throw all Dubblets,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:179790:69"/>whether all of a ſort or otherwiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> four Aces, four Deuces, or four Cinques, or two Aces, two Deuces, two Treys, two Quaters, or two Cinques, two Sixes, and ſo forth.</p>
               <p>Your Battail may be as much and as little as you will, from twenty Shillings to twenty Pounds, and ſo onward to a thouſand, which Battail is not ended till every penny of that money agreed upon for the Battail be won; and it is but requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, for it is frequently ſeen that in a Battail of ten Pound a Gentleman hath been reduced to five Shillings, and yet hath won at laſt the Battail.</p>
               <p>For a Gameſter that would win without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding much his money, Dice that will run ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeldom otherwiſe but Sixes, Cinques, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are very neceſſary; If thoſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not to be had, a Taper-box will not be amiſs, that as the Dice are thrown in may ſtick by the way, and ſo thrown to advantage. I have heard of one, who having ſpent the major part of his Patrimony in good fellowſhip, and ſuch paſtimes as the heat of blood with vigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous youth moſt proſecute; at length conſider'd how he ſhould live hereafter, and finding but ſmall encouragements at home, and leſſer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, thought if he could contrive a way to win a conſiderable ſum at play (having been a great loſer himſelf) that ſhould be the baſis of his future ſettlement; after various conſultations within himſelf he at length contrived this ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem; He cauſed a Box to be made, not as they
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:179790:69"/>are uſual ſcrewed within, but ſmooth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it to be ſo well painted and ſhadowed within that it lookt like a ſcrew'd Box; now this Box was but half board wide at top, and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row at bottom, that the Dice as aforeſaid might ſtick, and the Box being ſmooth would come out without tumbling. With this Box he went and play'd at <hi>Inn and Inn,</hi> by vertue whereof and his art of taking up and throwing in his Dice into the Box, he got the firſt night a Thouſand pound, and the next night Two hundred a year, with a Coach and ſix Horſes, which Coach and Horſes (being very valuable) he ſold, but the Eſtate he lives on to this day with great improvements, and never would handle a Dye ſince, well knowing how many worthy Families it hath ruin'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXII. <hi>Of PASSAGE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAſſage</hi> is a Game at Dice to be play'd at but by two, and it is performed with three Dice. The <hi>Caster</hi> throws continually till he hath thrown Dubblets under ten, and then he is out and loſeth, or dubblets above ten, and then he <hi>paſſeth</hi> and wins; high runners are moſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for this Game, ſuch as will rarely run any
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:179790:70"/>other chance than four, five, or ſix, by which means if the Caſter throws Dubblets he ſcarcely can throw out. There is the ſame advantage of the Smooth taper-box aforeſaid in this Game, as at <hi>Inn and Inn;</hi> with the like benefit of the Dice, whether by <hi>palming, topping, ſlurring,</hi> or <hi>knap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII. <hi>Of HAZZARD.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAzzard</hi> is a proper name for this Game; for it ſpeedily makes a Man or undoes him; in the twinkling of an eye either a Man or a Mouſe.</p>
               <p>This Game is play'd but with two Dice, but there may play at it as many as can ſtand round the largeſt round Table.</p>
               <p>There are two things chiefly to be obſerved, that is, <hi>Main</hi> and <hi>Chance;</hi> the <hi>Chance</hi> is the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> and the <hi>Main</hi> theirs who are concerned in play with him. There can be no <hi>Main</hi> thrown above nine and under five; ſo that five, ſix, ſeven, eight and nine are the only <hi>Mains</hi> and no more which are flung at Hazzard; <hi>Chances</hi> and <hi>Nicks</hi> are from four to ten, thus four is a <hi>chance</hi> to nine, five to eight, ſix to ſeven, ſeven to ſix, eight to five; and nine and ten a chance
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:179790:70"/>to five, ſix, ſeven and eight: in ſhort, four, five, ſix, ſeven, eight, nine and ten are chances to any <hi>Main,</hi> if any of theſe <hi>Nick</hi> it not: now <hi>Nicks</hi> are either when the <hi>chance</hi> is the ſame with the <hi>Main,</hi> as five and five, ſix and ſix, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and ſeven, and ſo on, or ſix and twelve, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and eleven, eight and twelve; where note, that twelve is out to nine, ſeven, and five; and eleven is out to nine, eight, ſix, and five; <hi>Ames-Ace,</hi> and Deuce-Ace, are out to all Mains what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p>That I may the better illuſtrate this Game, it will not be amiſs to give one example for your better information; Seven's the <hi>Main,</hi> the Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er throws five, and that's his <hi>chance,</hi> and ſo hath five to ſeven; if the Caſter throw his own <hi>chance</hi> he wins all the money was ſet him, but if he throw Seven which was the <hi>Main,</hi> he muſt pay as much money as is on the Board; if again Seven be the <hi>Main,</hi> and the <hi>Caſter</hi> throws ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that is a <hi>Nick,</hi> and ſweeps away all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney on the Table; but if he throw a <hi>chance,</hi> he muſt wait which will come firſt; Laſtly, if Seven be the <hi>Main,</hi> and the Caſter throws Ames-Ace, Deuce-Ace, or twelve, he is out, but if he throw from four to ten he hath a <hi>chance,</hi> though they are accounted the worſt <hi>chances</hi> on the Dice, as ſeven is reputed the beſt and eaſieſt <hi>Main</hi> to be flung; thus it is in eight or ſix, if either of them be the <hi>Main,</hi> and the <hi>Caſter</hi> throw either four, five, ſeven, nine, or ten, this is his <hi>chance,</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:179790:71"/>which if he throw firſt, he wins, otherwiſe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; if he throw twelve to eight, or ſix or the ſame Caſt with the <hi>Main,</hi> he wins; but if Ames-Ace or Deuce-Ace to all he loſeth; or if twelve when the <hi>Main</hi> is either five or nine. Here note, that nothing <hi>Nicks</hi> five but five, nor no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing nine but nine.</p>
               <p>Four and Five to Seven is judged to have the worſt on't, becauſe Four (called by the Tribe of Nickers little Dick-Fiſher) and Five have but two <hi>chances,</hi> Trey Ace and two Deuces, or Trey Deuce and Quater Ace, whereas Seven hath three Chances, Cinque Deuce, Six Ace, and Quater Trey; in like condition is nine and ten, having but two chances, ſix trey, cinque and quater, or ſix quater and two cinques.</p>
               <p>Now ſix and eight one would think ſhould admit of no difference in advantage with ſeven, but if you will rightly conſider the caſe, and be ſo vain to make trial thereof, you will find a great advantage in ſeven over ſix and eight. How can that be you will ſay, hath not ſix, ſeven and eight, eight equal chances? For example, in ſix, quater deuce, cinque Ace, and two Treys; in eight, ſix deuce, cinque trey, and two quarters, and hath not ſeven three as aforeſaid? It is confeſt; but pray conſider the diſadvantage in the dubblets, two treys and two quarters, and you wil lfind that ſix deuce is ſooner thrown than two quarters, and ſo conſequently cinque Ace or quater deuce ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:179790:71"/>than two treys. I ſaw an old Rook once take up a young fellow in a Tavern, upon this very ſcore: the bargain was made that the Rook ſhould have ſeven always and the young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſix, and throw continually; agreed to play they went, the Rook got the firſt day ten pound, the next day the like ſum; and ſo for ſix days together loſing in all threeſcore pounds; notwithſtanding the Gentleman, I am confident, had ſquare Dice, and threw them always him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And farther to confirm what I alledg'd before, not only this Rook, but many more have told me that they deſir'd no greater advantage than to have ſeven always and the <hi>Caster</hi> to have ſix. Here note, it is the opinion of moſt that at the firſt throw the Caſter hath the worſt on't.</p>
               <p>Certainly <hi>Hazzard</hi> is the moſt bewitching Game that is plaid on the Dice; for when a man begins to play he knows not when to leave off; and having once accuſtom'd himſelf to play at <hi>Hazzard,</hi> he hardly ever after minds any thing elſe. I have ſeen an old man about the Age of Seventy play at an Ordinary when his own eyes were ſo defective, that he was forced to help them with a pair of Spectacles; and having an opportunity one day to ſpeak to him, How a man of his years could be ſo vain and boyiſh ſtill to mind play; inſiſting withall upon the folly of that action to hazzard his money when he had not ſight enough remaining to diſcern whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:179790:72"/>he had won or loſt; beſides Sir, ſaid I, you cannot but hear how you are derided every time you come to the Ordinary; one ſays, here comes he that cannot reſt quiet, but will cry without the rattle of the Dice; another cries, certainly ſuch a one plays by the ear, for he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee to play. Let them talk what they will, ſaid the Gentleman, I cannot help it, I have been for above forty years ſo us'd to play, that ſhould I leave it off now, I were as good ſtop thoſe Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues about me, which have been inſtrumental in the preſervation of my life to this length of time.</p>
               <p>To conclude, happy is he that having been much inclined to this time-ſpending-money-waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Game, hath took up in time, and reſolved for the future never to be concerned with it more; but more happy is he that hath never heard the name thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIV. <hi>The Art and Myſtery of RIDING, Whether the Great-Horſe or any other.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS an Introduction to the Art of Riding, I think it requiſite to treat of the taming of a young Colt: In order thereunto, obſerve, that after your Colt hath been eight or ten days
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:179790:72"/>at home, and is reduced to that familiarity that he will indure currying without ſhowing aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereunto, and will ſuffer his Keeper to handle and ſtroke him in what part of the body he thinketh beſt, then it is time to offer him the Saddle; firſt laying it in the Manger that he may ſmell to it, and thereby grow acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with it, uſing all other means that he may not be afraid either at the ſight thereof or at the noiſe of the Stirrops. Having gently put on the Saddle, take a ſweet watring Trench waſht and anointed with Honey and Salt, and ſo place it in his mouth, that it may hang directly about his Tuſh, ſomewhat leaning thereon: having ſo done, which muſt be in a morning after dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, then lead him out in your hand and water him abroad, then bring him in, and after he hath ſtood rein'd a little upon his Trench an hour or thereabout, then unbridle and unſaddle him, and give him liberty to feed till Evening, and then do as before; having cheriſhed him, dreſs and cloath him for the Night.</p>
               <p>The next day do as you did before, and after that put on him a ſtrong Muſrole, or ſharp Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vezan and Martingal, which you muſt buckle at that length, that he may only feel it when he jer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth up his head, then lead him forth into ſome new plow'd land or ſoft ground, and there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made him trot a good while about in your hand to take him off from wantonneſs and wild tricks, offer to mount, which if he refuſe, then trot
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:179790:73"/>him again in your hand, then put your foot in the Stirrup, and mount half way and diſmount again; if he ſeem diſtaſted at it, about with him again, and let him not want correction; but if he take it patiently, cheriſh him, and place your ſelf in the Saddle, but ſtay there a very little while, then cheriſh him again and give him bread or graſs to feed on; then having ſeen all things fit and ſtrong without offence to your ſelf and Horſe, remount him, placing your, ſelf e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the Saddle, carrying your Rod inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively to his eye, then let ſome perſon having in his hand the Chaff-halter, lead him a little way, then make him ſtand, and having cheriſht him, let him forward again, do this ſeven or eight times, or ſo often till you have brought him of his own accord to go forward, then muſt you ſtay and cheriſh him, and having brought him home, alight gently, then dreſs and feed him well.</p>
               <p>Obſerve this courſe every day till you have brought him to trot, which will be but three at the moſt, if you obſerve to make him fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſome other Horſman, ſtopping him now and then gently, and then making him go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, remembring his ſeaſonable cheriſhings, and not forgetting his due corrections as often as you find him froward and rebellious; and when you ride him abroad, return not the ſame way home, that you may make him take all
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:179790:73"/>ways indifferently: and by theſe obſervations you will bring him to underſtand your will and purpoſe in leſs than a Fortnights time.</p>
               <p>Having brought your Horſe to receive you to his back, trot fore-right, ſtop and retire with patience and obedience, be never unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of your <hi>Helps, corrections</hi> and <hi>cheriſhings,</hi> which conſiſt in the <hi>Voice, Bridle, Rod, Calves of the Legs,</hi> and <hi>Spurs;</hi> the laſt of which is chief for correction, which muſt not be done faintly but ſharply when occaſion ſhall require it.</p>
               <p>Cheriſhings may be comprehended within three Heads, the Voice delivered ſmoothly and lovingly, as <hi>ſo, ſo boy, ſo;</hi> then the hand by clapping him gently on the neck or buttock: laſtly the Rod by rubbing him therewith upon the Withers or the Main, in which he very much delights.</p>
               <p>The next that you are to regard, is the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>role or Cavezan and Martingale; this is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Guide to a well diſpoſed Horſe for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his Head in due place, forming of his Rein, and making him appear lovely to the eye of the Spectator; and withall this is a ſharp correction when a Horſe yerketh out his Noſe, diſorders his Head, or endeavours to run away with his Rider.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:179790:74"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:179790:74"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:179790:75"/>
               <p>The manner of placing it, is thus: let it hang ſomewhat low, and reſt upon the tender griſſel of the Horſes noſe, that he may be the more ſenſible of correction; and let it not be ſtrait, but looſe, whereby the Horſe may feel, upon the yielding in of his Head, how the offence goeth from him, and by that means be made ſenſible, that his own diſorder was his only puniſhment.</p>
               <p>You muſt carefully obſerve how you win your Horſes head, and by thoſe degrees bring his Martingale ſtraighter and ſtraighter, ſo as the Horſe may ever have a gentle feeling of the ſame, and no more, till his head be brought to its true perfection, and there ſtay.</p>
               <p>When you have brought your Horſe to ſome certainty of Rein, and will Trot forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, then bring him to the treading forth of the large rings. If your Horſes nature be ſloathful and dull, yet ſtrong trot him firſt in ſome new plow'd field; but if agil, and of a fiery ſpirit, then trot him in ſome ſandy ground, and there mark out a ſpacious large ring, about a hundred paces in circumference. Having walkt him about it on the right ſeven or eight times, you muſt then by a little ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your right Rein, and laying the calf of your left Leg to his ſide, making a half cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:179790:75"/>within your ring, upon your right hand down to the center thereof, and then by ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a little your left Rein, and laying the calf of your right Leg to his ſide, making another ſemi-circle to your left hand from the center to the outmoſt verge; which two Semicir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles contrary turned, will make a perfect Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man S within the ring; then keeping your firſt large circumference, walk your Horſe about in your left hand, as oft as you did on your right; and then change within your ring as you did before, to your right hand again; and then trot him firſt on the right hand, then on the left, as long as you ſhall think conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, either one, two, or three hours, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect him in this leſſon; and this muſt be done every morning and evening too, if you find your Horſe ſloathful and dull; otherwiſe you need not take ſo much pains with him.</p>
               <p>Having taught him to trot the large rings perfectly, which will not require above four or five days; then in the ſame manner and changes make him gallop the ſame rings, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him take up his Feet ſo truly and loftily, that no falſhood may be perceived in his ſtroke, but that his inward Feet play before his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and each of a ſide follow the other ſo exactly, that his gallop may appear the beſt grace of all his motions.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:179790:76"/>
               <p>Here note: You muſt not enter him all at once to gallop this great ring, but by degrees; firſt a quarter, then a half quarter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ever remembring, not to force him into it with the ſpur, but by the lightneſs and cheerfulneſs of your body let him paſs of his own accord into a gallop.</p>
               <p>Helps, corrections, and cheriſhings in the ring-turn, are as aforeſaid, the elevation of the voice, and the threatning of the rod, and ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the bridle, are good helps, which you muſt uſe as you muſt the ſpur, rod and leg, for timely due corrections: neither muſt you ever cheriſh without deſert.</p>
               <p>Having made your Horſe gallop as well as trot the large ring, then teach him to ſtop fair, comely, and without danger, after this manner: Firſt, having cheriſht him, bring him into a ſwift trot forward about fifty paces: then draw in your bridle-hand ſtraightly and ſuddenly, which will make him gather up his hinder and fore-legs together, and thereby ſtand ſtill: then eaſe your hand a little, that he may give backward: which if he doth, give him more liberty, and cheriſh him: having given a little reſpit, draw in your bridle-hand, and make him go back three or four paces, at which if he ſtrike, inſtantly eaſe your hand, and draw it up again, letting him come and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:179790:76"/>go till he yield and go backward: but if he refuſe it, let ſome perſon ſtanding by, put him back, and then cheriſh him, that he may know your intention. Thus every time you ſtop, make him retire, till you have perfected him in theſe two leſſons at one time.</p>
               <p>Have a care that the ground be not ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery where you ſtop, but firm and hard, leſt the Horſe apprehenſive of the danger of falling, refuſe to ſtop as you would have him.</p>
               <p>When your Horſe can ſtop well, and retire, you muſt then teach him to advance before, when he ſtoppeth; a leſſon that carrieth much grace and comelineſs therein; it is performed in this manner: After you have ſtopped your Horſe without giving your hand any eaſe, lay the calves of both your Legs hard to his ſides, ſhaking your Rod, and crying, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p, up;</hi> which though he underſtand not at firſt, yet by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent practice, with helps, cheriſhings, and corrections as aforeſaid, he will come to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand your meaning. But be ſure you look narrowly to the comelineſs of the advancing, which conſiſts in taking up his Legs both even together, bending them inward to his body; next, his advance muſt not be too high, for fear of his coming over upon you; but let him couch his hinder-loins cloſe to the ground, but
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:179790:77"/>by no means ſuffer him to ſprawl or paw with his Feet forward. Laſtly, he muſt not advance for his own pleaſure (for that is a great fault) but for yours, according to your will and command.</p>
               <p>If in advancing he riſe too high, ready to come over, or ſprawl, or paw; give him not only your ſpurs both together, but laſh him twice or thrice with your Rod between his ears, and if he advanceth of his own accord, then jerk him over the knees, doing ſo as often as he commits thoſe faults.</p>
               <p>Now the uſe of advancing is this; it not only graceth all his other leſſons, but makes his body agil and nimble, and fits him for ready turning; it is moſt uſed at ſtopping, and then very gracefully.</p>
               <p>In the next place you muſt teach your Horſe to yerk out behind, after this manner: As ſoon as you have made him ſtop, preſently give him a good jerk under his belly, near his flank, which will make him underſtand you in time, though not preſently. At firſt doing, cheriſh him much, and having let him pawſe, make him do it again, till he will do it as often as you will have him: but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, look to the comelineſs of his yerking, for it is not graceful for him to yerk out his
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:179790:77"/>hinder-legs till his fore-legs be above the ground; and ſee that he yerk not one leg far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out than the other, but both even toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not too high, or one leg out whilſt the other is on the ground.</p>
               <p>Helps in yerking, are the conſtant ſtaying of his mouth on the bridle, the ſtroke of the Rod under his belly, or a gentle touch there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of on his Rump.</p>
               <p>If he refuſe to yerk, or doth it diſorderly, then a ſingle ſpur on that ſide that is faulty; and laſtly, continual diſeaſing him till he hath done it.</p>
               <p>Now to teach him to turn readily on both hands, is firſt to bring his large rings into a narrower compaſs, that is about four yards in circumference, walking your Horſe therein with all gentleneſs, and at his own pleaſure, till he is acquainted therewith: After this, carry your bridle-hand conſtant, and ſomewhat ſtraight, the outmoſt Rein ſtraighter than the inmoſt, making the Horſe rather look from the ring, than into it; and thus trot him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, firſt on the one ſide, then on the other, making your changes as aforeſaid. Thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe him an hour and half, then ſtop and make him advance three or four times together, then retire in an even line, afterwards ſtand ſtill and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:179790:78"/>cheriſh him: Having pawſed a while to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover breath, exerciſe him as aforeſaid, ſtill endeavouring to bring his trot to all the ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and loftineſs poſſible, making him do his changes roundly and readily, and cauſing him to lap his outmoſt leg ſo much over his inmoſt leg, that he may cover it more than a foot over: and thus exerciſe him ſeven or eight days, every morning at leaſt three hours, and ſuffer him only to practiſe his former leſſons once in a morning; in this manner you teach your Horſe three leſſons together, the <hi>Terra à Terra,</hi> the <hi>Incavalere,</hi> and the <hi>Chambletta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The turn <hi>Terra à Terra</hi> in the outmoſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the ſtraight ring, and the <hi>Incavalere</hi> and <hi>Chambletta</hi> in the changes, wherein he is forced to lap one leg over another, or elſe to lift up the inmoſt Leg from the ground, whilſt he brings the outmoſt over it: This leſſon is ſo difficult, that a compleat Horſeman ſhould think his Horſe hath never perfectly learn'd it; and therefore he muſt continually practiſe his Horſe in trading, trotting, and galloping theſe nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row rings; and from thence to paſs them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in ground-ſalts, as from taking up his fore-legs from the ground both together, and bringing his hinder-feet in their place, and ſo paſſing the Ring as often as the ſtrength of your Horſe and your own reaſon will allow of.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:179790:78"/>
               <p>Thus you ſee the perfecting your Horſe in the large Ring will eaſily introduce him into the knowledge of the ſtraight Ring, and that brings him to turn perfectly, and ſtopping be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets retiring, and retiring advancing.</p>
               <p>Having brought your Horſe to this perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, take off his <hi>Muſrole</hi> and <hi>Trench,</hi> and in their ſtead put on his head a gentle <hi>Cavezan,</hi> in ſuch manner that it lye on the tender griſſel of his noſe ſomewhat near the upper part of his noſtrils; put in his mouth a ſweet ſmooth cannon-bit, with a plain watering chain, the cheek being of a large ſize, let the <hi>Kirble</hi> be thick, round and large, hanging looſly upon his neather lip, ſo that it may entice him to play therewith.</p>
               <p>Having ſo done, mount, caſting the left rein of your <hi>Cavezan</hi> over the Horſes right ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and bear it with your thumb with the reins of the Bit in your left hand; let the right reins of the <hi>Cavezan</hi> be caſt over his left ſhoulder, and bear it with your Rod in your hand, and ſo trot him forth the firſt morning about two miles in the high-way, making him now and then ſtop and retire, and gather up his head in its due place; the next day bring him to his former large Rings, and perfect him therein with the Bit as you did with the Snaffle in all the foregoing leſſons, which is more eaſily done by
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:179790:79"/>reaſon the Bit is of better command and of ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per correction.</p>
               <p>The next thing we ſhall ſpeak of (to avoid every thing that is not very pertinent to our purpoſe) is the <hi>Turning-Post,</hi> which muſt be ſmooth and ſtrong, and very well fixt in the center of the ſtraight Ring, then cauſing ſome perſon to ſtand at the Poſt, give him the right rein of your <hi>Cavezan</hi> to hold about the Poſt, and ſo walk or trot your Horſe about the ſame as oft as you think fit on your right hand; then change your right rein for your left, and do as before; continue thus doing till your Horſe be perfect in every turn. Having ſo done, teach him to manage (the proper poſture for a ſword) which is thus performed: Cauſe two Rods to be prickt in the earth, at what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as you ſhall think fit from one another; then walk your Horſe in a ſtraight ring about the firſt on your right hand, paſſing him in an even furrow down to the other Rod, and walk about that alſo in a narrow Ring on your left hand, then thruſt him into a gentle gallop down the even furrow, till you come to the firſt Rod, and there make him ſtop (as it were) and advance without pawſe or intermiſſion of time; thruſt him forward again, beat the turn <hi>Terra à Terra</hi> about on your right hand; then gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop forth right to the other Rod, and in the ſame manner beat the turn about on the left
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:179790:79"/>hand, do this as often as you ſhall think con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient: Though there are many ſorts of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, yet I hold but two neceſſary and uſeful, and that is this already deſcribed, called <hi>Terra à Terra,</hi> and <hi>Incavalere</hi> or <hi>Chambletta,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed afore-going. As for the <hi>Career,</hi> I need not ſpeak much thereof; ony this, when you run him forth-right at full ſpeed, ſtop him quickly, ſuddenly, firm and cloſe on his but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tock, and mark that you make not your <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer</hi> too long, nor too ſhort; the one weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, and the other hinders the diſcovery of his true wind and courage; therefore let not the length of your Career extend above ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Yards; and be ſure you give him ſome little warning by your bridle-hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſtart him, and then ſtop him firmly and ſtrongly.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the War-Horſe or great Saddle.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:179790:80"/>
                  <head>Of the Horſe of Pleaſure.</head>
                  <p>IF you will make your Horſe to <hi>bound</hi> aloft, you muſt firſt trot him about ſixteen yards, then ſtop him, and when he hath advanced twice, ſtreighten a little your Bridle-hand, and then give him the even ſtroke of both your ſpurs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether hard, which at firſt will only amaze him, but if he have good mettle and courage, he will at length riſe from the ground by often doing it; if he doth it, though but little, cheriſh him very much, then let him pauſe and give him your ſpurs again, and if he acts according to your deſire, cheriſh him again, make him do thus three or four times a day, till he is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that he will do it at any time at your ſpurs command.</p>
                  <p>Next, teach him to <hi>corvet</hi> thus; hollow the ground a Horſe's length, where two walls joyn together, then place a ſtrong ſmooth Poſt by the ſide of the hollowneſs of a Horſe's length, likewiſe from the wall, then over againſt the Poſt faſten an Iron-ring at the wall; this done, ride your Horſe into the hollow place, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten one of the Reins of the Cavezan to the Ring, and the other about the Poſt; then (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt cheriſhed your Horſe) make him ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:179790:80"/>by the help of the calves of your Legs, twice or thrice together, then let him pauſe; after this (cheriſhing him again) advance him half a ſcore times together, and daily encreaſe his advancings, till you perceive he hath got ſuch a habit therein, that he will by no means go forward, but keeping his ground certain, advance both before and behind of an equal height, and keep juſt and certain time with the motions of your Legs; and if he raiſe his hinder legs not high enough, you muſt have ſome body behind, who having a rod, muſt gently jerk him on the fillets, to make him raiſe his hinder parts. By taking this courſe, in a few days you will ſo teach your Horſe to corvet, that without any helps at any time and place, you may make him cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet at your pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>I need not ſpeak of the <hi>Capriole,</hi> ſince it is the ſame manner of motion as the <hi>Corvet,</hi> only it is done forward, gaining ground in the ſalt, raiſing his hinder parts as high or higher than the foremoſt.</p>
                  <p>If you would have your Horſe go ſide-long on any hand, you muſt draw up your bridle-hand ſtraight, and if you would have him go on the right hand, lay your left rein cloſe to his neck, and the calf of your Leg cloſe to his ſide, making him put his left leg
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:179790:81"/>over his right, then turning your rod back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, gently jerking him on the left hinder thigh, make him bring his hinder parts to the right ſide alſo, and ſtand in an even line as at the firſt, then make him remove his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts more than before, ſo that he may as it were croſs over the even line, and then make him bring his hinder part after, and ſtand in an even line again, and this do till by practice he will move his fore-parts and hinder-parts both together, and go ſide-long as far as you pleaſe; and if you would have him go on the left hand, do as before.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, theſe are the moſt material Leſſons requiſite to be taught any Horſe whatever, either for ſervice or pleaſure, which if taught your Horſe with care and patience, you may conclude your Horſe perfect and compleat. But be ſure you obſerve this, that whatſoever Leſſon your Horſe is moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect in, with that Leſſon ever when you ride begin and end with it; repeating every one over, more or leſs, leſt want of uſe breed forgetfulneſs, and forgetfulneſs abſolute ignorance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:179790:81"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXV. <hi>Of RACING.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOR the compleating a Gentleman's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Art of <hi>Racing,</hi> he is to take ſpecial cognizance of theſe ſubſequent Rules and Orders.</p>
               <p>Firſt, He is to conſider what is the moſt convenient time to take his Horſe from graſs, which is about <hi>Bartholomew-tide,</hi> the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dry, fair, and pleaſant; as ſoon as he is taken up, let him let him ſtand all that night in ſome convenient dry place to empty his body; the next day put him into a ſtable, and feed him with wheat-ſtraw, but no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; for though the Rule be good in taking up Horſes bellies after this manner, yet if you exceed your time in ſo doing, this ſtraw will ſtraighten his guts, heat his liver, and hurt his blood; therefore what you want in ſtraw let it be ſupplied by riding him forth to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter morning and evening, airings, and other moderate exerciſe. And for his food, let it be good old ſweet Hay, and clothe him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the weather and temper of his body; for as the Year grows colder, and thereby you find his hair riſe and ſtare about
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:179790:82"/>his neck, flanks, or other parts, then add a woollen cloth, or more if need require, till his hair fall ſmooth. Where note, <hi>That a rough coat ſhews want of cloth, and a ſmooth coat cloth enough.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Race-horſe ought to be dreſt in his reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing days twice a day, before his morning and evening waterings; and muſt be done after this manner: Curry him from the tips of his ears to the ſetting on of his tail, all his body entirely over with an Iron-Comb, his Legs under the knees and gambrels excepted; then duſt him and curry him high again all over with a round bruſh of briſtles, then duſt him the ſecond time, and rub all the looſe hair off with your hands dipt in fair water, and continue rubbing till he is as dry as at firſt, then rub every part of him with a hair-cloth, and laſtly rub him all over with a white lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth; then pick his eyes, noſtrils, ſheath, cods, tuel, and feet very clean, then cloath him and ſtop him round with wiſps.</p>
               <p>There is no better water for a Race-horſe, than a running River or clear Spring, about a mile and half from the ſtable, near ſome level ground, where you may gallop him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, having ſcop'd him a little, bring him to the water again, then ſcope him and bring him again, ſo often till he refuſe to drink
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:179790:82"/>more for that time; after this, walk him home, clothe and ſtop him up round with great ſoft wiſps, and having ſtood an hour upon the bridle, feed him with ſweet ſound Oats, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dryed by age or art: If your Horſe be low of fleſh, or hath a bad ſtomach, add one third of Beans to two parts of Oats, and that will recover both.</p>
               <p>The next food you ſhall give him ſhall be better and ſtronger, and it is bread, which you muſt make after this manner: take two buſhels of beans, and one of wheat, and grind them together, then boult through a fine Range the quantity of half a buſhel of pure meal, and bake it in three loaves, and the reſt ſift through a Meal-ſieve, and knead it with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and good ſtore of barm, and bake it in great loaves; with the courſer bread feed your Runner in his reſting days, and with the finer againſt the days of his exerciſe and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt labour.</p>
               <p>The times of his feeding, upon the days of his reſt, muſt be after his coming from wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the morning, an hour after mid-day, after his evening watering, and at ten a clock at night; but upon his labouring days, two hours after he is throughly cold, outwardly and inwardly, afterwards as aforeſaid.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:179790:83"/>
               <p>Let his Hay be dry and ſhort; if it be ſweet no matter how courſe it is, for if it be rough it will ſcowre his teeth. As for the proportion of his food, I need not preſcribe a quantity, ſince you muſt allow him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the goodneſs and badneſs of his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</p>
               <p>His exerciſe ought to be thrice a week, and it muſt be more or leſs according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his body; for if it be foul, exerciſe him moderately to break his greaſe; if clean, you may do as you think fit, having a care that you diſcourage him not, nor abate his mettle; and after every exerciſe give him that night, or the next morning, a ſcouring; the beſt I know to purge a Horſe from all greaſe, glut, or filth whatever, is this, take three ounces of Anniſeeds, ſix drams of Cummin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds, a dram and half of Carthamus, two drams of Fenugreek-ſeed, and of Brimſtone an ounce and half; beat all theſe to a fine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſearſe them; then take of Sallet-oyl ſomewhat more than a pint, a pound and half of Honey, and a pottle of white Wine, then with fine white Meal knead it well into a ſtrong paſte, and keep it by you, it will laſt a long time; when you uſe it, diſſolve a ball thereof in a Pail of fair water, and give it him to drink after exerciſe, in the dark, leſt diſcolouring the water, the Horſe refuſe to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:179790:83"/>drink. This is an excellent ſcouring, and a remedy for all internal diſtempers.</p>
               <p>Now after exerciſe, cool him a little abroad before you bring him home, then houſe him and litter him well, rubbing him with dry Clothes till there be never a wet hair about him, then clothe and wiſp him round.</p>
               <p>Here note, before you air your Horſe, it will be requiſite to break a raw Egg into his mouth, for it will add to his wind. If he be fat, air him before Sun-riſe and after Sun-ſet; but if lean, let him have as much comfort of the Sun as you can. Courſing in his clothes ſometimes to make him ſweat is not irrequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, ſo it be moderately done; but when without his clothes, let it be ſharp and ſwift. Let his body be empty before he courſe; and to waſh his tongue and noſtrils with Vinegar, or to piſs in his mouth e're you back him, is wholeſom; having courſt him, clothe him, after he hath taken breath, and ride him home gently.</p>
               <p>To be ſhort, what is here defective in the right ordering of a Race-horſe, your own judgments may eaſily ſupply. All that you have to do, is to be careful when to take him up, how to clothe him and dreſs him, when and how to feed and water, what and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:179790:84"/>how much exerciſe is requiſite either by air<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or by courſing, and his ordering after exerciſe, and what ſcowrings are moſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite; and that I may add a little more to your knowledge, and conclude this ſubject, take theſe general Rules and Inſtructions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Courſe not your Horſe hard at leaſt four or five days before you run your match, leſt the ſoarneſs of his Limbs abate his ſpeed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Except your Horſe be a foul feeder muzzle him not above two or three Nights before his match, and the Night before his bloody courſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As you give your Horſe gentle cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, give him ſharp ones too, that he may as well find comfort as diſpleaſure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Upon the match-day let your Horſe be empty, and that he take his reſt undiſturbed till you lead him out.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Shoo your Horſe ever a day before you run him, that the pain of the Hammers knocks may be out of his Feet.</p>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:179790:84"/>
               <p n="6">6. Saddle your Horſe on the Race-day in the ſtable before you lead him forth, and fix both the Pannel and the Girths to his back and ſides with Shoo-makers wax, to prevent all dangers.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Lead your Horſe to his courſe with all gentleneſs, and give him leave to ſmell to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Horſes dung, that thereby he may be enticed to ſtole and empty his body as he goes.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Laſtly, When you come to the place where you muſt ſtart, firſt rub his limbs well, then uncloath him, then take his back, and the word given, ſtart him with all gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and quietneſs that may, leſt doing any thing raſhly, you choak him in his own wind.</p>
               <p>A Race-horſe ought to have all the fineſt ſhapes that may be, but above all things he muſt be nimble, quick, and fiery, apt to flye with the leaſt motion. Long ſhapes are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerably good, for though they ſhew weakneſs, yet they aſſure ſudden ſpeed. The beſt horſe for this uſe is the <hi>Arabian Barbary,</hi> or his Baſtard; not but <hi>Gennets</hi> are good, but the <hi>Turks</hi> much better.</p>
               <p>Having laid you down all theſe advantages
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:179790:85"/>for ordering your Racer, from his taking up, to the day of his running, I hope you will make ſuch good uſe of them, that if upon an equal match you ſhould lay your money on the heels of your Horſe thus ordered, he ſhall be ſo far from kicking away his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſtake, that the nimbleneſs of his feet ſhall make it double.</p>
               <p>I might here inſert the many ſubtilties and tricks there are uſed in making a Match, the craft of the Betters, with the knavery of the Riders, but that they are now too generally known by the woful experience of too many <hi>Racing-loſers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:179790:85"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXVI. <hi>Of ARCHERY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARchery,</hi> as it is a recreation, ſo it hath been heretofore, and is ſtill in ſome parts of the World very uſeful in military affairs, but now quite laid aſide by <hi>Engliſh</hi> men for fighting, there being found out more dextrous and ſpeedy ways to kill and deſtroy one another.</p>
               <p>Yet it is not ſo laid aſide, but that it is uſed by ſome for paſtime, either at Buts or Rovers, and ſhould not be forgotten by Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, as appears by the continuance of that ancient cuſtom for every Lord Mayor to ſee the prize performed by ſhooting annually with the pound Arrow.</p>
               <p>Certainly this ſhooting in the long Bow is very healthful for the body, by extending the Limbs, and making them pliant; and it hath been neceſſary for a Commonwealth, in the defence and preſervation of the Country; but ſince it is ſo little uſed now adays, I ſhall abbreviate my diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>There are theſe Rules to be obſerved for ſhooting in the Long-bow.</p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:179790:86"/>
               <p>Firſt, He muſt have a good eye to behold and diſcern his mark; and knowing-judgment to underſtand the diſtance of ground, to take the true advantage of a ſide-wind, and to know in what compaſs his Arrow muſt fly; and a quick dexterity, to give his ſhaft a ſtrong, ſharp, and ſudden looſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He muſt in the action it ſelf ſtand fair and upright with his body; his left foot a convenient ſtride before his right, both his hams ſtiff, his left arm holding his Bow in the midſt, ſtretcht ſtraight out, and his right arm with his firſt three fingers and his thumb drawing the ſtring to his right ear, the notch of his Arrow reſting between his fore-finger and middle-finger of his right hand, and the ſteel of his Arrow below the feathers upon the middle knuckle of his fore-finger on his left hand; he ſhall draw his Arrow cloſe up to the head, and deliver on the inſtant, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hanging on the ſtring.</p>
               <p>The beſt Bow is either <hi>Spaniſh</hi> or <hi>Engliſh</hi> Yew; the beſt Shaft is of Burch, Sugar-cheſt, or Brazel, and the beſt Feathers gray or white.</p>
               <p>There are three <hi>Marks</hi> to ſhoot at, <hi>Buts, Pricks,</hi> or <hi>Rovers.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:179790:86"/>
               <p>The firſt is a level mark, and therefore you muſt have a ſtrong Arrow with a broad feather.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is a mark of ſome compaſs, yet moſt certain in the diſtance, therefore you muſt have nimble ſtrong Arrows, with a middle feather, all of one weight and fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The laſt; which is the <hi>Rover,</hi> is uncertain, ſometimes longer, ſometimes ſhorter, and therefore requires Arrows lighter or heavier, according to the diſtance of ſhooting.</p>
               <p>If you want ſtrength, by debilitation in the Arm or Back, you may reap the ſame pleaſure by uſing the Croſs-Bow, with which you may ſhoot at <hi>Buts, Pricks,</hi> or <hi>Rovers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:179790:87"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXVII. <hi>Of Cock-Fighting.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COcking is a ſport or paſtime ſo full of delight and pleaſure, that I know not any Game in that reſpect is to be preferred before it, and ſince the <hi>Fighting-Cock</hi> hath gain'd ſo great an eſtimation among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, in reſpect to this noble recreation I ſhall here propoſe it before all the other Games of which I have afore ſuccinctly diſcourſed; that therefore I may methodically give in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to ſuch as are unexperienced, and add more knowledge to ſuch who have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready gain'd a competent proficiency in this pleaſing Art, I ſhall as briefly as I can give you information how you ſhall chuſe, breed, and diet the <hi>Fighting-Cock,</hi> with what choice Secrets are thereunto belonging, in order thus.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:179790:87"/>
                  <head>Of the Choice of the Fighting-Cock.</head>
                  <p>IN the election of a <hi>Fighting-Cock</hi> there are Four things principally to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and they are <hi>Shape, Colour, Courage,</hi> and <hi>Sharp-heel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, as to his <hi>ſhape,</hi> you muſt not chuſe him neither too ſmall, nor too large; the firſt is weak and tedious in his fighting, and the other unweildy and not active, and both very difficult to be matched; wherefore the middle-ſiz'd Cock is the proper choice for your purpoſe, being eaſily matcht, and is both ſtrong and nimble.</p>
                  <p>His Head ought to be ſmall, with a quick large eye, and a ſtrong back, and (as Maſter <hi>Markham</hi> obſerves) muſt be crookt and big at the ſetting on, and in colour ſuitable to the plume of his Feathers, whether black, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low or reddiſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The beam of his Leg muſt be very ſtrong, and according to his plume, blew, gray, or yellow, his Spurs rough, long, and ſharp, a little bending and looking inward.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, his <hi>Colour</hi> ought to be either
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:179790:88"/>gray, yellow, or red, with a black breaſt; not but that there are many other colour'd pyles very excellent good, which you muſt find out by practice and obſervation, but the three former by the experience of moſt found ever the beſt, the pide pyle may paſs indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, but the white and dun are rarely found good for any thing.</p>
                  <p>Here note, That if your Cocks neck be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with a ſcarlet complexion it is a ſign he is ſtrong, luſty and couragious; but on the contrary, if pale and wan, it denotes the Cock to be faint, and in health defective.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, you may know his courage by his proud upright ſtanding, and ſtately tread in walking, and if he croweth very frequently in the Pen, it is a couragious demonſtration.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly and laſtly, his narrow-heel or ſharpneſs of heel is known no other-ways than by obſervation in fighting, and that is, when upon every riſing he ſo hits that he extracts blood from his opponent, gilding his Spurs continually and every blow threatning immediate death to his adverſary.</p>
                  <p>Here note, That it is the opinion of the beſt <hi>Cock-Masters,</hi> that a ſharp-heel'd Cock though he be ſomewhat falſe, is better than a
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:179790:88"/>true Cock with a dull heel; and the reaſon is this, the one fights long but ſeldom wounds, the other carrieth a heel ſo fatal that every moment produceth an expectation of the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tails concluſion; and though he is not ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as to endure the utmoſt hewing, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly there is little occaſion for it, being a quick diſpatcher of his buſineſs; now ſhould your Cock prove both hardy and narrow-heel'd, he is then the beſt Cock you can make choice of.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, make your choice of ſuch a one that is of <hi>Shape</hi> ſtrong, of <hi>Colour</hi> good, of <hi>Valour</hi> true, and of <hi>Heel</hi> ſharp and ready.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to breed a Cock of the Game.</head>
                  <p>WHatever you do, let your Hen be of a good complexion, that is to ſay, rightly plumed, as black, brown, ſpeckt, gray, griſſel, or yellowiſh; theſe are the right and proper colours for a Hen of the Game; and if ſhe be tufted on the crown it is ſo much the better, for that argues courage and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and if ſhe have the addition of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons they conduce very much to her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:179790:89"/>
                  <p>Let her body be large and well poked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind for the production of large Eggs; you will do well to obſerve how ſhe behaveth her ſelf to her Chickens, whether friendly or fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and take eſpecial notice of her car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and deportment among other Hens, if ſhe will receive abuſes from them without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or ſhow any thing of Cowardice, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue her not, for you may aſſure your ſelf her Chickens will be good for nothing.</p>
                  <p>By the way take this obſervation, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the opinions of the beſt <hi>Cock-Maſters</hi> both ancient and modern, that a right Hen of the Game from a Dunghill-Cock will bring forth very good Chickens, but the beſt Cock from a Dunghill-Hen will never get a Bird that's fit for the Game: wherefore if you intend to have a good breed get perfect Cocks for your perfect Hens.</p>
                  <p>The beſt ſeaſon for breeding is from the encreaſe of the Moon in <hi>February,</hi> to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the ſame in <hi>March.</hi> Let her Neſt be ſo placed that ſhe may not be diſturbed by the ſight of any other Fowl, which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſo raiſeth her choler that the Eggs are in great danger; let the compoſure of her Neſt be made of ſoft ſweet ſtraw, and let it ſtand in ſome warm place, for ſhe is a Bird that is very tender.</p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:179790:89"/>
                  <p>The next thing that you are to obſerve is, whether ſhe turn her Eggs often or not, if ſhe is remiſs therein, you muſt ſupply her du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but if ſhe ſave you the labour, prize her more than ordinary. And that ſhe may not ſtraggle too far from her Eggs being neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to ſeek abroad for food, and ſo cool her Eggs, it will be altogether neceſſary for you to ſet by her ſuch neceſſary food as you ſhall think fit with ſome fair water; and that ſhe may bathe and trim her ſelf at her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: in the place where ſhe ſiteth let there be ſand, gravel and aſhes finely ſifted.</p>
                  <p>The Hen hatcheth her Chickens commonly after one and twenty days; obſerve in the hatching to take thoſe newly hatched, and wrapping them in wool keep them warm by a fire-ſide till the reſt are diſcloſed; being all hatcht put them under the Hen, and be ſure to keep her warm, and ſuffer not your Hen and Chickens to ſtraggle abroad till they are above three weeks old; and let the room wherein they walk be boarded, for all other Flours are either too moiſt or too cold.</p>
                  <p>Let their Walk be in ſome Graſs-court or Green-place, after they are a month old, that they may have the benefit of feeding on Worms, and now and then to ſcowre them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with Graſs and Chick-weed, but be
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:179790:90"/>careful they come not near Puddles or filthy places, for they engender in birds of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture venemous diſtempers, which commonly prove fatal; for the prevention of ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies by way of antidote give them every morning before they range abroad, the blades of Leeks chopt or minced ſmall and mingled among their uſual diet; alſo it will be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to perfume their room with burnt Peny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>royal or Roſemary.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve to take this courſe till their Sexes are diſtinguiſhable; as ſoon as the Comb or Wattles are diſcernable, or plainly viſible to the eye, cut them away, and anoint the ſore place with ſweet butter, till it be whole. The reaſons why their Combs or Wattles ſhould be cut ſo ſoon, are theſe, Firſt if you let them grow till they arrive to their full bigneſs, and then cut them, there will follow a great flux of blood, and the leaſt loſs of blood in feather'd fowl is very dangerous; if much, frequently mortal; moreover to let them grow thus, cauſeth gouty thick heads, with great lumps; whereas if you take them off betime as aforeſaid, they will have heads finely ſmall, ſmooth and ſlender.</p>
                  <p>The time of the ſeparation of the Cock-Chickens is when they begin to fight with and peck one another, till which time you
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:179790:90"/>may let them walk with the Hen promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly together, but afterwards let their Walks be apart, and that Walk is beſt where he may ſecurely and privately enjoy his Hens without the diſturbance and annoyance of other Cocks, for which purpoſe walks at Wind-mills, Water-mills, Grange-houſes, Lodges in Parks, and Coney-Warrens, are very good Walks, but that the later is ſomewhat dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, being too frequently haunted with Pole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cats, and other vermin.</p>
                  <p>Let the place of feeding be as near as you can on ſoft dry ground, or on boards if the place be harder, as on paved earth, or floors plaiſter'd, it will ſo weaken and blunt their beaks, that they will be unable to hold faſt.</p>
                  <p>Here note, That any white Corn is good for a Cock in his Walk, and ſo are white-bread toſts ſteeped in drink, or man's urine, which will both ſcowre and cool them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly.</p>
                  <p>Let not above three Hens walk with your Cock, for ſhould you ſuffer more, they will tread too much by reaſon of the hear of their nature, and by often treading they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their ſtrength, and become ſo debilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that though they have courage enough, yet they have not ſtrength to perform their
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:179790:91"/>parts as they ought to do in a battel.</p>
                  <p>Obſerve the crowing of your Chickens; if you find them crow too ſoon, that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſix months old, or unſeaſonably, and that their crowing is clear and loud, fit them as ſoon as you can for the Pot or Spit, for they are infallible ſigns of cowardiſe and falſhood: on the contrary the true and perfect Cock is long before he obtains his voice, and when he hath got it, obſerves his hours with the beſt judgment.</p>
                  <p>Suffer not your Cock to fight a battel till he is compleat and perfect in every member, and that is when he is two years old; for to fight him when his Spurs are but warts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively, is no ſign of diſcretion, for you may then probably know his valour and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, but you cannot know his worth and goodneſs.</p>
                  <p>In eſpecial manner take care that your Cocks rooſting-Perch be not too ſmall in the gripe, or ſo ill placed that he cannot ſit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtradling, or if it be crooked it is bad, for by theſe means, a Cock will be uneven heel'd, and conſequently no good ſtriker; and know that a Perch either maketh or marreth a Cock; to remedy or prevent ſuch faults, is to have in your rooſt a row of little Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:179790:91"/>about eight inches in length, and ten inches from the ground, that the Cock may with more facility aſcend, and being up, is forced to keep his Legs near together; and here take notice of this maxim amongſt the beſt <hi>Cock-breeders, That the Cock which is a cloſe ſitter, is ever a narrow striker.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the foot-ſtool of the Perch be round and ſmooth about the thickneſs of a man's arm, or if you will have the beſt form for a Perch, go viſit the houſes of the moſt skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cock-maſters, and from them all gather what is moſt neceſſary for your purpoſe by making inſpection into their feeding-pens and other places; and let the ground underneath the Perch be ſoft, for otherwiſe when he leaps down, he will be apt on a rough and hard ground to hurt his feet, inſomuch that they will grow knotty and gouty.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of dieting and ordering a Cock for Battel.</head>
                  <p>IN the dieting and ordering of a Cock for Battail conſiſteth all the ſubſtance of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and pleaſure; and therefore your cunning Cock-merchants are very cautious of divulg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecrets (as they call them) of diet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:179790:92"/>for on that depends the winning or lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Battel, they knowing very well that the beſt Cock undieted is unable to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the worſt that is dieted; let others be as niggardly as they pleaſe of their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and obſervations, for my part I ſhall be free and ſcorn to conceal any thing that may tend to the propagation of the art and myſtery of Cock fighting; wherefore as to the dieting and ordering of fighting Cocks take theſe Inſtructions following.</p>
                  <p>The time of taking up your Cocks is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the latter end of <hi>August,</hi> for from that time till the latter end of <hi>May</hi> Cocking is ſeaſonable and in requeſt, the Summer ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being improper by reaſon of its great heat.</p>
                  <p>Having taken them up, view them well, and ſee that they are ſound, hard feather'd, and full ſumm'd, that is having all their fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers compleat, then put them into ſeveral pens, having a moving Perch therein, to ſet it at which corner of the perch you think moſt convenient; the faſhion and form of theſe pens you may have at the houſe of any Cocker, and therefore I ſhall give you no directions how to make them; only be advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to keep your Pens clean, and let not your Cocks want either meat or water.</p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:179790:92"/>
                  <p>For the firſt four days after your Cock is pend, feed him with the crumb of old Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet cut into ſquare bits about a handful at a time, and feed him thrice a day therewith, that is at Sun-riſing, when the Sun is in his Meridian, and at Sun-ſetting, and let his wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be from the coldeſt Spring you can get it.</p>
                  <p>Having fed your Cock thus four days, or ſo long till you think he hath purg'd himſelf of his corn, worms, gravel, and other coarſe feeding, then in the morning take him out of the Pen and let him <hi>Sparr</hi> a while with another Cock. <hi>Sparring</hi> is after this manner: Cover each of your Cocks heels with a pair of <hi>Hots</hi> made of bombaſted rolls of Leather, ſo covering the Spurs that they cannot bruiſe or wound one another, and ſo ſetting them down on ſtraw in a room, or green-graſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, let them fight a good while, but by no means ſuffer them to draw blood of one another; the benefit that accrues hereby is this, it heateth and chafeth their bodies, and it breaketh the fat and the glut that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, and adapts it for purgation.</p>
                  <p>Having ſparred as much as is ſufficient, which you may know when you ſee them pant and grow weary, then take them up, and taking off their <hi>Hots</hi> give them a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoretick
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:179790:93"/>or ſweating after this manner: You muſt put them in deep ſtraw-baskets made for the purpoſe, or for want of them take a couple of Cocking-bags and fill theſe with ſtraw half ways, then put in your Cocks ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, and cover them over with ſtraw to the top, then ſhut down the lids and let them ſweat; but do not forget to give them firſt ſome white Sugar-candy, chopt Roſemary, and Butter mingled and incorporated together, let the quantity be about the bigneſs of a Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nut, by ſo doing you will cleanſe him of his greaſe, increaſe his ſtrength, and prolong his breath.</p>
                  <p>Towards four or five a clock in the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing take them out of their Stoves, and having lickt their eyes and head with your tongue, put them into their Pens, and having fil'ed their Troughs with ſquare-cut-manchet, piſs therein, and let them feed whilſt the Urine is hot; for this will cauſe their ſcouring to work, and will wonderfully cleanſe both head and body.</p>
                  <p>After this, diet your Cocks with a Bread made after this manner: Of Wheat-meal, and Oat-meal Flower, take of each a Gallon, and knead them into a ſtiff paſte, with Ale, the whites of half a ſcore Eggs, and ſome Butter; having wrought the Dow very well, make it
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:179790:93"/>into broad thick Cakes, and when they are four days old, cut them into ſquare pieces; I will not adviſe you to uſe (as ſome impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently do) Liquoriſh, Anniſeeds, or rather hot Spices among your foreſaid Ingredients; for they will make a Cock ſo hot at the heart, that upon the concluding of the Battel, he will be ſuffocated and overcome with his own heat. In ſhort, that food is beſt which is moſt conſentaneous to his own natural feeding.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond day after his <hi>ſparring,</hi> take your Cock into a fair green Cloſe, and having a Dunghil Cock in your arms, ſhow it him, and then run from him, that thereby you may intice him to follow, you permitting him to have now and then a blow, and thus chace him up and down about half an hour; when he begins to pant, being well heated, take him up and carry him home, and give him this ſcouring; take half a pound of freſh But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and beat it in a Mortar with the leaves of <hi>Herb of Grace, Hyſop</hi> and <hi>Roſemary,</hi> till they all look like a green Salve, give him thereof a piece as big as a Walnut, and then ſtove him as aforeſaid till evening, and then feed him according to former preſcription.</p>
                  <p>The next day let him ſeed and reſt, and ſpar him the next day after; thus do every other
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:179790:94"/>day for the firſt fortnight, either <hi>ſparring</hi> or <hi>chaſing,</hi> and after every heat a ſcowring, which will keep him from being faint and purſie.</p>
                  <p>Feed him the ſecond fortnight as you did the firſt, but you muſt not <hi>ſpar</hi> him or <hi>chaſe</hi> him above twice a week, obſerving ſtill, that if you heat him much, you muſt ſtove him long and give him a greater quantity of ſcow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. When well in breath, ſlight heats, ſmall ſcowrings, and little ſtoving will ſerve the turn.</p>
                  <p>The third fortnight (which is a time ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for ordering a Cock for the Battel) you muſt feed him as aforeſaid, but you muſt not <hi>ſpar</hi> him at all for fear of making his head ſore, but you may moderately chaſe him twice or thrice in that time as aforeſaid, then give him his ſcowring rolled well in brown Sugar-Candy which will prevent the ſcowring from making the Cock ſick; now may you let him fight, having firſt let him reſt four days, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that he come empty into the Pit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:179790:94"/>
                  <head>The right way of Cock-matching.</head>
                  <p>OF all things have a ſpecial care how you match your Cock; for ſhould you feed your Cock with never ſo much circumſpect care and prudence, it will avail nothing if your Cock be over-matcht.</p>
                  <p>In matching, take notice of theſe two things; firſt, the length of Cocks, ſecondly, the ſtrength of Cocks; for the length, if your Adverſaries Cock be too long, yours ſhall hardly catch his head, and ſo be incapable of indangering eye or life; and if he be the ſtronger, he will overbear your Cock, and not ſuffer him to riſe or ſtrike with any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
                  <p>The length you may judge of by the eye, when you gripe the Cock by the waſte, and make him ſhoot out his legs, in which poſture you ſhall ſee the utmoſt of his height, and ſo compare them together, being herein gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by your judgment, his ſtrength is known by the thickneſs of his body. Take this for a Rule, <hi>That a Cock is ever held the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, which is the largest in the garth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:179790:95"/>
                  <p>You ſhall know the dimenſion of the <hi>garth</hi> by the meaſure of your hands, griping the Cock about from the points of your great finger to the joynts of your thumbs, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe advantages by no means give your Adverſary; if you doubt loſs in the one, be ſure to gain in the other: for the weak long Cock will riſe at more eaſe, and the ſhort ſtrong Cock will give the ſurer blow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to prepare Cocks for Fight.</head>
                  <p>SInce all Cocks are not caſt in one mould, the advantages on either ſide muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled by matching; and having made an equal Match as near as you can, you muſt thus prepare him to fight:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, with a pair of fine Cock-ſhears cut all his main off cloſe unto his neck, from the head to the ſetting on of the ſhoulders; Secondly, clip off all the feathers from the tail cloſe to his rump, the redder it appears the better is the Cock in condition. Thirdly, take his wings and ſpread them forth by the length of the firſt riſing feather, and clip the reſt ſlope-wiſe with ſharp points, that in his riſing he may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with endanger an eye of his adverſary. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſcrape, ſmooth, and ſharpen his Spurs with a Pen-knife. Fifthly and laſtly, ſee that there be no feathers on the Crown of his head for
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:179790:95"/>his adverſary to take hold of; then with your ſpittle, moiſtning his head all over, turn him into the Pit to move his fortune.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How to order Cocks after Battel, and how to cure wounds.</head>
                  <p>THe Battel being ended, immediately ſearch your Cocks wounds, as many as you can find, ſuck the blood out of them, then waſh them well with warm urine, and that will keep them from rankling; after this give him a roll or two of your beſt ſcowring, and ſo ſtove him up as hot as you can for that night; in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, if you find his head ſwell'd, you muſt ſuck his wounds again, and bathe them again with warm urine, then take the powder of herb <hi>Robert,</hi> and put it into a fine bag, and pounce his wounds therewith; after this give him a good handful of bread to eat out of warm urine, and ſo put him into the ſtove again, and let him not feel the Air till the ſwelling be fallen.</p>
                  <p>If he hath received any hurt in his eye, then take a leaf or two of right ground Ivy, that which grows in little tufts in the bottom of Hedges, and hath a little rough leaf; I ſay, take this Ivy and chew it in your mouth, and ſpit the juyce into the eye of the Cock, and this
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:179790:96"/>will not only cure the preſent Malady, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the growth of Films, Haws, Warts, or the like, deſtructive to the eye-ſight.</p>
                  <p>If after you have put out your wounded Cocks to their Walks, and viſiting them a Month or two after, if you find about their head any ſwollen bunches hard and blackiſh at one end, you may then conclude in ſuch bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches there are unſound cores, which muſt be opened and cruſht out with your thumbs; and after this, you muſt ſuck out the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and filling the holes full of freſh Butter, you need not doubt a Cure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Cures for ſome Distempers in a Cock, Chick, or Hen o'th' Game.</head>
                  <p>THe Pip is a white thin ſcale growing on the tip of the tongue, by which means Poultry in general cannot feed, it is very viſible to the eye, and proceedeth from foul feeding or want of water; it is cured by pulling off the ſcales with your nail, and rubbing the tongue with ſalt.</p>
                  <p>The Roup is a filthy byle or ſwelling on the rump of the Cock, Hen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and will corrupt the whole body. It is known by the ſtaring and turning back of the feathers. For the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:179790:96"/>cure, you muſt pull away the feathers, and open the ſore to thruſt out the core, then waſh the place with water and ſalt, the Cure is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
                  <p>If your Cock or Hen have the flux which hapneth by eating too much moiſt meat, you may cure them by giving them ſcalded Peaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bran; but if they cannot <hi>mute,</hi> anoint their vents, and give them corn ſteept in Man's Urine.</p>
                  <p>Lice is a common infirmity among them, proceeding from corrupt food, or for want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of bathing in Sand-Aſhes or the like; this Malady you muſt cure by taking Pepper beaten to powder, and mixing it with warm water, waſh them therewith. If they are troubled with ſore eyes, take a leaf or two of ground-Ivy, and chawing it well in your mouth, ſpit the juyce thereof into their eyes, and it will preſently heal. What other infirmities are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to theſe Birds of Game I ſhall leave, and their Cures, to your own practice and obſervation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:179790:97"/>
                  <head>An excellent and elegant COPY of VERSES upon two <hi>Cock's fighting,</hi> by Dr. <hi>R. Wild.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>GO you tame Gallants, you that have a name,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And would accounted be Cocks of the Game;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That have brave Spurs to ſhew for't, and can crow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And count all Dunghill breed, that cannot ſhow</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such painted plumes as yours, which think on't vice</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With Cock-like luſt to tread your Cockatrice;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though Peacocks, Woodcocks, Weathercocks you be</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If y'are not fighting-Cocks, y'are not for me.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I of two feather Combatants will write,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And he that means to th' life to expreſs their fight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Muſt make his ink the blood which they did ſpill.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And from their dying wings muſt take his quill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No ſooner were the doubtful people ſet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The match made up, and all that would had bet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ſtraight the skilful Judges of the Play</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Brought forth their ſharp heel'd Warriors, and they</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Were both in linnen bags, as if 'twere meet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Before they dy'd to have their winding-ſheet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Into the Pit they're brought, and being there</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Stage, the</hi> Norfolk Chanticleer</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Looks ſtoutly at his ne're before ſeen foe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And like a Challenger began to crow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And clap his wings as if he would diſplay</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His warlike colours, which were black and gray.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mean time the wary</hi> Wisbich <hi>walks and breathes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His active body, and in fury wreathes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="173" facs="tcp:179790:97"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His comely creſt; and often looking down,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He beats his angry beak upon the ground.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This done, they meet, not like that coward breed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Aeſop<hi>'s; theſe can better fight than feed.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They ſcorn the Dunghil; 'tis their only prize,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To dig for Pearls within each others eyes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They fought ſo nimbly that 'twas hard to know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To th' skilful whether they did fight or no,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If that the blood which dy'd the fatal floor</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Had not born witneſs of 't. Yet fought they more,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As if each wound were but a ſpur to prick</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their fury forward. Lightning's not more quick</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or red, than were their eyes; 'twas hard to know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whether 'twas blood or anger made them ſo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'm ſure they had been out, had they not ſtood</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>More ſafe, being wall'd in each others blood.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus they vy'd blows; but yet, alas at length,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Although their courage were full try'd, their ſtrength</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And blood began to ebb. You that have ſeen</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A watery combat on the Sea, between</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Two angry roaring boiling billows, how</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They march and meet, and daſh their curled brow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Swelling like graves, as though they did intend</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>T' intomb each other, ere the quarrel end;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But when the wind is down, and bluſtring wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They are made friends, and ſweetly run together,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>May think theſe Champions ſuch; their blood grows low,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And they which leapt but now, now ſcarce can go,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:179790:98"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For having left th' advantage of the heel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drunk with each others blood, they only reel;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And yet they would fain fight; they came ſo near</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Methought they meant into each others ear</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To whiſper wounds; and when they could not riſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They lay and lookt blows int' each others eyes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But now the Tragick part! After this fit</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When</hi> Norfolk <hi>Cock had got the beſt of it,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Wisbich <hi>lay a dying, ſo that none,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though ſober, but might venture ſeven to one;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Contracting, like a dying Taper, all</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His ſtrength, intending with the blow to fall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He ſtruggles up, and having taken wind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ventures a blow, and ſtrikes the other blind.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And now poor</hi> Norfolk <hi>having loſt his eyes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fights, guided only by antipathies.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With him, alas, the Proverb is not true,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The blows his eyes ne're ſaw, his heart muſt rue</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At laſt by chance he ſtumbling on his foe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Not having any ſtrength to give a blow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He falls upon him with his wounded head,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And makes his Conquerors wings his feather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His friends ran in, and being very chary,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sent in all haſte to call a Pothecary;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But all in vain, his body did ſo bliſter,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That 'twas not capable of any cliſter.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phyſick's in vain, and 'twill not him reſtore.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alas poor Cock he was let blood before.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then finding himſelf weak, op'ning his bill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>He calls a Scrivener, and thus makes his Will:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="175" facs="tcp:179790:98"/>
                     <l>Imp. <hi>firſt of all, let never be forgot.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My body freely I bequeath to th' pot</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Decently to be boil'd, and for its Tomb</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let it be buried in ſome hungry Womb.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Item, <hi>For Executors I'le have none,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But he that on my ſide laid ſeven to one,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, like a Gentleman that he may live,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To him and to his heirs, my Comb I give,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Together with my brains, that all may know,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That oftentimes his brains did uſe to crow.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Item. <hi>For comfort of thoſe weaker ones,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whoſe wives complain of, let them have my ſtones.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For Ladies that are light, it is my will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Feathers make a Fan. And for my Bill</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'le give a Taylor: but faith 'tis ſo ſhort</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I am afraid he'l rather curſe me for't.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And for that worthy Doctors ſake, who meant</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To give me a Cliſter, let my Rump be ſent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Laſtly, <hi>Becauſe I find my ſelf decay,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I yield and give to</hi> Wisbich <hi>Cock the Day.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179790:99"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:179790:99"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
